<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus sarawakensis</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Beccari, Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 208 (1902)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 335 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 45: 87 (1990)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 91 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus scabrifolius</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 56 (1913)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 121 (1984)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Of Sarawak</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Uwai Buloh Giok (Dus.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering rattan climbing to 30 m tall; stems without sheaths to 4-5 mm diam., with sheaths to 13 mm diam., internodes to 10 cm long. Sheaths dark green, smooth, sometimes with a few scattered spines to 4 mm; knee conspicuous; ocrea forming a low membranous ridge c. 1 mm high. Flagellum to 1.5 m. Leaf cirrate to 70 cm including the petiole to 11 cm; petiole very sparsely armed with short lateral spines; rachis covered in sparse rusty-coloured hairs; leaflets c. 10-22 on each side of the rachis, regularly or slightly irregularly arranged, lanceolate, the longest to 18 &#215; 1.5 cm, densely covered in minute rigid bristles on both surfaces giving the leaflets a scabrid feel. Inflorescences to 1 m, with only a small flagellum, with c. 5 strongly curved partial inflorescences bearing strongly curved rachillae; rachillae bearing conspicuous cups of bracteoles and rather distant flowers; female rachillae to 3.5 cm. Almost mature fruit elongate, c. 13 &#215; 6 mm, tipped with a beak to 1 &#215; 1 mm, and covered in 15 vertical rows of pale brown scales with dark tips. Seed fusiform with disgustingly sour and foetid sarcotesta; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf pinnate with c. 5 hairy leaflets on each side of the rachis.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Recorded from Tasek Merimbun. Elsewhere in Sabah and Sarawak. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>A good slender cane used for binding.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This is a beautiful slender species with very neat short leaflets. It resembles C. pilosellus and C. hispidulus.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TUT: Rambai, Tasek Merimbun, Bernstein 337.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>