<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sabah. Sabah Forest Records 13.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1984</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Sabah Forest Department</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus elopurensis</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 36: 787 (1982)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>From Elopura, the old district name for the Sandakan area</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering slender rattan climbing to c 5 m only; stem without sheaths to 6 mm, with sheaths to 10 mm; internodes to 22 cm. Sheaths dull green, longitudinally striate, covered In grey indumentum, unarmed or with very few spines to 8 mm. Knee conspicuous, round, &#177; glabrous. Ocrea conspicuous, developed as a triangular limb to 7 cm opposite the petiole. Flagellum to 1 m. Leaf ecirrate to 60 cm including petiole,- petiole to 20 cm, sometimes much less, but always conspicuous, densely covered in grey floccose indumentum; leaflets dark green, usually 2 pairs only or 2 pairs and a single leaflet, or 3 pairs; terminal leaflet pair joined for c 5/6 their length forming a terminal flabellum to 35 x 10 cm; lateral leaflets usually close to the terminal pair, to 35 x 5 cm; young leaves pinkish. Male inflorescence to 1.5, m with 8 partial inflorescences, the first borne about 80 cm above the base; bracts with expanded limb to 16 x 1 cm bearing scattered spines; axis of partial inflorescence to 9 cm and rachillae to 12 x 0.2 cm, crimson when fresh. Female inflorescence known only in dead state, superficially similar to the male, with rachillae much shorter to 5 x 0.3 cm. Fruit not known. (Fig. 70)</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Confined to the lowlands of the eastern part of Sabah; endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known: probably with qualities similar to those of C. javensis.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. elopurensis is a striking rattan of the alluvial flats of the lowlands of Sabah; it is nowhere very abundant. It may easily be distinguished by the distinctive leaf with conspicuous petiole and few large leaflets crowded at the rachis tip.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>