<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus gonospermus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 202 (1902</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 190 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 130 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 131 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Angled seed</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering, very slender rattan climbing to 10 m; stem without sheaths to 8 mm diam. (usually less), with sheaths to 12 mm diam., internodes 5-12 cm long. Sheaths dark green, &#177; unarmed or armed with scattered short bulbous-based spines to 4 mm, sparse deciduous brown indumentum sometimes present; knee conspicuous; ocrea inconspicuous. Flagellum to 1.5 m. Leaf ecirrate to c. 60 cm including petiole to 25 cm; petiole sparsely armed with reflexed spines; leaflets 3-4 (rarely 5) on each side of the rachis, the apical two close together, the proximal 1 or 2 close together but distant from the apical, lanceolate to spathulate, usually &#177; cucullate and with a pronounced drip-tip, rarely linear and lacking a drip-tip, the longest to 30 &#215; 3.5 cm, the apical pair fused for up to 1/2 their length, dull green, &#177; unarmed. Inflorescences shorter than the leaves, without terminal flagellum, rarely exceeding 40 cm; partial inflorescences up to 5, each subtended by a loosely tubular, rather conspicuously bulbous-spiny bract, the male branching to 3 orders, the female to 2, the rachillae very short, somewhat condensed, the bracteoles forming rather large cups. Mature fruit usually 2-3 only per infructescence, large, rounded, c. 20 mm diam., tipped with a conical beak and covered in 16 vertical rows of smooth unchannelled pale brown scales with darker tips. Seed irregularly globular, acutely angled, 10-12 mm diam.; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 47).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Found scattered throughout Brunei, but always rare. Elsewhere in Sabah and Sarawak. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known, though the fruit contains a thick sweet sarcotesta, good to eat.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. gonospermus has been collected in lowland and hill dipterocarp forest</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Labi, Dransfield J. 6528; Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6613; Sungai Liang, Andulau F.R, Wong 490. TEM: Amo, Bukit Belalong, Stockdale 58.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>