<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The lost palm of Fiji – a resolution of Goniocladus and a preliminary cladistic analysis of Physokentia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Fuller</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Pages 203-213 in Andrew Henderson and Finn Borchsenius (eds.). Evolution, variation and classification of palms. Memoirs of The New York Botanical Garden. Vol 83.</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1999</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Physokentia petiolatus</name>
<author>(Burret) Fuller</author>
<citation>Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 83: 208 (1999)</citation>
<type>Viti Levu, on the Rairaimatuku Plateau between Nubulolo Creek and Wainisavulevu Creek, near the Nadroga &amp; Navosa-Naitasiri boundary, 18 Aug 1937; St. John; 18338</type>
<type_loc>Holotype B†</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Goniocladus petiolatus</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<bibref>Burret, Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Berlin 15: 87. 1940</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Physokentia rosea</name>
<author>H. E. Moore</author>
<bibref>H. E. Moore, Principes 10: 90. 1966</bibref>
<type>Viti Levu, Ba Province, mossy cloud forest on upper slopes and ridges from Mt. Lomalagi beyond second peak in E direction, vicinity of Nadarivatu, 2 May 1964; Moore &amp; Koroiveibau; 9363</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BH; isotype SUVA!</type_loc>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>Named for the prominent leaf petiole.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>tagadanu</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Trunk erect, to 8 m tall, 10 cm diam., green, with irregular leaf scars, with a cone of prickly stilt roots to 1 m long, ca. 4 cm diam., reddish. Leaves pinnate, 8-10 in crown, stiffly spreading to ascending; sheaths forming a prominent crownshaft to 50 cm long, thickened at base, olive-green, sometimes pink flushed to red toward base; petiole to 22 cm long; pinnae 25-35 per side, dull green, once ribbed, acute with decurved margins, to 70 X 4 cm. Inflorescence infrafoliar, to 50 cm long, branched to three orders, red in bud becoming green in fruit. Flowers in spirally arranged triads, with triads along proximal half, sometimes to distal portions; staminate flowers to 5 mm long; petals 3, deep rose-red; stamens 6 with white anthers; pistillode trifid; pistillate flowers to 5 mm long; petals dark rose-red; sepals strongly imbricate. Fruit globose, to 2 cm diam., dark red at maturity; endocarp angled, keeled and longitudinally ridged. Seed same shape as fruit, 1.2 cm long, 1 cm diam. Eophyll pinnate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Endemic to Fiji and known only from the island of Viti Levu.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Grows as an understorey palm in upper montane rainforests and mossy cloud forests at altitudes of 750-1250 m. Known to flower and fruit April-May.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>This palm species is common in areas that are protected for watershed management purposes (Monasavu Hydroelectric Dam Project). However, on the basis of collection data and disturbance of some P. petiolatus habitat in other areas (e.g., Navai) by logging activities, this taxon should be considered rare. Dick Phillips (pers. comm.) has had limited success cultivating this species in Fiji, and so far I have no reports of successful cultivation of P. petiolatus outside of Fiji.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>No uses recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Additional specimens examined: Fiji: Viti Levu: Ba Province: Vuninatabua, Navai, 750-900 m, 4 Feb-26 Mar 1941, Degener 14792 (A, K, BISH, UC, US); Ridge from Mt. Namana (E of Nadarivatu) toward Mt. Tomanivi (Mt. Victoria), 1050-1120 m, dense forest, 18 Aug 1947, Smith 5700 (A, K, BISH, US). Nadroga &amp; Navosa Province: Nad-rua, in forest, 750-900 m, 4 Feb-26 Mar 1941, Degener 14893 (A, K, BISH); Forest at Taunaisali on central plateau between headwaters of the Wainimala and Sigatoka Rivers [type locality of Goniocladus petiolatus Burret], c. 3800 ft, 9-10 Sep 1972, Moore et al. 10008 (BH, SUVA); Rairai-matuku Plateau [type location of Goniocladus petiolatus], 1100 m, Jul 1995, Masitoqi s.n. (SUVA). Naitasiri Province: Monasavu area, 17°45.706'S, 178°00.357'E, 1190 m, 11 Mar 1995, Fuller 169 (CAS, SUVA); Monasavu area, 1100+ m, 30 Sep 1995, Fuller 276, 278 (SUVA); Monasavu area, 17°45.706'S, 178°00.357'E, 1190 m, 1 Oct 1995, Fuller 281 (SUVA, US); Ra Province: Nadarivatu, Lom-alagi, South ridge, 3000 ft, dense shade, moist forest, 19 Oct 1969, Anderson s.n. (BISH).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>