<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Plectocomiopsis geminiflora</name>
<author>(Griff.) Becc.</author>
<citation>in Hooker f., Fl. Br. India 6: 479 (1893)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 48 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 61 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 37: 246 (1982)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 38 (1984) and Ratt. Sarawak 210 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus geminiflorus</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<bibref>Griff., Palms Br. India 70 (1850)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Paired flowers</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Embalua (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering, moderate to robust rattan with stems to 30 m or more, forming rather dense thickets. Stem without sheaths to 30 mm diam., with sheaths to 60 mm diam., but usually more slender, internodes to 40 cm, shorter in exposed stems. Sheaths generally dull green with persistent grey tomentum and scattered caducous reddish-brown scales, and abundant scattered golden-yellow spines to 8 mm long, the spines sometimes absent on the sheaths subtending the inflorescences; knee absent; ocrea not well developed except on juvenile shoots where irregular, oblique and tattering. Leaf to 3 m including the cirrus to 1 m; petiole present on juvenile stems, absent in adult; leaflets c. 30 on each side of the rachis, regularly arranged, the largest to 40 &#215; 4 cm, bright shining green, concolorous, with short bristles along the margins, the mid nerve on the upper surface with conspicuous golden bristles to 1.5 cm. Inflorescences up to 15 produced simultaneously, the male with more slender branches than the female, to 40 cm, with curving branches to 30 cm bearing clusters of flowers. Ripe fruit oblate, to 2.5 &#215; 3 cm, covered in up to 42 vertical rows of pale greenish to chestnut brown scales. Seed c. 2 &#215; 2 cm; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf bifid. (Fig. 79, Pl. 13B).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Local in mixed dipterocarp forest scattered throughout Brunei at altitudes up to 750 m above sea level, but remarkably patchy in distribution. Elsewhere a common rattan throughout Borneo, Sumatra, S Thailand and Peninsular Malaysia.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cabbage, although bitter, is highly esteemed, and is sometimes sold in village markets. The cane seems only to be used for coarse basketware and cordage.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The clustering habit, moderate to robust size, absence of knee and the conspicuous long bristles on the upper surface of the main vein of the leaflets make this a very easily distinguished species.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Bt.Belalong, Wong 1393.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>