<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Monograph of Phoenix L. (Palmae: Coryphoideae)</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Barrow</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1998</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 53, No. 3 (1998), pp. 513-575</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Phoenix atlantica</name>
<author>A. Chev.</author>
<citation>Bull. Mus. Hist. Nat. (Paris), sér. 2, 7: 137 (1935)</citation>
<type>Isle de Sal, Algodeiro, 1934 (stam., pist.); Chevalier; 45839</type>
<type_loc>Type P!</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>CAPE VERDE IS. Isle de Sal, Palmeira, Palha Verde (ster.), Chevalier 45840 (P!); San Thiago Praia, (pist.), Chevalier 45851 (P!); Isle de San Thiago, Praia, Sao Martinho, Chevalier 45854, 45858 (P!); Is. de Sal, Algodeiro, 1934 (stam., pist.), Chevalier 45839 (P!); Is. de Sal, Palmeira, Palha Verde, 1934 (ster.), Chevalier 45840 (P!); Is. de Sal, Pedro Lime, 26 June 1934 (stam.), Chevalier s.n. (P!).</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>IMPERFECTLY KNOWN TAXON. Phoenix atlantica was described by Chevalier (1952) from the Cape Verde Islands as a clustering species occurring in large clumps of 2 - 6 stems, to 15 m tall and 45 cm in diameter. Chevalier (1952) considered the taxon to have characteristics of P. dactylifera, P. canariensis and R reclinata. All available evidence suggests to me that P. atlantica is a close relative of P. dactylifera, but, it is not yet clear whether the taxon merely represents feral date palms, or products of a series of hybridisation events between P. dactylifera and other species in the genus, or whether it is a distinct species. Further information is required before the species status of P. atlantica can be clarified. Chevalier (1952) described P. atlantica var. maroccana A. Chev. from the Atlas Mountains of southwestern Morocco and reported large groves of 100,000 - 150,000 palms near Marrakech. The edible fruits were said to be sold locally in the markets but not exported. I consider this varietal name to refer to P. dactylifera and have included it here as a synonym of that name.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>

