<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis coursii</name>
<author>Beentje</author>
<citation>in J. Dransfield &amp; H. Beentje, Palms Madagascar: 230 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Marojejy W, near Doanyanala col; Humbert; 23159</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus P; isotypus K</type_loc>			
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A curious montane species, with a short, wide trunk. The name refers to one of the collectors, G. Cours, who made many good palm collections between 1939 and 1952.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Palma distinctissima caule breve lato foliolis in greges distantes dense aggregatis fructo grande profunde ruminato.</p></div> 
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm. STEM 2-8 m, 8-18 cm diam., near the apex c. 2.2 cm diam. LEAVES c. 4 in the crown; sheath 18-36 x 9 cm, with dense reddish tomentum and wax, and with triangular auricles to 5 x 3 cm; petiole 4-27 cm long, 1.1-1.3 x 0.3-0.7 cm diam., with few scattered scales; rachis 0.4-1 m long (Humbert 23159: leaves 2 m long), in mid-leaf 0.6-1 x 0.4 cm diam., with scattered scales; leaflets 35-39 on each side of the rachis, in groups of pairs proximally, in 2-7 medially (group interval 2.2-7 cm), the proximal 10-29 x 0.2-1.2 cm, median 12-34 x 1.6-3.5 cm (interval 0.7-1.2 cm), distal 6-17 x 0.4-2.2 cm, main veins 1-5, and thickened margins, ramenta few or none, plus red scattered scales on midrib and veins, apex acute, unequally bifid. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, pendulous, branching to (1-) 2 orders; peduncle 23-70 cm, 5-10 x 2-4 mm diam., with dense to few scattered scales; prophyll 12-26 cm long, borne at 1-6 cm above the base of the peduncle, 1.6-2 cm wide; peduncular bract inserted at 2-17 cm, deciduous, 24 cm long; sterile bract inserted at 19-25 cm, 0.2-3 x 0.6-3 cm; rachis 19-36 cm, glabrous or nearly so, with 6 branched (first order rachis to 20 cm, proximally to 8 x 4 mm diam., with up to 9 rachillae) and 8-22 unbranched first order branches; rachis bracts to 3 mm; rachillae 1-27 cm, 1.2-3 mm diam., glabrous; triads distant, superficial; rachilla bract c. 1 mm, obtuse. STAMINATE FLOWERS yellowish; sepals 1.5-1.6 x 1.3-1.8 mm; petals 2.7-3 x 1.6-2 mm; stamens 6, uniseriate, filaments 1.6-2.8 mm long with triangular base and cylindrical distal half, anthers 1.2-1.6 x 0.6-0.9 mm; pistillode 0.6-1 mm high, 0.4-0.6 mm diam. PISTILLATE FLOWERS with sepals 1.7-2.8 x 1.5-3.9 mm; petals 4-5 x 2.5-5.5 mm; staminodes 0.3-0.8 mm long; ovary 2.5-3 mm high, 0.9-1.5 mm diam. FRUIT ellipsoid or slightly obovoid, 20-35 x 15-25 mm, pointed at the base, rounded at the apex; endocarp flaky. SEED obovoid, c. 25 x 13-17 mm, pointed at the base, rounded at the apex, the surface slightly channelled, with a sub-basal or lateral depression; endosperm ruminate, the ruminations many, 2-7 mm deep.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from the Marojejy area.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Moist montane forest or dense sclerophyll forest on ridges; on gneiss and quartzite, (400-) 900-1850 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Vulnerable. Distribution area small, but protected. Numbers unknown, but thought to be low.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Distinct by its short, wide trunk, the distant groups of densely set leaflets, and large ruminate fruits.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Mt Beondroka, N of Maroambihy, March 1949 (fr.), Humbert 23463 (K, P); Marojejy W, near Doanyanala col, Jan./Feb. 1949 (fl.), Humbert 23159 (K, P); Marojejy E, W of Manantenina R, Dec. 1948 (bud), Humbert 22558 (K, P); Marojejy E trail, Oct. 1988 (fl., y.fr.), Miller at al. 3566 (TAN); Marojejy, 1700-1800 m, Nov. 1972 (fl.), Guillaumet 4105 (P, TAN); idem (bud), Guillaumet 4106 (P, TAN). Sambava: Mt. d'Ambatosoratra, Jan. 1949 (fr.), Cours 3299 (K, P, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>