<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A monographic study of the subfamily Phytelephantoideae (Arecaceae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Barfod</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">A.S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Opera Botanica 105: 1-73</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1991</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Phytelephas aequatorialis</name>
<author>Spruce</author>
<citation>J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 11: 179 (1869)</citation>
<type>Ecuador. Chim-borazo: ad pedem Chimborazo, Andes Quitensis (&#9794;); Spruce; 64</type>
<type_loc>Holotype K</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Palandra aequatorialis</name>
<author>(Spruce) Cook</author>
<bibref>(Spruce) Cook, J. Wash. Acad. Sci. 17: 218-230, 1927</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Din-chi or timo-bulo (Cayapa) entire plant; timo-poca or handa-kika (Cayapa) ivory nut; tchape-taka (Cayapa) liquid endosperm; pimbu-ku or yau-ku (Cayapa) edible mesocarp; mazorca (Quechua) infructescence; maguay (Que-chua) fruit; fiadi (Spanish).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm tree, 3-15 m tall, erect at flowering, rarely with subterranean or decumbent stem; stem distally covered by marcescent leaves, 25-30 cm in diam. Leaves 10-25; about 100 cm long from point of insertion to blade, leaf sheath split to the base; petiole about 7 cm wide distally, glabrous, green to grayish-green; rachis 5-7 m long; pinnae 200-280 per side, those inserted at the ends evenly distributed, opposite, and in one plane, otherwise inserted in opposite groups of 2-7 and diverging 5-20° above the one plane, largest in the middle part, to 90 x 6.5 cm, 50-70 x 2-4 cm proximally and 25-30 x 1-2 cm distally; midnerve prominent, yellowish green above, submarginal veins prominulent, transverse commissures more or less conspicuous. Staminate peduncle 50-80 cm long, 4-6 cm wide in the middle part, yellow and glabrous; prophyll 50-70 cm long, 8-10 cm wide in the middle part, grayish-green to grayish-brown; first peduncular bract inserted 5-10 cm above prophyll, 50-110 cm long, glabrous, yellowish-brown both inside and outside, coriaceous, longitudinally splitting on adaxial side to little below the middle; 3-8 incomplete peduncular bracts deltoid, often plicate basally, the basal ones to 8 x 5 cm; rachis 90-150 cm long at anthesis, elliptic in cross-section, 5-6 X 3^1 cm, glabrous, furrowed, yellow sometimes with a red tinge, tapering to a blunt apex; flower clusters 300-500, crowded at early anthesis, later separating, the proxmal ones mostly so, rachis terminated by numerous, closely inserted, solitary flowers; flower clusters subtended by shallow membranous bracts decreasing in size towards the distal part of the rachis, pedicels fused to a longitudinally furrowed flower-bearing stalk, bracts subtending the pedicels adnate laterally forming a narrow rim encircling the cluster basally, flowers 4, closely aggregated in capitula, fusion between adjacent receptacles occasionally occurring; receptacle flattened, angled by mutual pressure at early an thesis later rounded in distal view, margin slightly deflexed; perianth cupule with about 8 free teeth, each 1 x 3-5 mm; stamens 500-700, about 1 cm long; filament 6-10 x 0.1 mm; anthers 3-5 x 0.5 mm, apiculate. Pistillate peduncle 40-50 cm long, 3.5^t cm. wide centrally, brown, woody-fleshy; prophyll inserted close to peduncle base, similar to staminate prophyll, but a little shorter; first peduncular bract inserted 5-10 cm above prophyll, 60-80 cm long, erect, otherwise similar to staminate homologue; 25-50(-100) incomplete peduncular bracts, arranged either in spiralling or straight vertical rows, the basal ones elliptic, 10-15 x 4-6 cm, with a 1-2 cm long acumen, insertion increasingly dense towards the bracts subtending flowers; flowers 15-25; floral subtending bracts 3-7 cm long, wider and clearly distinct from the sepaloid bracts, these 4-6, uneven in length and basal width, strap shaped, from 3 to 8 cm long and with papillose margins; tepals 6-9, 15-20 cm long, 1.5-2 cm wide basally; non-functional stamens 20-25; filament up to 35 mm long, curled basally; anthers 0.6-0.8 x ca. 0.5 mm; pistil 5-6-locul-ate, 10-15 x 5-10 mm; style 10-15 x 3-4 mm in diam., obtuse angled; stigmas 5, 7-9 cm long. Infructescences 5-10(-20); peduncle 10-20 x 5-7 cm; incomplete bracts covering 20 cm of peduncle below the bracts subtending flowers, the proximal ones widely separated 10-15 cm apart and up to 15 cm long. Infructescences (10-)15—20 (-25) on one palm, about 30 cm in diameter; fruits obconical, 5 to 6-angled by mutual pressure, the tangential face 10-15 cm in diam., firmly attached, sometimes not separating cleanly, with rough about 1 cm long spiny processes, basal portion of style persistent; inner meso-carp 1-2 mm, drying pulveraceous; seeds 5-6; pyrenes unevenly sized and shaped in the same fruit, usually elongated longitudinally, 5x3 cm on average; rostrum often conspicuous, about 5x1 mm and easily breaking; umbo rounded to somewhat elliptical in outline, 5-15 mm in largest diameter, mature endosperm often without cavity. Seedling with two scale leaves; cotyledonary petiole usually elongating to less than 10 cm; eophyll with smooth petiole and rachis and about 25 opposite pinnae.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>An endemic to the coastal plains of Ecuador. Ranging up to about 1500 m. on the western Andean slopes.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Flowering peaks at the end of the rainy season in Feb.-May and extends into the drier season. In large populations, a few flowering palm individuals can be found most of the year. Vegetative characters such as grouping and divergence of the pinnae are variable. Juvenile leaves and leaves of young individuals have pinnae that are almost evenly distributed and that diverge little from the one plane. Lowland populations are similar to populations at higher altitudes with a slight bias towards more evenly distributed pinnae. Moderate-sized palms that occasionally grow tall especially at higher altitudes. Occurring scattered in undisturbed forest on the coastal plain. Often seen in pastures or in orchards where they are conserved because of their ornamental and economic value.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The white, hard endosperm is the source of vegetable ivory in Ecuador. Vegetable ivory is suitable for carving and turning on a lathe and is currently used for handicrafts and buttons. For more than a century it was used in Europe and the United States to produce buttons for clothings. Ecuador was the foremost exporting country. After World War II, it was broadly replaced by plastics. A more detailed description of the economic history of vegetable ivory is given by Barfod (1989). A few factories on the coast of Ecuador have survived the post-war decline of the industry and still produce buttons from vegetable ivory (Barfod et al. 1990). The buttons are exported to Japan, West Germany and Italy. All wastes from the production are collected and ground into a flour used as cattle or pig fodder. Barret (1925) and Barfod &amp; Balslev (1988) describe how leaves are used for thatching by the Cayapa Indians in the Province of Esmeraldas. They are extracted from individual palms that are preserved especially for this purpose. A few juvenile leaves are spared to protect the apical meristem and secure continued growth. The leaves are either dried on racks or fermented in ponds to prevent attacks from fungi and insects. They are split along the rachis and the halves are fastened to the roof construction, one on top of the other. The pinnae are not braided except in ceremonial houses. According to Acosta Soli's (1944), a thatch may last between six and eight years in the humid lowlands, whereas mountain dwellers will have to repair and partly replace the thatch every year before the rainy season. Fibres extracted from the leaf-bases are used to produce brooms. These brooms are inferior to those made of Aphandra natalia, however. The inner mesocarp is edible either raw or, prepared over a fire as described by Barrett (1925). The consistency is fleshy-oleaginous and the taste is rather neutral. The liquid endosperm of the unripe fruit is considered a delicacy. It is usually extracted with a machete which demands much work and skill. Acosta Solfs (1944) described how dwellers on the western slopes of the Ecuadorean Andes consider the palm heart a great delicacy. The palm heart is named "Guagra changa" (Quechua) locally and is either eaten raw as a salad or boiled. Larvae of Rhynchophora palmarum (Latv.) are collected on dead trunks and eaten. This beetle larvae is found on the decomposing trunks of other palm species as well.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>