<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the Rattans of Andaman and Nicobar Islands</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Renuka</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kerala Forest Research Institute, India</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia rogersii</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12(2): 131. 1918</citation>
<bibref>Basu, Rattans in India Monogr. Rev.: 26-27. 1992</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering.very small diameter rattan. Stem 20 m long or more, with sheaths 0.7 cm in diameter,without sheaths 0.4 cm. Leaf upto 1 m long, cirrate; sheath light green, sparingly armed with spines; spines 1 cm long; knee absent; ocrea prominent, fibrous; petioles 15 cm long, margins armed below with 2 rows of recurved spines to 0.4 cm long; cirrus armed below with whorls of recurved spines to 0.3 cm long; leaflets 13 x 6.5 cm, equidistant, cuneate-rhomboid, irregularly toothed, dark green above and pale below, narrowed to a short petiole. Inflorescence 15 cm long; primary sheath tubular, unarmed; secondary sheaths obliquely truncate; rachillae 3-5 cm long. Fruits obovoid, turbinate ca. 1.8 x 1.5 cm; scales light yellow with reddish brown margin, channelled in the middle.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Distributed in Radhanagar and Diglipur in North Andamans and Havlock island in South Andamans. (Map. 10)</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Not known</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not much used.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>During recent survey the inflorescence and fruits could not be collected. The description of reproductive parts is basedon Basu (1992).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Diglipur, North Andaman, 27.4.92, Vijayakumaran 6638 (KFRI).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>