<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Genera Palmarum. The evolution and classification of palms</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Uhl</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">N.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Asmussen</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Baker</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">W.J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Harley</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2008</mods:dateIssued><mods:publisher>Kew Publishing, Royal Botanic Gardens Kew</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="genus">
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Solitary, moderate or tall pinnate-leaved monoecious palms from Central America and the Caribbean; stems often bear many inflorescences at the same time; flowers are borne in groups of 3–7.</p></div>
<nomenclature>
<name>Gaussia</name>
<author>H. Wendl.</author>
<citation>Nachr. Königl. Ges. Wiss. Geor g-Augusts-Univ. 327 (1865).</citation>
<type>Type; Gaussia princeps; H. Wendl.</type>
<synonymy>
<name>Aeria</name>
<author>O.F. Cook</author>
<bibref>O.F. Cook, Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 28: 547 (1901).</bibref>
<type>Type; Aeria attenuata; O.F. Cook</type>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Opsiandra</name>
<author>O.F. Cook</author>
<bibref>O.F. Cook, J. Wash. Acad. Sci. 13: 182 (1923).</bibref>
<type>Type; Opsiandra maya; O.F. Cook</type>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="etymology"><p>Commemorates German mathematician Karl Friedrich Gauss (1777–1855).</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary, moderate or tall, unarmed, monoecious, pleonanthic palms.</p></div>
Stem occasionally leaning, brown or grey to whitish, straight or somewhat ventricose basally or near the middle, leaf scars prominent and broad, or inconspicuous, roots bearing small prickly lateral roots in a prominent mass at base of trunk. Leaves pinnate; sheath wide basally, narrowing distally into the petiole, split opposite the petiole at maturity, not forming a distinct crownshaft, upper edges reflexed, edges sometimes shredded; petiole short, subterete, only narrowly and shallowly channelled adaxially; rachis prominently ridged adaxially, ± rounded abaxially; leaflets acute, single-fold, broadly reduplicate at insertion, obscurely or prominately pulvinate above, lightly waxy, midribs prominent with 2 or more conspicuous secondary pairs of ribs, transverse veinlets not evident. Inflorescences interfoliar, not long-persistent, falling with or soon after the subtending leaves, branching to 2–3 orders; peduncle elongate, ascending; prophyll very short, tubular, flat, ± 2-keeled, pointed, open at apex; peduncular bracts 4–7, each progressively longer, tubular with obliquely open apices, the distal usually reaching or exceeding the base of the first-flowering branches; rachis about as long as the peduncle; first-order branches numerous, crowded, spirally inserted; rachillae glabrous, slender, lacking bracts, bearing spirally arranged rows of flowers (acervuli) of a proximal pistillate and (2–)3–7, distal staminate, the distal flower opening first, the pistillate maturing and expanding normally when all the staminate have been shed, all flowers caducous after anthesis unless fertilised. Flowers small, green in bud, yellow or yellow-green at anthesis. Staminate flowers ovoid to ellipsoid in bud; sepals 3, rounded, imbricate basally; petals 3, valvate, strongly nerved in bud (when dry), fleshy or thin and not prominently nerved when expanded; stamens 6, filaments subulate, very short or well developed, not inflexed at the apex in bud, emarginate or deeply divided apically, anthers dorsifixed above the middle, deeply sagittate or bifid at the base, shallowly bifid at the apex; pistillode angled-columnar, as long as the stamens in bud. Pollen ellipsoidal, slightly asymmetric; aperture a distal sulcus; ectexine tectate, scabrate and finely perforate including aperture margin or, finely perforate-reticulate with broad, scabrate, finely perforate aperture margin; infratectum columellate; longest axis ranging from 25–40 µm; post-meiotic tetrads usually tetrahedral, occasionally tetragonal or rhomboidal [3/5]. Pistillate flowers ovoid; sepals 3, distinct, rounded, imbricate basally; petals 3, narrowly imbricate basally and subvalvate to valvate distally, the tips spreading at anthesis; staminodes 6, minute, tooth-like; gynoecium angled-ovoid, with 3 recurved stigmas, trilocular, triovulate, ovules laterally attached, with funicular aril, campylotropous. Fruit ellipsoidal or globose to kidney-shaped, red or deep orange, fleshy, with basal stigmatic remains; epicarp smooth, mesocarp lacking anastomosing fibres against the membranous endocarp. Seed ellipsoidal to kidney-shaped or subglobose, not adherent to the endocarp, with stalked or indistinct, round basal hilum, raphe not evident, raphe branches few, sparsely branched, ascending adaxially, curved laterally, descending abaxially toward the embryo, endosperm homogeneous; embryo lateral. Germination and eophyll not recorded. Cytology: 2n = 28. 
<div type="distribution"><p>Five species, occurring in Mexico, Guatemala, Belize, Cuba, Hispaniola and Puerto Rico.  </p></div>
<div type="anatomy"><p>Leaf (Tomlinson 1961), root (Seubert 1998a, 1998b). </p></div>
<div type="relationships"><p>Gaussia is monophyletic with high support (Cuenca and Asmussen-Lange 2007). For relationships, see Chamaedorea. In addition, a phylogeny based on morphology alone places Gaussia as sister to the rest of tribe Chamaedoreeae (Cuenca-Navarro 2007). </p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Local uses are not recorded. Species are rarely grown as ornamentals. </p></div>
<div type="taxonomic accounts"><p>Quero and Read (1986), Beccari (1912)and Moya Lopez and Leiva (1991).</p></div>
<div type="fossil record"><p>No generic records found.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Species of Gaussia superficially resemble Pseudophoenixspp. However, they are easily recognised because they havegrouped unisexual flowers rather than solitary hermaphroditicflowers.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Llume palm (Gaussia attenuata), maya palm (G. maya). </p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>On limestone hills (mogotes), sometimes growing from crevices in very steep rocks and at low elevations on limestone escarpments or low hills, often on pyramids in the archeological region of Guatemala, less frequently on the forest floor in high forest over limestone.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>
