<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Synopsis of the Genus Korthalsia (Palmae: Lepidocaryoideae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 1, pp. 163-194</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1981</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia bejaudii</name>
<author>Gagnep. ex Humbert</author>
<citation>Not. Syst. 6: 152 (1937)</citation>
<bibref>Gagnep. ex Humbert, Fl. Gen. Indo-China 6: 1000 (1937)</bibref>
<type>Cambodia, Kompong-cham; Bejaud; s.n.</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P; isotype P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p></p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species is known only from two sheets in Paris; there are no accom- panying fieldnotes to indicate habitat, or distribution in Cambodia. Gagnepain distinguished this taxon from K. laciniosa based on the nature of the ocrea and the primary inflorescence bracts. I have examined the type and isotype and agree that in details of ocrea it is distinct from K. laciniosa; however I can see no significant differences in the inflorescence. Whereas the ocrea of K. laciniosa is usually much larger than 10 cm, is armed with scattered or few spines, and disintegrates into a weft of fibres, that of K. bejaudii is very short and truncate (not exceeding 4 cm), does not apparently disintegrate, and is armed with crowded flattened spines near the tip. The leaflets are described as concolorous, and this would be a further character separating it from K. laciniosa, but the leaflets may be concolorous through old age-there are certainly traces of indumentum on the abaxial leaflet surfaces. In the absence of further material, K. bejaudii is retained as a distinct species.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>