<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis heteromorpha</name>
<author>(Jum.) Beentje &amp; J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 197 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Tsaratanana; Perrier; 11935, 15266 and 15266bis</type>
<type_loc>Syntypes P</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Neodypsis heteromorphus</name>
<author>Jum.</author>
<bibref>Jum., Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 4, 2 (2): 20 (1924)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. Cat. Pl. Madagascar, Palmae: 18 (1938)</bibref> 
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier Fl. Madagascar 30: 145 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>This palm has not been collected since 1959, and the material available to us was fairly fragmentary. A high altitude species, with the name indicating the variation in the leaf division: from regularly pinnate with many leaflets, to entire-leaved on young shoots.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering palm in tufts of 3-6, but sometimes appearing solitary. STEMS 3-12 m high, 8-12 cm diam.; internodes green, nodal scars obvious. LEAVES c. 10 in the crown, tristichous (fide Humbert &amp; Saboureau 31725); sheath 27-50 cm long, to 7 cm wide when flattened, with sloping shoulders, adaxially red-brown, abaxially very waxy, in the distal part with dense reddish laciniate scales; petiole absent or up to 35 cm long, 1-1.8 cm diam., densely pubescent or with scattered scales; rachis c. 1.5 m long, in mid- leaf 0.9-1.3 cm wide, slightly keeled, pubescent on both surfaces; leaflets (number unknown) regular, the proximal 20-62 x 0.2-2.5 cm, median 41-67 x 1-3.5 cm (interval 1.5-3.5 cm), distal 7-35 x 0.6-2.5 cm, main veins 1-5, and with thickened margins, abaxially with scattered reddish glands on the minor veins and continuous or scattered laciniate ramenta 3-20 mm long on the midrib, apex bifid, unequally attenuate, young shoots with entire, deeply bilobed leaves 26-50 cm long with a costa 2-4 cm and lobes 24-46 cm long, or leaves with 2-4 leaflets (not seen), on a 64-75 cm long petiole. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, branched to 2 orders, pendulous; peduncle 20-40 (+) cm long, proximally 2-3.5 x 0.8-1.3 cm, distally 1-2 x 0.7-1.2 cm, glabrous; prophyll 38-52 x 3-8.5 cm, borne at 9-20 cm above the base of the peduncle, open for a third or over its whole length, erect, with scattered scales; peduncular bract inserted at 17-29 cm from the base of the peduncle, 27-55 (+) cm long, open over its whole length, beaked for 0.5-4 cm, with scattered scales; non-tubular peduncular bracts one or two, 2-5 cm long; rachis 10-35 cm long, glabrous, with 8-10 branched and 7-9 unbranched first order branches, first order branches with a rachis 1.5-13 cm long and 1.1-1.7 x 0.5-0.8 cm diam. proximally with 3-9 rachillae; rachis bracts conspicuous, to 2.5 cm, pale brown; rachillae 5-23 cm long, 2-4 mm diam., with dense triads (more distant in fruit), superficial or slightly sunk, with triangular acute rachilla bracts and very pronounced bracteoles. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 2.7-3.2 x 3.5-4.4 mm; petals 3.5-3.8 x 2.5-3 mm; stamens 6, slightly 2-seriate (offset 0.2 mm), filaments in ripe buds 1.8-2.1 mm, cylindrical, anthers 2.2-2.4 x 0.9-1.2 mm; pistillode c. 2.4 mm high, 1.2 mm diam. PISTILLATE FLOWERS with sepals 3-4 x 3.3-5mm; petals (at young bud stage) 3.6-3.8 x c. 3.5 mm, very concave (4-5.5 x 5-7.2 mm in young fruit); staminodes not seen; gynoecium when young c. 3 mm high, 1.8 mm diam. FRUIT ellipsoid, 17- 23 x 14-22 mm, rounded at the apex; endocarp fibrous, the fibres anastomosing. SEED ellipsoid, 16-22 x 13-21 mm, obtuse at the base with a sub-aequatorial depression, rounded at apex, with slight surface grooving; endosperm ruminate, the ruminations distant and 1-7 mm deep. EOPHYLL bifid.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>N Madagascar: Tsaratanana, Marojejy and Anjanaharibe.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Moist montane forest; 1300-2200 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Uncertain, but probably rare; the distribution area is not well known botanically.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Related to D. baronii and D. onilahensis, and possibly a high-altitude variant of the former; distinct by deep-ruminate endosperm.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Andapa / Ambilobe / Bealanana: Mt Tsaratanana, Oct. 1912 (y.fr.), Perrier 11935 (P); idem, Jan. 1923 (fr.), Perrier 15266 (P, syntype); idem, sine die (fl., fr.), Perrier 15266 bis (P, syntype). Bealanana: Ambohimirahavavy Mts, Jan./Feb. 1951 (fr.), Humbert &amp; Capuron 25281 (K, P). Andapa: N Anjanaharibe, Dec. 1950/Jan. 1951 (fr.), Humbert et al. 24766 (K, P); Ambatoharanana valley to upper Antsahaberoka, Nov./Dec. 1959 (y.fr.), Humbert &amp; Saboureau 31725 (K, P).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>