<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Pritchardia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Hodel</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms 51(4) Special Supplement S-1-53</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pritchardia napaliensis</name>
<author>H. St. John</author>
<citation>Pacific Sci. 35: 97. 1981</citation>
<type>Hoolulu Valley, Kauai, Hawaii; Christensen; 39</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BISH!; isotype US</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Pritchardia limahuliensis</name>
<author>H. St. John</author>
<bibref>H. St. John, Phytologia 64: 177. 1988</bibref>
<type>Limahuli Valley, Kauai, Hawaii; Perlman; 7</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BISH!</type_loc>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>To 10 m tall; proximal margins of petiole sparsely to moderately fibrous; leaf blade nearly flat, divided 1/2, abaxial surface incompletely covered with scattered lepidia,segment tips stiff or only slightly drooping in shade; inflorescences composed of 1-3 panicles, shorter than to equaling petioles in flower and fruit, panicles branched to 2 (or 3?) orders, rachillae glabrous; fruits 17-23 x 14-18 mm, ellipsoid. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Moist to wet forests on steep slopes, Napali Coast, Kauai, 150-600 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Pritchardia napaliensis is distinguished by its flat leaf blade incompletely covered abaxially with lepidia, inflorescences shorter than or equaling the petioles, and small fruits. Pritchardia napaliensis is similar in habit to P. minor and their ranges may overlap slightly but the latter differs in its ieaf blades completely covered abaxially with lepidia and the panicles permanently clothed with thick, pinkish brown, woolly indumentum. I am unable to find significant differences between Pritchardia napaliensis and P. limahuliensis after examining the types and liVing plants at the type localities of both species. Collections and cultivated plants from higher eievations in upper Limahuli Valley, which have been annotated or labeled as P. limahuliensis, have the abaxial leaf blade surface completely covered with lepidia and are best referred to P. perlmanii.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>U.S.A. Hawaii. Kauai: Hanakapiai Valley, below Pohakea, Perlman 15446, 16521, 16686 (PTBG); Hoolulu Valley, Christensen 39 (BISH), St. John 23185 (BISH), Wood 215,216, 7289 (PTBG); lower Limahuli Valley, Perlman 7 (BISH), Perlman 12932 (PTBG), Wood 295, 296 (PTBG); Pohakuao, Perlman 12690 (PTBG), Wood 1784,7651,7652, 8055, 9883 (PTBG). CULT. U.S.A. Hawaii. Kauai: National Tropical Botanical Garden, NTBG 930109, Chapin 75 (PTBG) </p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>