<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Pritchardia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Hodel</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms 51(4) Special Supplement S-1-53</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pritchardia glabrata</name>
<author>Becc. &amp; Rock</author>
<citation>Mem. Bernice P. Bishop Mus. 8: 42. 1921</citation>
<type>Iao Valley, Maui (W. Maul), Hawaii; Rock; 14077</type>
<type_loc>Holotype FI (photo!)</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Pritchardia lanaiensis</name>
<author>Becc. &amp; Rock</author>
<bibref>Becc. &amp; Rock, Mem. Bernice P. Bishop Mus. 8: 41. 1921</bibref>
<type>Mauna Lei Gorge, Lanai, Hawaii; Rock (ex Munro); 17242</type>
<type_loc>Holotype FI; isotype BISH!</type_loc>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Pritchardia elliptica</name>
<author>Rock &amp; Caum</author>
<bibref>Rock &amp; Caum, Occas. Pap. Bernice P. Bishop Mus. 9(S): 14. 1930</bibref>
<type>Kunoa Valley, Lanai, Hawaii, 18 Oct. 1927; Munro; s. n.</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BISH!</type_loc>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>To 5 m tall; proximal margins of petiole with only a few fibers; leaf blade undulate, divided 1/2, abaxial surface incompletely covered with scattered lepidia, segment tips stiff to drooping; inflorescences composed of 1-3 panicles, shorter than or equaling petioles in flower and fruit, panicles branched to 2 or 3 orders, rachillae glabrous; fruits 20-30 x 20-2S mm, globose to ellipsoid.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Moist forest on Lanai and the southern and southeastern slopes and valleys of the Puu Kukui massif, West Maui, 300-900 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>I could find no reliable characters to separate Pritchardia glabrata from P. eiliptica and P. lanaiensisi thus, with the inclusion of these in synonymy, P. glabrata is another of the four Hawaiian species that is recorded from more than one island. Pritchardia glabrata is difficult to distinguish from P. remota and P. waialealeana. All three share the undulate leaf blades incompletely covered abaxially with lepidia and with drooping segment tips, inflorescences shorter than or equaling the petioles with panicles branched to three orders, glabrous rachillae, and small fruits. Both the latter species, however, differ in their generally larger habit. Also, P. remota differs in its slightly waxy glaucous leaf blades while P. waialealeana differs in the lack of cottony hairs or mealy indumentum on the abaxial folds of its leaf blades and the longer-than-wide fruits. The holotype of Pritchardia lanaiensis at FI is unnumbered while the isotype at BISH has a Rock number, probably one that Rock added later to Munro's specimen. Rock not infrequently added his or some other number (perhaps a number from a herbarium numbering system) to other collectors' material.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>U.S.A. Hawaii. Maui (W. Maui): Iao Valley, Flynn 2699 (PTBG), Perlman 12969 (PTBG), Rock 12801 (BISH), 14077 (FI), Wood 256,257, 7586 (PTBG); upper Waikapu, Wood 7579 (PTBG). Lanai: Haua Gulch, Palea Ridge, Perlman 16386 (PTBG), Wood 7526 (PTBG); Kunoa Valley, Munro s. n. 18 October 1927 (BISH), Munro 221, 350 (BISH), Perlman 16388, 16392, 16394 (PTBG), Wood 7517 (PTBG); Kunoa Ridge, Wood 7530 (PTBG); Mauna Lei Gorge, Hobdy 208 (BISH), Mllnro s. n., March 1918, 56 (BlSH), Rock 17242 (BISH); 3rd valley east of Kaiholena, Munro 202 (BISH); Waialala, Perlman 12938, 16382, 16384, 16385 (PTBG); mountain at east end of island, Munro 245 (BlSH). CULT. U.S.A. Hawaii. Maui: Kahanu Garden, Hana, Flynn 5797 (PTBG), Lorence 7668 (PTBG). Oahu: Waimea Valley Audubon Center, 885168, Zona 1004 (HAW).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>