<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Revision of Wallichia (Palmae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Henderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">A.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Taiwania 52(1) 1-11</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Wallichia marianneae</name>
<author>Hodel</author>
<citation>Palm J. 137: 8 (1997)</citation>
<type>THAILAND. Trang, SE of Trang near Ton Tok Park, 3 May 1997; D. Hodel, P. Vatcharakorn &amp; R. Vatcharakorn; 1703</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BK; isotype BH!</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Kuong (Thailand).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Stems clustered, to 1.6 m tall, 4-10 cm diameter, stems bearing staminate and pistillate inflorescences about equal in length. Leaves spirally arranged; sheaths 30-75 cm long, disintegrating into black fibers, with a prominent, fibrous ligule at the apex; petioles 1-1.5 m long; rachis 0.8-1.3 m long; pinnae 5-10 per side of rachis, regularly and alternately arranged, spreading in the same plane, proximal 2-3 pinnae in a cluster, pinnae from middle of leaf 57-77 cm long, 6-8 cm wide at widest point, lanceolate, scarcely lobed. Inflorescences unixexual, subtended by smaller leaves, staminate and pistillate borne on the same stems, the pistillate terminal, the staminate lateral; staminate inflorescences not seen in their entirety; rachillae to 10, to 20 cm long, 2-2.5 mm diameter; staminate flowers to 6 mm long; sepals 1.5 mm long, connate into a cupular calyx, very briefly lobed; petals 6 mm long, purple; stamens 16-19; pistillate inflorescences not seen; rachillae to 11 cm long, 3.5 mm diameter; pistillate flowers to 3 mm long; sepals to 0.5 mm long; petals 3 mm long; gynoecium 1.5 mm long; fruits ovoid to ellipsoid, to 1.1 cm long, to 0.8 cm diameter, red or purple. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Thailand (Peninsula) and probably adjacent Myanmar.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland moist forest, 600-1100 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>No uses recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Distinguished from other species by its lanceolate pinnae (Fig. 2E) and purple staminate flowers with 16-19 stamens. One specimen from Thailand (Kanchanaburi: ca. 30 km NW of Thong Pha Phum on highway 323 to Myanmar border, ca. 20 km E of Koeng Ka Vin and Pawanaputso Temple, 500 m, 1 Nov 1997, Hodel &amp; Vatcharakorn 1765 (BH, MO)) has lanceolate pinnae as in W. marianneae and 12 stamens as in W. caryotoides. It is illustrated in Hodel (1998), plate 83c. It may be a hybrid between W. marianneae and W. caryotoides. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>THAILAND. Trang: Khao Chong, forest adjacent to Peninsular Botanic Garden, 7°37’N, 99°37’E, 150-200 m, 24 Oct 1992, Barfod et al. 43985 (AAU); Khao Chang, Botanical Gardens, Tub Kian, 2 km from headquarters, 3 Dec 1986, Smith 94 (K). Phangnga: Sri Phangnga National Park, 9°00’N, 98°28’E, 100-200 m, Barfod et al. 45264 (AAU). Phuket Khao: Khao Phra Kaeo non-hunting area, 8°02’N, 98°21’E, 50-100 m, 27 Feb 1994, Barfod et al. 45273 (AAU). Ranong: La-un, 1100 m, 3 Jan 1929, Kerr 16522 (AAU, BH, BK, K, NY); Kapur District, Klong Na Kha Wildlife Sanctuary, Bang Mon, 25 Nov 1986, Smith &amp; Sumawong 47 (K). </p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>