<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus pycnocarpus</name>
<author>(Furtado) Dransfield</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 40 (1977) 202</citation>
<synonymy>
<name>Cornera pycnocarpa</name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1955) 523</bibref>
</synonymy>
<bibref>Dransfield, Malay. Forester 40 (1977) 202</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Puknos - compact, karpos - fruit, referring to the compact spike of fruit</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan kong</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering rattan climbing to 30 cm; stem without sheaths 5 mm in diameter with internodes to 25 cm; stem with sheaths 1.5 cm in diameter. Sheaths bright green with scattered yellowish black-tipped spines of varying length the largest to 1.5 cm long interspersed with much smaller spines to 1 mm long mostly &#177; horizontal. Knee present, rather small, ocrea very short. Flagellum to 1.25 m. Leaf to about 40 cm long sessile or with a very short petiole scarcely exceeding 3 cm long. No cirrus. Leaflets 7 to 8 in number the uppermost four in a group with the 2 apical leaflets joined through up to Vs their length, with rachis continuing, spiny along underside, lower leaflets in a basal group separated by about 25 cm from upper; leaflets &#177; equal to 30 cm long by 3 cm wide, the lowermost usually somewhat narrower, all leaflets bristly at tip. Inflorescence very short, to 25 cm long, very rarely longer,  with one partial inflorescence only, the axis continuing as a short flagellum beyond this; bracts sparsely to densely spiny; male partial inflorescence branched once only bearing densely crowded flowers to 6 mm long. Female partial inflorescence spike-like or branched once. Female with densely crowded flowers. Ripe fruit to 2.2 cm long including conspicuous beak, by 1.5 cm wide elongate ovoid, covered in 14-18 vertical rows of dull chestnut brown scales with shiny black margins (whole fruit black scaly when young), with very faint groove. Seed angular; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Trengganu: Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Calamus pycnocarpus is a very local rattan known only from Trengganu (Kemaman), where it is common in lowland Dipterocarp forest on gently undulating ground or steep slopes. It is unlike any other Malayan rattan and can easily be distinguished by the combination of characters italicized above. This species is closely related to but distinct from the Bornean rattan Calamus gonospermus Becc.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>