<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops cristata</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Nelle Foreste di Borneo 608 (1902)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 288 (1902)</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(1): 190 (1911)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 60 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Crested</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Moderate clustering rather variable short-stemmed rattan climbing to about 3-4 m tall only; stem without sheaths to c. 15 mm diam., with sheaths to 30 mm diam., usually less, internodes to 20 cm long. Sheath green, armed with partial whorls of brown to black spines and spicules, the longest to c. 20 mm long, and abundant deciduous tomentum; knee inconspicuous. Leaf usually briefly cirrate, to 2 m long including the petiole to 40 cm, and cirrus to 80 cm, usually less; petiole usually bearing very conspicuous large, close, flattened, &#177; erect spines at the base and by the leaf sheath mouth, the longest to c. 12 cm, usually much less; leaflets c. 45 on each side of the rachis, dark green, regularly arranged, gradually tapering at both ends, the longest to c. 35 &#215; 2 cm, usually very bristly on all nerves, but particularly on the main vein on the undersurface, transverse veinlets rather conspicuous. Inflorescences &#177; erect at first, the female rather lax, the male more condensed, in all up to c. 50 cm long; prophyll and other bracts thin, unarmed; male rachilla c. 15 mm long with crowded flowers; female rachilla 7-12 cm long with very distant flowers, the flower cushions oblique. Mature fruit rounded to &#177; oblate, c. 14 &#215; 18 mm, with a short beak and covered with c. 16-20 vertical rows of yellowish brown scales. Seed &#177; rounded or oblate, c. 10 mm diam.; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf pinnate with 3-4 pairs of narrow leaflets. (Fig. 17).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Rather local on ridges and slopes in lowland forest. Also in Sarawak. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>D. cristata is a rattan of hill slopes and ridges in mixed dipterocarp forest. The poorly developed knee, crests of spines, the large erect spines at the petiole base, the regular bristly leaflets and the fruit with numerous yellowish-brown scales help to distinguish it.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6618. Without prov.: BRUN 15092.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>