<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis oropedionis</name>
<author>Beentje</author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 158 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar: Ambohitsaratelo; Dransfield et al.; JD6446</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypus TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>Although the material of this palm is incomplete, it needs a name; it is clearly distinct, and severely threatened. The specific name is Greek for 'of the plateau', referring to the habitat.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>inter species maximas foliolis fasciculatis inflorescentiis multo ramosis pedunculo breve rachillis glabris endospermio ruminato distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm. TRUNK 8-20 m tall, 27-35 cm diam., near the crown c. 20 cm diam.; internodes 10-20 cm, grey-brown but distally green, nodal scars pronounced, 4-5 cm; crownshaft grey-green, covered in white wax. LEAVES tristichous, 6-11 in the crown, porrect to spreading; sheath grey-green, white-waxy, 80-157 cm, without auricles; petiole 25-35 cm long, channelled, densely scaly, 5.5-6 x 4.5-5 cm diam.; rachis c. 3.1 m, in mid-leaf  c. 3.5 cm wide; leaflets 80-172 on each side of the rachis, in groups of 3-9 and fanned within the groups, stiff with the distal 1/3 pendulous, the proximal 80-93 x 1.7-2.1 cm, median 102-110 x 2-3.5 cm, distal 15-43 x 0.8-1.8 cm, main vein 1, plus thickened margins, with few ramenta to 8 mm long, otherwise glabrous, apices unequally bifid, attenuate. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, branched to 3 orders, spreading, 85-130 x 90-100 cm; peduncle 18-40 cm, c. 10 x 6 cm diam., glabrous; prophyll c. 72 x 20 cm, borne at c. 11 cm above the base of the peduncle, erect, split over its length; peduncular bract deciduous, inserted at 18 cm from the base of the peduncle, 87 cm long, 24 cm wide, closed for its distal 7 cm beak; rachis with c. 27 branched and 13 unbranched first order branches, these proximally 3.4-4 x 1.4-1.5 cm diam.; rachis bracts to 7 mm long; rachillae spreading-pendulous, cream, 10-37 cm long, 3.5-5 mm diam., glabrous, with distant</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from two sites on the western side of the central high plateaux.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Relict dry evergreen plateau forest in steepsided valleys; 1100-1450 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Critical. Numbers within the two sites were low; both populations are without real protection, with their habitat under serious threat from annual fires as well as tree-cutting.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Probably closest to D. pilulifera.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Miandrivazo: Ambohitsaratelo, Nov. 1986 (fl., fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6446 (Holotype K; isotype TAN). Ankazobe: Manerinerina, April 1992 (fr.), Beentje et al. 4659 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>