<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops sabut</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Hooker f., Fl. Br. India 6: 469 (1893)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(1): 181 (1911)</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado, Gard. Bull. Singapore 14: 137 (1953)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 109 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 59 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 69 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops annulata</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 227 (1902)</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(1): 174 (1911)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops pseudomirabilis</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(1): 179 (1911)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops turbinata</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(1): 225 (1911)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>From a local name</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Lepoh (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering moderate-sized rattan climbing to 40 m; stem without sheaths c. 15 mm diam., with sheaths to 30 mm diam., internodes to 15 cm long. Sheaths bright green, bearing complete and partial collars to 10 mm, tipped with black and brown horse-hair-like spines, 1-6 cm long, the longesttending to be paler in colour and all bearing abundant dark grey, caducous indumentum, at least some of the collars interlocking to produce ant galleries; knee conspicuous, usually less heavily armed than the sheath. Leaf cirrate, to 2.5 m long including the petiole to 40 cm and the cirrus to 1 m; petiole armed near the base with low collars bearing black spines, distally with scattered or grouped triangular spines; leaflets very variable in arrangement, to c. 20 on each side of the rachis, rarely subregular, usually grouped in 3&amp;rsquo;s to 6&amp;rsquo;s, the basal 2 groups being congested and the leaflets pointing in several directions, the longest usually the most basal, to 40 &#215; 2.5 cm, unarmed except for short marginal bristles. Inflorescences pendulous, to 60 cm long, primary bracts densely armed with fine black spines, all except the prophyll quickly falling at anthesis, other bracts inconspicuous. Mature fruit ovoid, very shortly beaked, c. 16 &#215; 12 mm, rarely spherical, covered with 14-17 vertical rows of yellowish-brown scales. Seed c. 12 &#215; 9 mm; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf with divergent leaflets. (Fig. 23, Pl. 4B).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread throughout Brunei. Elsewhere throughout Borneo and Peninsular Malaysia.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a good quality cane.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>D. sabut is a frequent rattan usually found in moist soils in valley bottoms and lower hill slopes at altitudes up to c. 500 m above sea level. It and D. formicaria are the only species of Daemonorops in Brunei with complete interlocking collars forming ant galleries; D. formicaria is easily distinguished by the narrow linear close, regularly arranged leaflets. We have included three other names as synonyms of D. sabut; although the types of these names appeared to represent distinct species, we now have a range of specimens that are intermediate and we are unable to recognise more than one variable taxon.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Melilas, Sg.Ingei, Wong 637. TUT: Johns 7600; Lamunin, Kpg.Lamunin, Wong 66; Rambai, Bt.Bahak, Coode 7037.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>