<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus erinaceus</name>
<author>(Becc.) J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 32: 484 (1978)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 130 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 94 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 97 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops erinaceus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 225 (1902)</bibref>
</synonymy> 
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus aquatilis</name>
<author>Ridl.</author>
<bibref>Ridl., J. Roy. As. Soc. Str. Br. 41: 43 (1904)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Like a hedgehog)</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Robust clustering rattan tending to form thickets on the landward side of mangrove or behind coastal sand bars; stem climbing to 15 m, without sheaths 2-3.5 cm diam., with sheaths to 5 cm diam., rarely more, internodes to c. 30 cm. Sheaths orange-yellow to yellowish-green when fresh, very densely armed with slender grey-brown spines, 2-35 mm, held horizontally and arranged in horizontal or oblique whorls, spines and sheath epidermis densely covered with grey deciduous indumentum; spines around the leaf sheath mouth upward-pointing, grouped in 5&amp;rsquo;s to 9&amp;rsquo;s, the longest to 60 mm; knee and base of petiole very conspicuous, unarmed, orange-yellow, when young densely covered with indumentum. Leaf cirrate to 4.5 m long including the petiole to 25 cm and cirrus to 2 m; petiole armed along the margins only with grouped spines to 3 cm; leaflets to 70 or more on each side of the rachis, grey-green, very regular, close, limply pendulous, the longest to 40 &#215; 2 cm, armed with short bristles along the margins and on the veins on the lower surface, the lower surface also with white wax and minute brown scales. Inflorescences to 1.5 m with very short peduncle enclosed by the leaf sheath; primary bracts armed with groups of short spines; partial inflorescences about 7 on each side of the axis, gradually decreasing in size distally; male rachillae 1-2 cm long with close distichous flowers; female rachillae 10 cm long with laxer distichous flowers. Fruit rounded, relatively small, to 1 cm diam., covered in 12 vertical rows of straw-coloured scales. Seed rounded, c. 7 mm diam.; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf unknown. (Fig. 32, Pls 8A, 10A)</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Unaccountably rare in Brunei, known from a single collection. Elsewhere abundant in coastal formations throughout Borneo, Sumatra, Peninsular Malaysia and S Thailand, very rare inland.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a medium to low quality coarse cane.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. erinaceus is an unmistakable and very beautiful species. It is one of the distinctive features of forest on the landward fringe of the mangrove; very rarely it can be found away from mangrove, but always near to the sea. Why it should be so rare in Brunei is not understood.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TUT: Telisai, Kpg. Danau, Wong 2094.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>