<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis simianensis</name>
<author>(Jum.) Beentje &amp; J. Dransf.</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 317 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Simianona (Simiane) River; Perrier; 11943</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Neophloga simianensis</name>
<author>Jum.</author>
<bibref>Jum., Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 4, 6 (3): 13 (1929)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum., Cat. Pl. Madagascar, Palmae: 23 (1938)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Fl. Madagascar 30: 61, fig. 15 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A very handsome small palm, with entire, very narrow leaves with only a short notch at the tip. We have never seen the fruit, but this species would make an exquisite ornamental. The name comes from the type locality, which was slightly mis-spelt on the label.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering palm in tufts of 2-12 stems. STEMS 0.5-2 m long, 0.4-1 cm diam., erect or curving; internodes 0.5-2 cm long, distally with reddish laciniate scales. LEAVES 5-15 in the crown, spreading, entire; sheath 4.5-6.6 cm long, pale yellow-brown with scattered reddish scales, densest distally, closed for 60-90%, with oblique opening and minute triangular ligules 2 mm high; petiole 0.5-6.6 cm long, 1.5-2 mm wide, adaxially flat, with a few scattered scales; blade dark green, narrowly triangular, acute at the base, 15-35 x 2.5-4.7 cm, the apex bifid for 2.1-4.2 cm, the apices of the lobes truncate and dentate and 1-1.2 cm wide, only the midrib prominent on both surfaces, with reddish scattered scales, the other veins faint, glabrous, c. 9 on each side of the    rachis. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, erect to spreading, unbranched; peduncle 5.5-24 cm long, c. 1.5 mm diam., proximally with a few scattered scales; prophyll 8-12 cm, borne at 2.5-4 cm above the base of the peduncle, 3 x 2 mm diam., with a few scattered scales mainly on the narrow wings, split only in its distal 5 mm; peduncular bract inserted at 7-8 cm from the base of the peduncle, 4.5-13 cm long, with a few scattered scales, split only in its distal 5 mm; rachilla 5-16 cm long, c. 2 mm diam., glabrous or minutely puberulous, with distant superficial triads; rachilla bract entire, rounded. STAMINATE FLOWERS white; sepals 1.3-1.7 x 1.2 -1.3 mm, keeled, gibbous, rounded, ciliate; petals 1.7-1.8 x 1.1-1.4 mm, ovate, acute, striate, at anthesis hardly opening and leaving an opening of only 0.6 mm wide for the stamens; stamens 6, uniseriate, the filaments connate for 0.2-0.5 mm, in bud 1 mm long but rapidly lengthening at anthesis to c. 2.5 mm, the antepetalous slightly wider than the antesepalous, anthers 1.2-1.4 x 0.5-0.6 mm, dorsifixed, the locules slightly divergent at the base; pistillode c. 1.5 mm, narrowly ovoid, 0.8 mm diam. PISTILLATE FLOWERS unknown except for very young buds. FRUIT unknown, except for the fibrous endocarp with almost free fibres. SEED c. 8 x 6 mm, rounded at both ends, with homogeneous endosperm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Mananara, Soanierana-Ivongo, Zahamena and Manombo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest to rather dry forest; steep to gentle mid slope, soils rocky; 65-250 (-850) m. NATURAL HISTORY. In Manombo HB photographed an insect visitor to the open male flowers, tentatively identified by Dr. Verdcourt as a Sphecoid wasp; it visited several open staminate flowers and inserted its mouth parts. One of the flowers of Beentje &amp; Andriampaniry 4786 is much larger than the others (some 3.5 mm), and it proved to contain a 3 mm long white caterpillar; such galled flowers are of very common occurrence in undergrowth species of Dypsis, particularly in those species with three stamens. Male flowers are open when female buds are still minute.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Endangered. Known from a limited number of sites, with the individual populations consisting of few individuals. Recent collections are few; HB has seen a total of less than forty plants.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Cours 4192 is from higher altitude than the other specimens; it has very short inflorescences with shorter rachillae than usual.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Mananara Avaratra: Antanambe, Oct. 1991 (bud), Beentje 4451 (K, MO, P, TAN). Soanierana-Ivongo: Simiane (Simianona) R, Sept. 1912 (fl.), Perrier 11943 (P, type). Ambatondrazaka: Bemainty, March 1951 (fl.), Cours 4192 (P, TAN). Farafangana: Manombo, Nov. 1991 (bud, seed), Beentje 4518 (BH, K, MO, P, TAN); idem, Jan. 1993 (fl.), Beentje &amp; Andriampaniry 4786 (BH, K, MO, P, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>