<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
	<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A new species of Daemonorops (Arecaceae) from Sekundur Forest, North Sumatra</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
		<mods:name><mods:namePart>Himmah  and </mods:namePart></mods:name>	
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Rustiami</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Zumaidar</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given"></mods:namePart>
</mods:name>	
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Floribunda 2(7)198-200</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
	</taxonxHeader>
	<taxonxBody>
		<treatment rank="species">
			<nomenclature>
				<name>Daemonorops sekundurensis</name>
				<author>Rustiami and Zumaidar</author>
				<citation>Floribunda 2: 198 (2005)</citation>
				<type>Zumaidar 21, North Sumatra, Sekundur forest, Aras Napal;; </type>
				<type_loc>Holotype BO</type_loc>			
			</nomenclature>
			<div type="introduction"><p>Daemonorops  is a rattan genus with a center of diversity in South East Asia, particularly in West Malesia. This genus is easily recognized by having bracts in inflorescence boat-like and easily fallen.  While working on the specimens collected by Zumaidar on her expedition at the Sekundur forest in 2001 we came across of one peculiar new species of  Daemonorops.  This new species belongs to the distinctive group within section  Piptospatha.  That is dragon's blood group. This group can be distinguished by the presence of red resin on its fruit scale.</p></div>
			<div type="diagnosis"><p>Hie species differt ab alius ad collaris forma in geniculatus bases spinus in folium vaginae et rhomboideus fructus cum leviter complanatus in fructus apices.</p></div>
			<div type="etymology"/>
			<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
			<div type="description"><p>Clustering small rattan up to 2 m tall. Leaf sheaths green, covered with jointed bases forming collar spines, scarcely, up to 3 cm long, sheath surface smooth with caducuous reddish-blackish scaly indumentum, leaf sheath mouth armed as the rest of sheath; knee present, very conspicuous, armed as the rest of sheath. Leaves to 3 m long including petiole to 25 cm, armed adaxially with short, erect, scattered spines to 4 mm long, abaxially armed with erect, solitary spines, rarely, up to 15 mm long; rachis unarmed, or armed only slightly proximally; cirrus up to 1.5 m long, armed with regularly arranged groups of grapnel-like spines, blackish at the tip; leaflets mostly arranged regularly, slightly irregular above, 30 on each side of the rachis, stiff, horizontal; leaflets lanceolate, papery, acute, 25-31 cm long, 2.5 cm wide, armed with scattered, reddish, short bristles along the main nerve on both surfaces. Inflorescences pendulous to 35 cm long, peduncle 13-16 cm long, armed distally with groups of spines; peduncular bracts leathery, erect, 17 cm long, 3 cm wide, ellipsoid oblong, covered by rusty indumentum, armed with scattered spines; partial inflorescences 6 each, bearing up to 11 rachillae; involucre pendulous, flat, just above the involucrophore, 5 mm long; involucrophore short, papery, 2 mm long. Female and male flowers unknown. Fruits diamond shape, slightly flat at the top of fruit, 1.5 x 1 cm, covered by 7 vertical rows of reddish brown dragon's blood encrusted scales. Seed ovoid, 18 x 7 mm, surface smooth.</p></div>
			<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
			<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Found on hill slopes in disturbed forest at an altitude of 800 m.</p></div>
			<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
			<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
			<div type="discussion"><p>Presumably its dragon's blood fruit can be used as dying or furnishing as like the other dragon's blood species. This is a very distinctive taxon that remains poorly known.  Daemonorops sekundurensis  appears to be most closely allied to  D. siberutensis  (Rustiami 2002) and  D. dracuncula  (Beccari 1911) by its small habit. However, this species differs from the other dragon's blood species by collar shape on jointed bases spines on the leaf sheath and diamond fruit shape with slightly flattened on top of fruit. As yet, this species is only known to occur in Sekundur forest area.</p></div>
			<div type="materials_examined"><p>North Sumatra, Sekundur forest, Aras Napal, Zumaidar 21.</p></div>
		</treatment>
	</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>