<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus crassifolius</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 45: 94 (1990)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Thick leaves</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering rattan climbing to 10 m; stem without sheaths c. 7 - 10 mm diam., with sheaths c. 10 - 18 mm diam., internodes 7-12 cm long. Sheath mid green, armed with short scattered or grouped triangular spines to 3 mm with conspicuous swollen bases and scattered brown scales between the spines; knee conspicuous; ocrea soon tattering, inconspicuous. Flagellum to 1.5 m. Leaf ecirrate, to c. 75 cm including the petiole and leaflets; petiole 4 - 11 cm, very sparsely armed; rachis very short; leaflets one on each side of the rachis, broad, to c. 60 x 12 cm, stiff, cucullate, very thick in texture, dark shiny green when fresh, transverse ve inlets very numerous, close, conspicuous. Inflorescence, only the young female known, with 3 partial inflorescences and lacking a terminal flagellum; bracts closely tubular, covered in pale brown indumentum; rachillae c. 20 x 2 mm bearing roughened bracts. Fruit not known (Fig. 71).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known only from Pasir Jangka and Sempadi Forest Reserves in the extreme west of 1st Division. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane appears to be of good quality.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. crassifolius is found at low altitudes in forest transitional between kerangas and mixed dipterocarp forest. It is easily distinguished by the single pair of leaflets of thick texture and the presence of a flagellum. It might be confused with C. flabellatus but the latter generally has very thin matt leaflets, joined for much of their length rather than only at the base, and the inflorescence with its long flagellum is quite different.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>