<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis ramentacea</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 411 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Mananara, Antanambe; Beentje; 4458</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi BH, MO, P, TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>This pretty little palm is known from a single collection from forest undergrowth in the lowlands near to Mananara Avaratra. The species name refers to the scales (ramenta) on the undersurface of the leaves.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Habitu inflorescentiaque D. louvelii superficialiter similis sed petiolo longiori, pagina inferiori laminae ramentas ferenti rachillis inflorescentiae papillosis differt (floribus ignotis). </p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender solitary forest undergrowth palmlet to 70 cm tall. STEMS c. 4-5 mm diam., when dry, when fresh to 8 mm diam., internodes 4-12 mm long, sparsely and minutely scaly. LEAVES 9-10 in crown, apparently marcescent, crownshaft poorly defined; sheath 5-6 cm long, 1 cm diam., rather densely covered in caducous dark red-brown indumentum; auricles triangular, to 5 x 3 mm, membranous, soon tattering; petiole 9-15 cm long, c. 2 mm wide, &#177; triangular in section, bearing scattered dark brown scales; lamina entire 25-31 cm long, deeply bifid, the rachis 8-9.5 cm, the two lobes to 18-22 x 3.5 cm, diverging at an acute angle, the lobes shallowly toothed, adaxial lamina surface with   sparse, minute brown punctiform scales, abaxial surface with conspicuous, abundant dark brown ramenta on all major veins and scattered red-brown punctiform scales. INFLORESCENCES 25-30 cm long, arching or semi-horizontal, branching to 1 order; peduncle to 21 cm, 1 mm diam., covered in discrete elevated dark brown scales; prophyll to 15 x 0.4 cm, membranous, straw-coloured, with sparse dark scales; peduncular bract exceeding the prophyll by 7 cm, similar to prophyll; rachis 5-6 cm; rachillae 8-10 in number, 2-3.5 cm long, c. 0.6 mm diam., with dark brown papillae, triads 1-3 mm distant. FLOWERS said to be red in bud, opening white, not available. Mature FRUIT bright red, ovoid, 13 x 8 mm; seed 1-2 x 6 mm; endosperm homogeneous, embryo lateral near the base.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Mananara, Antanambe.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest; 115 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Critical; found in a tiny patch of forest near agricultural land; individuals seen less than twenty-five.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Although no flowers have been available for study, the habit and inflorescence structure suggests that this is probably a species of Dypsis with three stamens and is certainly undescribed. Because it is so distinctive, we have named it D. ramentacea, even though staminate flowers that would suggest relationships are missing. The inflorescence is reminiscent of that of D. louvelii but the rachillae are distinctive in the presence of dark papillae. The undersurface of the leaf bears abundant ramenta, whence the specific epithet. Such ramenta are also present in D. mocquerysiana but this species has a very different erect inflorescence with many rachillae, and the leaves are usually epetiolate. There is also a superficial similarity with D. glabrescens but in the latter ramenta are absent, there is no petiole and the rachillae are shorter.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Mananara Avaratra: Antanambe, 1.5 hours walk upstream from first ferry north of Antanambe, Oct. 1991 (fr.), Beentje 4458 (Holotype K; isotypes BH, MO, P, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>