<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis tsaravoasira</name>
<author>Beentje </author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 154 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Sahavary, hills E of village, Andilampananina; Dransfield et al.; JD6463</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi P, TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A majestic, tristichous palm. The leaves are in three ranks. Although the material is incomplete, this isclearly a distinct taxon. The name derives from the local name.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Tsaravoasira, Hovotravavy, avaboko (Betsimisaraka).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>inter species maximas tristichas foliolis regulariter dispositis inflorescentiis multo ramosis numero foliolorum infra glandibus dispersis tectorum distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm. TRUNK 10-25 m, 18-40 cm diam, prominently ringed above, scarcely below, 7.5-25 cm across near crown, internodes 5-15 cm, pale brown, distally green. Crownshaft green, swollen, 1-1.5 m. Wood pink. LEAVES 5-9, tristichous, porrect, stiff to arcuate; sheath 69-150 cm long, 12 cm across, green, distally densely scaly, with or without irregular ligule c. 22 mm; petiole 0-13 cm, distally 4.5 x 4 cm, densely scaly to glabrous; rachis strongly arcuate, 2-3.5 m long, glabrous or scaly, in mid-leaf 2-3 cm wide; leaflets 102-120 on each side of the rachis, regular, stiff to arcuate, dull dark green, the ones on opposite sides of the rachis in one plane or at a slight angle, less  conspicuously so near the tip, mid-green, proximal leaflets 68-135 x 0.5-3.1 cm with conspicuous pendulous reins, median 81-127 x 2.2-3 cm (interval 1.5-3  cm), distal 10-48 x 0.2-2 cm, apex single or bifid, unequal, main vein 1, thickened margins, rest faint, scattered tufts of ramenta, and with a few  scattered scales on the minor veins. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, branching to 3 orders, arching with pendulous rachillae; peduncle 22-26 cm, strongly curved, distally c. 4 x 3 cm, with scattered scales; prophyll 41-54 cm, borne at 6-9.5 cm above the base of the peduncle, c. 14 cm wide, persistent, pale brown abaxially, chestnut-red adaxially; peduncular bract inserted at c. 14 cm above the base of the peduncle, deciduous; rachis 47-50 cm, first order branches 14-20, 15 x 9 mm across, glabrous or with minute scattered scales, all axes green; rachillae cream-coloured, pendulous, 13-53 cm, 3-4 mm across, glabrous; triads spaced to dense, sunken; rachilla bract obtuse. STAMINATE FLOWERS only known in young bud. PISTILLATE FLOWERS in young fruit with sepals 2.8-3.7 x 4-5.2 mm, ciliolate; petals 4.5-5 x 5.6-6 mm; staminodes c. 1.2mm long. Young FRUIT 4-5 x 5-5.5 mm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from Marojejy, Maroantsetra and Mananara.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Open primary forest, steep upper slopes or ridgetop hollows; 275-1050 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Endangered. Only known from three sites, two of which are under agricultural pressure; numbers within the populations are low, and we have seen less than thirty altogether.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Palm-heart edible and highly esteemed.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This taxon resembles D. pilulifera but is distinct by the regular leaflets and the presence of scattered scales on the leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Andapa: Marojejy E, N of Mandena, Nov. 1989 (y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6760 (K, P, TAN). Maroantsetra, Sahavary, hills E of village, Andilampananina, Feb. 1988 (y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6463 (Holotype K; isotypes P, TAN); Antanambe, Oct. 1991, (dead infl.), Beentje &amp; Andriampaniry 4467 (K, TAN).
Allied Specimen: close, but with clear differences are two specimens from Andapa: Marojejy, Nov. 1984 (y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6762 (K, P, TAN); idem, S base of Mt. Beondroka, Oct. 1989 (dead infl.), Miller &amp; Randrianasolo 4493 (K, P, TAN); local names: Voanioala, Lavaboko, Tsaravoasira. A solitary palm 15-20 m high, 15-20 cm diam., with 8-10 tristichous leaves; leaf sheath 62 cm, hardly scaly; petiole 0-5 cm; rachis c. 4 m with c. 70 leaflets on each side, the median 85-104 x 3.3-3.6 cm. Inflorescence branched to 2 orders; rachillae pink, 11-26 cm long, 3-4.5 mm diam., glabrous, with distant triads in slight pits. No flowers have been seen; fruit only seen when young. Similar is possibly Moore 9919 from Masoala: Ambohitralanana, April 1971 (fr.) with the leaf sheath c. 90 cm, petiole 45 cm, rachis 3.2 m, but this has interfoliar inflorescences with rachillae 19-29 cm and fruits 16-17 x 12-13 mm, with homogeneous endosperm; the leaves are said to be in five ranks. The local name is Buresy.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>