<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis lanuginosa</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 395 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, lower basin of Mangoro; Perrier; 18050</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>Represented by a single herbarium specimen collected in 1922. We know little about this undergrowth palmlet. Its most distinctive feature is the densely woolly inflorescence with a large number of rachillae. Superficially it resembles D. eriostachys, but the latter has staminate flowers with six rather than three stamens. The species name refers to the woolly hairs on the inflorescence.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Gregem specierum floribus staminatis triandris staminibus antepetalis, staminodiis antesepalis alternantibus pertinens, folio magno integrobifido inflorescentia lanuginosa distincta; D. lantzeanae superficialiter similis sed positione staminum omnino diversa.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>  
Slender clustering undergrowth palm to 4 m tall. STEM 13 mm diam., but said to reach 40 mm diam., internodes 24-27 mm long, covered in dark brown caducous scales. LEAF with sheath c. 15 cm long, c. 2 cm diam., distally very densely covered with thick red-brown tomentum and scales; auricles ill-defined; petiole absent; rachis 38-44 cm; blade entire bifid or with very small basal leaflets, otherwise entire-bifid, probably undulate and bullate; basal leaflets where present 7-11 x 0.4-1 cm, blade to 48 cm long, gradually widening from c. 4 cm near the base to widest at the tip where 18 cm, the two lobes with a broad sinus, and shallowly to deeply lobed apically, adaxially with minute brown punctiform scales, abaxially minutely roughened and with irregular bands of caducous dark brown scales. INFLORESCENCE probably erect, branching to 2 orders; peduncle 40 cm long, c. 4 mm wide at the base tapering to 3 mm diam. distally, loosely shaggy hairy; prophyll inserted at least 3.5 cm above the base, 28 x 0.7 cm, with scattered dark and pale stellate and shaggy hairs; peduncular bract exceeding the prophyll by 9 cm; rachis 25 cm; rachillae numerous, probably at least 100, c. 2-2.5 cm long, c. 1 mm diam., densely covered in pale brown shaggy hairs, triads c. 1-1.5 mm apart, rachilla bracts rounded, c. 0.5 mm high, obscured by hairs. Immature STAMINATE FLOWER buds c. 0.5 mm diam.; stamens 3, antepetalous. Other parts unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Lower Mangoro.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland forest; 300 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Presumed extinct. Not collected for more than seventy years. The forests of the lower Mangoro River have now disappeared.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Although known from a single collection, this appears to be a distinctive species. The leaves are entire bifid or with two very small basal leaflets, and otherwise entire bifid, and there is no petiole. Drying of the specimen suggests that in the living state the leaf was probably beautifully undulate and bullate. The shaggyhairy inflorescence is similar to that of D. lantzeana but instead of having three antesepalous stamens, the three stamens are antepetalous.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Mahanoro: lower basin of Mangoro, forest vestiges, Oct. 1922 (fl.), Perrier 18050 (Holotype P).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>