<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus divaricatus Becc. var. divaricatus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 10 (1913)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 152 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 168 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Widely divergent</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering rattan climbing to 15 m, very rarely &#177; "stemless"; stem without sheaths 5-7.5 mm diam., with sheaths to 20 mm, usually less, internodes to 12 cm. Sheaths bright green armed with short triangular horizontal spines to 5 mm, united by their bases to form low ridges, these interspersed with low ridges bearing minute tooth-like spines, all covered in deciduous grey indumentum; knee conspicuous, armed as the rest of the sheath; ocrea to 5 mm, ridged, irregularly tattering. Flagellum to 1 m. Leaf ecirrate, to c. 1.1 m including the petiole to 15 cm; petiole armed with short spines to 7 mm and minute scattered prickles; leaflets up to c. 17 on each side of the rachis, distant, usually &#177; reflexed and subopposite in proximal part, strictly opposite and divaricate near the tip, the apical pair often &#177; reflexed, the longest at the base, to 30 &#215; 2.5 cm, decreasing to 8.5 &#215; 1 cm, &#177; unarmed, young leaflets tinged pink. Inflorescences to c. 1 m including terminal flagellum, the female usually with only 1 partial inflorescence, the male with 2-3; bracts conspicuous, those subtending partial inflorescences usually splitting neatly to produce a limb, armed with ridges and scattered spines; axis of female partial inflorescence to c. 12 cm, rather robust, scabrid, bearing c. 12 short reflexed rachillae on each side; rachillae to 3 cm bearing densely crowded flowers; male partial inflorescence laxer, to 20 cm with proximal branches also branched further and with all axes scabrid, male flowers densely crowded. Mature fruit top-shaped, to 16 &#215; 10 mm, including the beak to 1 mm, and covered in 16 vertical rows of chestnut brown scales. Seed pointed, c. 8 &#215; 6 mm, irregularly pitted but endosperm homogeneous. (Fig. 61).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from a single collection from Temburong. Widespread in Sarawak and Sabah, rare in Kalimantan. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. divaricatus var. divaricatus has been recorded from montane forest on Bt. Tudal. In Sabah it seems to be much more a plant of the lowlands. It is immediately distinguishable by the combination of ecirrate leaf, rugose sheaths and divaricate leaflets. On Bukit Batu Patam grows a rattan very similar in texture and leaf sheath armature to C. divaricatus var. divaricatus but the leaflets are not typically divaricate and the bracts in the inflorescence are not minutely spiny. Unfortunately, it is represented by a single collection with dead inflorescences - Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6586 - and its true identity will remain uncertain until it is recollected (see Fig. 62).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Bukit Tudal, Davis 461.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>