<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus poensis</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 43 (1913)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>From G Pueh, the type locality</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary (?) or clustered (?) rather slender rattan climbing to 5 m tall; stem without sheaths c. 8 mm diam., with to c. 15 mm diam., internodes short. Sheath mottled yellowish and reddish-brown, bearing scattered, slightly reflexed yellowish-based spines, 6-12 mm long and abundant indumentum between the spines; knee poorly developed; ocrea rather conspicuous, to 5 mm long. Flagellum apparently present. Leaves ecirrate to c. 80 cm long including the petiole to c. 16 cm; petiok armed with regular lateral spines to 30 mm long; leaflets c. 20 on each side of th( rachis, arranged in groups of 2 - 8, the apical c. 3 -4 leaflets on each side crowdei together and radiating, the leaflet bases slightly swollen, the longest leaflets 30 - 35: 1.8-2 cm, bristly along the midrib and margins, transverse veinlets conspicuous Inflorescences long, slender, with a terminal flagellum, to c. 2.3 m, with 4 very la partial inflorescences; male rachillae c. 2 - 2.5 cm long; female rachillae to c. 5 ci long. Young fruit ovoid, beaked, covered in 17 vertical rows of dark brown scale: Other details not known (Fig. 93).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known only from two collections from the summit of G Pueh. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. poensis is a little known species occurring in low mossy forest on the summit of G Pueh. In 19811 searched for it but without success; it seems likely that the two collections were made on the summit of a higher peak elsewhere in the G Pueh Range. From herbarium material it seems to be close to C. marginatus but is immediately distinguished by the grouped leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>