<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Genera Palmarum. The evolution and classification of palms</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Uhl</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">N.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Asmussen</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Baker</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">W.J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Harley</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2008</mods:dateIssued><mods:publisher>Kew Publishing, Royal Botanic Gardens Kew</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="genus">
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Extremely variable genus of mostly rather small solitary or clustering palms from rain forest in Central and South America, with distinctive anthers with divergent thecae.</p></div>
<nomenclature>
<name>Geonoma</name>
<author>Willd.</author> 
<citation>Sp. pl. 4(1): 174, 593 (1805).</citation>
<type>Lectotype; Geonoma simplicifrons; Willd.</type>
<synonymy>
<name>Vouay</name>
<author>Aubl.</author>
<bibref>Aubl., Hist. pl. Guiane 2 (Appendix): 99 (1775)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Gynestum</name>
<author>Poit.</author>
<bibref>Poit., Mém Mus. Hist. Nat. 9: 387 (1822).</bibref>
<type>Lectotype; Gynestum maximum; Poit.</type>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Roebelia</name>
<author>Engel</author>
<bibref>Engel, Linnaea 33: 680 (1865).</bibref>
<type>Type; Roebelia solitaria; Engel</type>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Kalbreyera</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<bibref>Burret, Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 63: 142 (1930).</bibref>
<type>Type; Kalbreyera triandra; Burret</type>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Taenianthera</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<bibref>Burret, Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 63: 267 (1930).</bibref>
<type>Type; Taenianthera macrostachys; (Mart.) Burret</type>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="etymology"><p>Geonomos — colonist, presumably referring to the clustering, spreading habit of many species.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Small to moderate, solitary or clustered, unarmed, pleonanthic, monoecious palms. Stem very short, subterranean, erect, or creeping, slender, sometimes tall, enclosed by thin leaf sheaths, becoming bare, usually cane-like, ringed with close or distant, conspicuous or inconspicuous leaf scars. Leaves pinnate, regularly or irregularly divided, or entire and bifid; sheath short, splitting opposite the petiole, margins fibrous, glabrous or variously tomentose; petiole short to long, slightly grooved or flattened adaxially, rounded abaxially, glabrous or tomentose; blade bifid, or with 2 or 3 pairs of leaflets, or irregularly divided, or nearly evenly pinnate, thin and papery or somewhat leathery, usually glabrous adaxially, glabrous, tomentose or with scales abaxially, especially along the main ribs, uniseriate hairs present or absent, midribs of single folds conspicuous, transverse veinlets not evident. Inflorescences solitary, interfoliar or infrafoliar, spicate, forked, or branched to 3(–4) orders, protandrous where known; peduncle very short to very long, glabrous or tomentose; prophyll tubular, short to long, pointed, very briefly 2-keeled laterally, membranous or leathery, glabrous or variously tomentose; peduncular bracts (0–)1(–2), short or long, deciduous or persistent, like the prophyll; rachillae straight or folded and twisted in bud, short to moderate, bearing rounded, truncate, or distally split, ± raised bracts, laterally adnate to the branch, decussate, spiral, or whorled and in definite rows, bracts closely appressed and the rachillae larger than the peduncle in diameter, or bracts more distant and the rachillae narrow, each bract subtending a triad of flowers sunken in a pit, pits without upper lip or upper lip distinct, glabrous or hairy, pit cavity glabrous or variously hairy; floral bracteoles 3, irregular, small, membranous. Staminate flowers about 1/2 exserted from the pit; sepals 3, distinct, chaffy, narrow, elongate, tips rounded, keeled or not; petals 3, connate for 2/3 their length, tips distinct, valvate; stamens (3) 6 (rarely more), filaments united with receptacle in a stalk-like base, connate in a tube above the base, free, narrow, flat, long or short distally, inflexed near the tip in bud, anthers borne at tips of the filaments, connective divided, thecae elongate, free and divaricate, or short and united, introrse; pistillode small, round, 3-lobed. Pollen ellipsoidal, usually with either slight or obvious asymmetry; aperture a distal sulcus; ectexine tectate, coarsely perforate or perforate and/or micro-channelled, and rugulate, aperture margin usually slightly finer; infratectum columellate; longest axis 22–48 µm [28/59]. Pistillate flowers sunken in the pit with only the tips of the floral organs exserted; sepals 3, united basally and adnate to the receptacle, often keeled, free and imbricate distally; petals 3, connate in a soft tube, briefly adnate to receptacle basally, ending in 3, valvate, chaffy, spreading lobes; staminodes united in a tube, truncate, 6-toothed or 6-lobed, lobes, if present, spreading at anthesis, tubes basally adnate to the receptacle, and sometimes also the corolla tube; gynoecium tricarpellate but 2 carpels vestigial at anthesis, unilocular, uniovulate, ovule anatropous, style tubular, lateral to basal, elongate, ending in 3 linear stigmas, recurved at anthesis. Fruit ±globose, sometimes somewhat pointed, green, brown, or purple-black, 1-seeded, stigmatic remains basal, the rachillae often becoming brightly coloured; epicarp, thin smooth, mesocarp thin, with narrow longitudinal fibres, endocarp thin, crustaceous to membranous. Seed ± globose, hilum short, basal, raphe encircling the seed, endosperm homogeneous; embryo erect basal. Germination adjacent-ligular; eophyll bifid. Cytology: 2n = 28.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Fifty-nine or more species ranging from Mexico to Brazil and Bolivia.</p></div>
<div type="anatomy"><p>Leaf (Tomlinson 1961, Roth 1990), root (Seubert 1998a, 1998b), floral (Uhl and Moore 1971, Stauffer and Endress 2003), and leaf and fruit (Wessels Boer 1968). </p></div>
<div type="relationships"><p>Geonoma is monophyletic with high support (Asmussen 1999a, Roncal et al. 2005). The genus is resolved as sister to a clade of Calyptronoma and Calyptrogyne with low support (Asmussen et al. 2006) or as sister to Asterogyne also with low support (Baker et al. in review).</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Many species are desirable ornamentals; some are also used for thatch. Young ‘cabbage’ is sometimes eaten.</p></div>
<div type="taxonomic accounts"><p>Wessels Boer (1968); see also Henderson et al. (1995). </p></div>
<div type="fossil record"><p>Pinnate leaf material (Phoenicites/Geonomites/ Hemiphoenicites) from the Tertiary of Italy (Verona) was first described by de Visiani (1864); the genus has since been sunk into the synonomy of the redefined Phoenicites of Read and Hickey (1972). Other records of Geonomites include that of Berry (1924): G. claibornensis from the Middle Eocene Claiborne Flora of southeastern North America. Whether the fossil genus has any affinity with extant Geonoma seems doubtful. </p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The reduction of two locules in the gynoecium makes this, the largest genus in the tribe, immediately distinct from the other genera. Sometimes a definite ‘upper lip’ on the pit-closing bracts is lacking.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>For local names, see Glassman (1972).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>All species are understorey rain forest palms, occurring at low to high elevations, including some of the highest elevations recorded for palms in South America. (G. weberbaueri has been recorded at 3150 m above sea level [Henderson et al. 1995].)</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>
