<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Leucothrinax morrisii, a New Name for a Familiar Caribbean Palm</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.E.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Zona</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms 52(2) 84-88</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2008</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Leucothrinax morrisii</name>
<author>(H.Wendl.) C.Lewis &amp; Zona</author>
<citation>Palms 52: 87 (2008).</citation>
<synonymy>
<name>Thrinax morrisii</name>
<author>H. Wendl.</author>
<bibref>H. Wendl., Gard. Chron. 1891(1): 700. 1891</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p></p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread and common in the Caribbean region, Leucothrinax morrisii occurs across a range of habitats in Florida, the Greater Antilles, and the western Lesser Antilles.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>It has a conservation status of “least concern” (Zona et al. 2007) under the World Conservation Union criteria (IUCN 2006). Nevertheless, it represents unexpected diversity in the Caribbean palm flora and suggests that further phylogenetic research may uncover additional surprises. This research must be done quickly, as many Caribbean palms are in rapid decline, along with the threatened areas they inhabit (Zona et al. 2007).</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Leucothrinax morrisii is one of the most familiar cultivated palms of the Caribbean region and is also found in tropical gardens and conservatories worldwide. Its status as a distinct, monotypic genus had been, until now, unrecognized, as it shares many visible features with Thrinax excelsa, T. parviflora and T. radiata. Using molecular tools that were unavailable to earlier taxonomists, we were able to show a clear distinction between Leucothrinax and related palms.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>