<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia hispida</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Malesia 2: 72 (1884)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 154 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Gard. Bull. Singapore 26: 239-244 (1973)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen 50 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 36: 192 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 30 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 37 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Hispid</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Asas, Wi Semut (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering moderate rattan with stems to 30m branching in the canopy; stem without sheaths to 1.5 cm diam., with sheaths to 2.5 cm diam., internodes to 12 cm long. Sheaths bright green, with deciduous chocolate-coloured scales, sparse black spines to 2.5 cm and sparse black brittle spicules; ocrea very conspicuous to c. 25 &#215; 5 cm, diverging from the stem at an acute angle, the two edges inrolled, armed with black spines to 2.5 cm, abundant black brittle spicules and deciduous chocolate-coloured scales; ants usually abundant and very noisy. Leaf to 1.5 m including cirrus to 75 cm and petiole to 20 cm; leaflets up to 7 on each side of the rachis, very shortly stalked, to 25 &#215; 10 cm, bright green on upper surface, whitish beneath. Inflorescences produced from topmost 2-4 nodes, crowded but not forming a head; bracts densely covered in chocolatecoloured scales and black spicules; rachillae few, large, to 20 &#215; 1.5 cm, with conspicuous bracts. Fruit rounded to somewhat oblong, to 2.2 &#215; 1.9 cm, shortly beaked, covered in 15 vertical rows of reddish-brown scales. Seed ovoid to 1.4 &#215; 1.2 cm; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 9, Pl. 1B).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from scattered localities throughout Brunei at altitudes up to 300 m above sea level. Elsewhere throughout Borneo though never common; very local in Sumatra and Peninsular Malaysia.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>K. hispida tends to occur in disturbed forest on steep slopes - e.g. on old land slips or along steep-sided river valleys in lowland and hill dipterocarp forest at altitudes up to 900 m above sea level.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known, though it probably has properties similar to other Korthalsia species.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Labi, Wong 540; Labi, Wong Kadir, Coode 7231. TEM: Amo, Kuala Belalong, Stockdale 31; Batu Apoi, Selapon, Dransfield J. 7494. TUT: Lamunin, Ladan Hills F.R., Wong 1663.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>