<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus endauensis</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 330.</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>Endau - from Ulu Endau, the type locality</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering, slender rattan climbing to 25 m tall, forming close clumps. Stem without sheaths 7 mm in diameter, with sheaths 1.5 cm; internodes 10-20 cm long Sheaths dull mid-green, armed rather densely with horizontal flat hairy-margined black spines to 2 cm long by 5 mm wide; brown indumentum scattered between spines. Vestigial flagellum to 8 cm long present Knee prominent. Ocrea rather large, to 2 cm long, densely dark in-dumentose quickly tattering. Leaf cirrate to 1.75 m long including the cirrus to 80 cm; petiole absent; leaflets about 15 on each side of the rachis, grouped in 4 groups of 2-5 leaflets, regularly arranged within the groups; groups subopposite; largest leaflet to about 30 cm long by 2.7 cm wide; upper leaflet surface unarmed, lower surface armed with short brown bristles along midrib, margins armed with black bristles. Male inflorescence to 1 m in length with first bract to 25 cm long armed with scattered and grouped triangular spines to 4 x 3 mm; allbracts tubular at the base, but conspicuously tattering in the upper pan; lowermost partial inflorescence to about 30 cm long all with tattering bracts; rachillae very short, rarely more than 1 cm in length. Fruit not known. Seedling not known.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Johore; endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a cane of good appearance.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species is known from one collection from the foot of G. Janing, Ulu Endau in Johore on hillslopes in hill Dipterocarp forest at 200 m altitude.
 This is a very distinctive species easily recognized by the characters emphasized above. It and C. ulur are the only species of rattan in Malaya that bear vestigial flagella. C. endau-ensis, unlike C. ulur, does not have partial whorls of spines, and the leaflets are much narrower.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>