<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Guide to Philippine Flora and Fauna. Vol. IV.</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">de Guzman</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">E.D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Fernando</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">E.S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Natural resources Management Center, Minstry of Natural Resources and university of Phillipines</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1986</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia scaphigeroides</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Philipp. J. Sci., C 4: 619 (1909)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Ant Palm (Engl.); Kaporigid (Pil.).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Rather slender, the sheathed stem apparently 15-18 mm in diameter. Ochrea elongate-elliptic, ventricose 9 to 10 cm long, 2 cm broad, thinly coriaceous, armed with small scattered, short, rigid prickles. Leaves with a slender biconvex, flattened petiolar part, about 20 cm long, 4 mm broad, with rather obtuse and smooth edges, armed claws, rachis in the intermediate portion armed almost regularly with ternate claws, leaflets distinctly ansate, narrowly rhomboid-cuneate, broadest above their middle, 15 to 20 cm long, 4 to 5 cm broad, rather accurately praemorse-dentate in the upper margins and produced at the summit into an acuminate point, green above, white beneath, with about 7 primary costae. Spadix unknown. The leaf-sheaths of this palm is interestingly inhabited by colonies of ants. The seeds, so far, is the means of its propagation.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Mindanao (Agusan, Surigao, Zamboanga), Basilan. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Growing in primary forests at low altitudes.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Indeterminate.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>It can be used as those of Daemonorops and Calamus in furniture and basket making.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>