<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus pygmaeus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Malesia 3: 62 (1886)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 205 (1902)</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 252 (1908)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Pertaining to the Pygmies, i.e. very small</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>wi anak (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender dwarf clustering rattan to c. 30 cm tall, spreading by new plantlets borne at the tips of the inflorescences', stem without sheaths c. 6 mm diam., with sheaths to 10 mm diam., internodes c. 5 cm long. Sheath dull brown, bearing rather few groups of horizontal or slightly reflexed triangular spines to 6 mm and abundant brown indumentum between the spines; knee absent; ocrea short, membranous, soon tattering. Flagellum, as distinct from inflorescences, absent. Leaf ecirrate to c. 75 cm long including the petiole 15 - 30 cm; petiole armed with whorls of horizontal spines near the base, unarmed distally; rachis unarmed (?always); leaflets 20 - 30 on each side of the rachis, regularly arranged, the largest to 15 x 1 cm, armed with short bristles on the upper surface, &#177; unarmed beneath. Inflorescences very slender, whip-like, to 2 m long, rooting at their tips and developing into new plantlets; partial inflorescences up to c. 5, distant, very sparsely branched and few-flowered, rarely exceeding 2.5 cm. Mature fruit &#177; rounded, c. 7.5 mm diam., with a short beak, and covered in 14 vertical rows of straw-coloured, brown margined scales. Seed slightly flattened and irregularly shallowly pitted, c. 5mm diam.; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known (Fig. 88).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known with certainty only from the summit of G Matang (G Serapi) near Kuching; sterile plants observed on G Gading may also belong here. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. pygmaeus is abundant in ridge top forest at altitudes of 700 - 800 m above sea level, where it forms great patches in the forest undergrowth. It and a form of C. nematospadix from G Gaharu are the only species in which the inflorescence produces young plantlets at its tip as a regular feature.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>