<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus holttumii</name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<citation>Gdns. Bull. Singapore 15 (1956) 228.</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>R.E. Holttum - eminent tropical botanist, one-time director of Botanic Gardens Singapore</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rota n peru t ay a m</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary rattan climbing to 15 m tall, usually less. Stem without sheaths to 10 mm in diameter, with sheaths to 2 cm; internodes about 15 cm long. All parts dull becoming reddish tinged on drying. Sheaths dull green armed with abundant bulbous-based spines to 1 cm long by 5 mm wide and abundant sinuous rough ridges. Knee conspicuous armed as the leaf sheath. Ocrea to 1 cm high. Flagellum to 2 m long. Leaf ecirrate to 1 m including petiole to 30 cm long; leaflets very variable, from 4 to 15 on each side, very broad (30 cm long by 5 cm wide) or narrow (30 cm long by 1.5 cm wide), with many intermediates, &#177; unarmed. Inflorescences to 1.5 m long, the male more highly branched than the female, with bracts rather densely spiny and armed with rough ridges. Mature fruit to about 1 cm in diameter, rounded, very shortly beaked covered in 15 vertical rows of green, drying brown scales; seed about 6 mm in diameter. Endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Johore, Trengganu. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane of good quality (5-10 mm) but probably too rare to be of much significance.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Calamus holttumii is a variable plant; the type specimen from G. Panti has relatively narrow leaflets, though most of the living population at the same locality has broad leaflets.
Yet in every other respect the plants are similar. For differences from C. tanakadatei see under the latter species. C. holttumii is known from three localities - Ulu Endau and G. Panti in Johore, and Bt. Bauk in Trengganu. It grows in all three localities in hill forest on humus rich soil.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>