<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis lucens</name>
<author>(Jum.) Beentje &amp; J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 315 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Antongil Bay; Perrier; 12032</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Neophloga lucens</name>
<author>Jum.,</author>
<bibref>Jum., Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 4, 6 (3): 15 (1929)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum., Cat. Pl. Madagascar Palmae: 21 (1938)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Fl. Madagascar 30: 62 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>Only known from the type, which consists of loose pieces of leaf and a few rachillae. These are nevertheless enough to distinguish it from other taxa. The name is Latin for 'shiny', and this presumably refers to the leaf when it is fresh.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Palm up to 60 cm. STEM 0.7-1 cm diam. LEAVES c.10; sheath 6.5-7.5 cm long, 1-1.2 cm diam., partly open, red-brown, covered    in small dark red-brown scales; petiole absent; lamina entire, shiny, narrowly triangular, 25-30 cm long, midrib 17-19 cm, lobed for 8-12 cm, the lobes 2.4-3.7 cm wide, the apices 5-10 mm wide and toothed, also toothed along the upper outer margins, adaxially with c. 9 prominent veins, abaxially covered in many small scales, intermixed with 2-5 mm long ramenta on the main veins. INFLORESCENCE 44-47 cm long, unbranched; peduncle 23-27 cm long, 1.5-2 mm diam., with a few minute scales; prophyll 8-11 cm long, 5-6 mm wide, borne at 0.5-3 cm above the base of the peduncle, opening near the apex only for c. 1 cm, with scattered scales; peduncular bract inserted at 5-8 cm from the base of the peduncle, 13-15 cm long, split for the distal 1 cm, with scattered scales; non-tubular bracts 2, 2-2.5 mm long; rachilla 23-24 cm long, 1-1.5 mm diam., glabrous; triads distant, the rachilla bract small and triangular. STAMINATE FLOWERS only known from an early bud stage; sepals 1.4-1.7 x 1-1.3 mm, ciliolate; petals 2.1-2.4 x 1.2 mm; stamens 6, biseriate (offset 0.2 mm), filaments c. 0.5 mm, anthers 0.5-0.6 mm, still in a very tight cone, the locules parallel. PISTILLATE FLOWERS unknown. FRUIT and seed unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from the type: 'Antongil Bay area'.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Rain forest; c. 400 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Probably extinct; not seen since the type was collected over eighty years ago.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>There is a bit of a mystery regarding the pistillate flowers; Jumelle gives a brief, non-committal description in the protologue which could refer to any pistillate flower in the Dypsidinae, but there is none on the type. The specimen has the appearance of D. concinna, with an unbranched inflorescence, but there is no petiole.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Maroantsetra: Antongil Bay area, Oct. 1912 (bud), Perrier 12032 (Holotype P).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>