<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus mattanensis</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2:216 (1902)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11:449(1908)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>C. mattanensis var. sabut</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 110 (1913)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>C. ferrugineus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 216 (1902)</bibref>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 488 (1908)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>From G Matang, the type locality</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary or clustering, moderate rattan climbing to 15 m, but usually much shorter; stem without sheaths to 8 mm diam., with sheaths to 18 mm diam., internodes c. 15 cm long. Sheaths bright green with sparse to rather dense scattered black triangular spines 7-15 mm long and abundant deciduous red-brown indumentum; knee present; ocrea not developed. Flagellum absent. Leaf cirrate, 1.2 - 2 m or more long, including the cirrus to 1.2 m; petiole 10-25 cm, sometimes much shorter, armed with rather coarse black-tipped spines; leaflets 6-8 on each side of the rachis, very distant and slightly to distinctly irregular, usually rather stiff, plicate, tending to diverge from the rachis at an acute angle, sometimes the basalmost reflexed, the longest to 35 x 2 cm, very sparsely spiny along the margins, transverse veinlets distinct. Inflorescences considerably shorter than the leaves, c. 40 - 50 cm long, but occasionally to 1 m, the male more highly branched than the female; prophyll and primary bracts short, spiny or not along the margins, often with abundant reddish-brown indumentum; partial inflorescences 3-8; male rachillae usually curved, c. 10 -15 mm long, the female fewer in number, to 25 mm long. Mature fruit ovoid to c. 15 x 10 mm with a distinct beak and covered in 15 vertical rows of cinnamon-brown scales. Seed ellipsoid c. 8x6x5 mm, endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf not known (Fig. 46).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Rather local in 1st and 2nd Divisions; once recorded for the Ulu Rejang. Elsewhere in W Kalimantan. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane appears to be of excellent quality but the stems are rarely very long.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C mattanensis occurs from sea level to altitudes of 700 - 800 m; it grows in a variety of forests from low-lying swamp margins to ridge tops. It is variable, but the few rather irregular stiff plicate leaflets, together with the leaf sheath spines and the short inflorescences with curving rachillae are distinctive.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>