<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis canescens</name>
<author>(Jum. &amp; H. Perrier) Beentje &amp; J. Dransf.</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 410 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Sambirano forest at Ambaliha; Perrier; s.n.</type>
<synonymy>
<name>Chrysalidocarpus canescens</name>
<author>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier</author>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Ma1): 38, t. 19 (1913)</bibref>
<bibref>Jumelle, Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 10, 3: 12 (1922)</bibref>
<bibref>Jumelle, Cat. Pl. Madagascar, Palmae: 8 (1938)</bibref> 
<bibref>Jumelle &amp; H. Perrier Fl. Madagascar 30: 106 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>Insufficiently known species.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>DESCRIPTION FROM LITERATURE: TRUNK 4-8m, straight, ringed, &#60; 10 cm diam., base somewhat thickened in a cone. LEAVES 8-12, ascending; sheath glabrous, membranous, without ligule; petiole absent; rachis c. 2 m long; leaflets regular, recurved, 3.5-4 cm distant, proximal 60-65 x 0.6-0.7 cm, median 75-80 x 1.5 cm, some brownish ramenta on the midrib, adaxially white-mealy when young. INFLORESCENCE at most branched to 2 orders; peduncle 60 cm; prophyll borne at 13 cm above the base of the peduncle, 40 cm long, split only at apex; peduncular bract deciduous, inserted at 30 cm above the base of the peduncle, 45 cm long, conical at the apex, split along its length; rachillae often with paired or solitary staminate flowers due to abortion of the pistillate ones. STAMINATE FLOWERS with keeled and slightly spurred sepals, glabrous, ovate, obtuse, 2 x 2 mm; petals ovate, acute, 3 x 2.2 mm; filaments c. 1.3 mm; ovary rudiment cylindrical, 1.8 mm, about aslong as the stamens. PISTILLATE FLOWERS unknown. FRUIT unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>NW Madagascar, only known from the type.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Forest on sandstone; c. 40 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Presumed extinct; not seen for more than fifty years.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>In the protologue the species is compared (as is Chrysalidocarpus brevinodis) with D. lutescens with the following difference: absence of petiole. The type locality is either Ambaliha on the Ampasindava Peninsula, as seems to be indicated in the protologue, or another Ambaliha (not found on map or in Gazetteer) on the left bank of the Sambirano River. 
The fact that it is compared with D. lutescens makes us think the leaflets might be regular, but unfortunately we cannot be certain.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>None. Despite a thorough search, we have not found the type specimen.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>