<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops jenkinsiana</name>
<author>(Griff.)Mart.</author>
<citation>Hist. Nat. Palm 3 :31850</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook. f. Fl. Brit. Ind. 6:462. 1893</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari inAnn. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12 :41. 1911, p1. 1. part n. 1911</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus jenkinsianus</name>
<author>Griff</author>
<bibref>Griff, in Calc. Journ. Nat. Hist. 5 : 81. 1845</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Golak bet, Cheka bet, Dudhia bet, Dangri bet, Golla bet.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>High climbing rattan; stem with lealshcath 3 - 4 cm in diameter; intemodes 15-20 cm long, longitudinally striatc. Leaves cirrate; leafblade excluding cirrus to 3 m long; leafsheath pale yellow to yellowish green, covered with brown scurf and armed with thin flattened, deep brown to blackish needle-like spines in series or scattered; petiole 15 - 20 cm long, 5 cm broad at widest part; scurfy outside, flat to slightly convex above, armed below with strong digitate claws and straight spines at margins; leaflets equidistant, alternate to suboppos-ite; largest leaflets little above the base, 40 - 50 cm long or in some vigorous specimens 50 - 70 cm long, 2 - 4 cm broad at widest part; ultimate leaflets rudimentary. Inflorescence sub-axillary or inserted above the mouth of their sheaths, not very broadly fusiform after opening; peduncle 3 - 6 cm long; outer bract tapering into a long beak, reddish to reddish brown in colour. Flower branches densely scurfy at base. Male flowers oblong in bud, 5 x 2.5 mm; calyx cupular, hairy at tips; corolla with 3-obIanceolate petals; stamens 6, anthers subulate, connate and thickened at base. Rachillae in female inflorescence upto 8 cm long, sinuous; female flowers 6 - 7 in number on each side; each 5 - 5.5 mm long; calyx cupular, truncate; corolla distinctly veined, with deeply divided lanceolate petals; ovary ovoid to globose, stigmas 3, pappillose inside. Fruit globose, 1.8 cm in diameter; fruit scales in 18 longitudinal series, yellowish brown in colour with distinct darker marginal lines; seed globose, about 10mm in diameter, minutely pitted; pits filled with dark subresinous substances; endosperm ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (West Bengal, Sikkim, Assam, Meghalaya), BANGLADESH, BHUTAN.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>In the eastern Himalaya it is common in the mixed forests up to 1000m.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Experimental cultivation exists in north Bengal. Cultivated in the Indian Botanic Garden, Howrah and in Forest Research Institute, Chittagong, Bangladesh.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane is mainly used for making rough baskets, chair frames etc. Tribal people use it for tying fences and for making canes bridges.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>