<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus paspalanthus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>in Hooker f., Fl. Br. India 6: 450 (1893)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 295 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 157 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 130 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 146 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Referring to the superficial resemblance of the male rachillae in flower to a grass inflorescence</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Singkau (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary moderate rattan, usually short-stemmed but rarely climbing to 20 m, frequently flopping to the ground and producing roots at a position about 1 cm below each node; stem without sheaths 10-15 mm diam., with sheaths to c. 40 mm diam., internodes usually rather short to 12 cm long. Sheath dull dark purplish-brown due to abundant persistent scales, armed with large dark spines 3-5 cm long except around the sheath mouth where very much larger and &#177; erect to 10 cm; knee very conspicuous, bulbous, grossly swollen; ocrea very long, up to c. 1 m, straw-coloured, fragile and papery, quickly disintegrating to leave almost no trace. Flagellum to 2 m long. Leaf ecirrate, to 2 m including petiole to 80 cm, but often much less;rachis covered with red-brown hairs; leaflets numerous, up to 100 on each side of the rachis, very close and regular, delicate in texture, to 30 &#215; 1 cm, densely bristly on the lower surface. Inflorescences to 5 m or more, including the terminal flagellum; bracts tightly sheathing at the base but thin, papery and disintegrating at the tips; rachillae held at right angles to the partial inflorescence axis. Flowers strictly distichous. Fruit &#177; spherical, to 18 &#215; 16 mm, covered in c. 15 vertical rows of smooth, red-brown scales with paler shiny margins. Seed &#177; anvil-shaped with two sharp wings, the sarcotesta extremely sour. Seedling leaf pinnate with numerous leaflets and reddish-brown hairy rachis. (Fig. 54).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Rare in Brunei; elsewhere throughout Borneo, local in Peninsular Malaysia.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane is &#177; useless as it shrinks and is frequently marred by the adventitious roots. The fruit is usually much appreciated for its sourness. Seedlings would make fine ornamentals.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. paspalanthus is such a strange species that there should be no difficulty in distinguishing it.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, K.Belalong, Dransfield J. 6672.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>