<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Areca (Palmae: Arecoideae) in Borneo</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 39, No. 1, pp 1-22</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1984</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Areca andersonii</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 39: 6 (1984)</citation>
<type>Borneo, Sarawak, 4th Division, Niah, G. Subis, Sg. Sekaloh; J. A. R. Anderson; S 31937</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypus SAR</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>This new species is named for the collector, J. A. R. Anderson, who has collected many curious Bornean palms.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>ad sectionem Microarecam pertinens, floribus staminatis stipitatisque A. abdulrahmanii J. Dransf. et A. klingkangensi J. Dransf. affinis, sed calcicola et staminibus tantum 6 distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Apparently solitary, short-stemmed, undergrowth palmlet. Stem to c. 2.5 m, 1.3 cm diam.; internodes to 1.5 cm, nodes marked by conspicuous leaf scars, c. 3 mm high; surface of internode dull green with sparse brown scales. Leaf sheaths forming a distinct crownshaft to 23 x 2 cm; sheaths 7-13 cm long with basal circumference 2-3 cm, striate, with sparse brown scales; ligule poorly developed. Leaf without sheath 65-80 cm including petiole to 30 x 0-3 cm; leaflets 2-3 on each side of the rachis, diverging at an angle of c. 30'; leaflets subequal, with up to 5 main ribs, acuminate except for the lobed apical pair, to c. 35 x 3 cm; lamina surfaces concolorous, ± glabrous on adaxial surface, with scattered brown scales on abaxial surface. Inflorescence infrafoliar; peduncle short, c. 10 x 3 mm; rachillae 3-4, divaricate, ± zig-zag, to 100 x 2 mm, covered in brown scales, each bearing 1-3 triads near the base, and spirally arranged pairs of staminate flowers distally. Staminate flower conspicuously stipitate, the stalk formed from the calyx base, glabrous, to 1.5 mm, the calyx tubular above the solid base, lobes 3, strongly keeled, narrow triangular, to 1 mm; corolla with 3 ovate apiculate petals to 3.5 x 1.75 mm; stamens 6, to 1.5 x 0.3 mm, anthers borne on short filaments; pistillode absent. Pistillate flower sessile with 3 imbricate, cucullate, apiculate free sepals to 4.5 x 3 mm, and 3 free imbricate apiculate petals to 4.5 x 2.5 mm; ovary to 7 x 2.5 mm, tipped with a beak and 3 stigmas. Immature fruit fusiform, 'ripening red', to 21 x 7 mm, tipped with stigmatic remains; seed immature, basally attached.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Borneo, Sarawak, 4th Division, known only from type collection.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>This is a lowland species, and was found growing in the unusual habitat of crevices in limestone.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>It belongs to section Microareca by virtue of its small habit and spirally arranged staminate flowers. Together with A. abdulrahmanii and A. klingkangensis it forms a group of species distinctive in the conspicuously stipitate staminate flowers, but is immediately distinguishable from these two by the presence of only 6 stamens.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>