<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus floribundus</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<citation>Calc. Journ. Nat. Hist. 5 : 1845</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook. f. Fl. Brit. Ind. 6 : 444. 1892</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 191. 1908 and Appendix Pl. 47. 1913.</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A strong climber; stem cluster-forming, with leafsheath to 3 cm in diameter. Leaves ecirrate; leafsheath armed with to 3 cm long, subulate, horizontal to deflexed spines, mostly scattered or seriate, intermingled with dark brown bulbous based bristles; petiole strongly armed at margins with to 4 cm long, straight rigid spines, horizontal or deflexed from petiole; flagellum armed with black tipped claws; leaflets not many, lanceolate, 3-5 nerved, to 50 cm long, 3 - 4 cm wide at middle; upper leaflets crowded; terminal leaflets conspicuously connate at base. Male inflorescence flagelliform, to 3 m long; partial inflorescences to 40 cm long, thrice branched; primary bracts tubular, 2-edged, armed with scattered straight spines; secondary bracts tubular, non spiny, with funnel-like opening; flower branches alternate, inserted at the mouth or just above the mnouth of the respective bracts, each holding alternate, to 2 cm long rachillae; male flowers distichous, ovoid, 3-4 mm long; calyx rounded, almost smooth at base with 3-acute lobes; corolla twice longer than calyx. Female partial inflorescences fewer in number, 15-30 cm long; base of the partial inflorescences inserted within the primary bracts; rachillae 4 - 8 in number on each side of the flower branch, 8 -12 cm long, slightly arched, zig-zag between the flowers; involucrophorum sub-cupular, acutely toothed on each side, almost exserted from own bract. Female flowers 4 mm long, ovoid, conic. Fruit almost globose, suddenly beaked to 10mm in diameter; fruit-scales in 15 series, obtuse, shining, superficially channelled at middle, straw yellow in colour; seed sub-orbicular.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (Assam, Meghalaya, Arunachal Pradesh), BANGLADESH, BURMA.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Grows in moist forests of the plains and lower hill valleys.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Not cultivated.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Arunachal Pradesh : Abor Expedition (1911-12),  Makum, 21.11.1919, Burkhil 35743 (CAL); Pobomukh, 15.12.1911, Burkhil 37041 (CAL).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>