<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus pseudoulur</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 133 (1913)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>False ulur, resembling Calamus ulur, a species from Sumatra and Peninsular Malaysia</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>wi tap ah (Ib.), wi lembah (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering moderate rattan with stems climbing to 20 m tall; stem without sheaths to 12 mm diam., with to 20 mm diam., internodes to 20 cm long. Sheaths green or greyish green, armed with rather sparse, large, scattered triangular spines to 20 x 5 mm, with conspicuous hairy margins, brown indumentum also present between the spines; knee conspicuous; ocrea poorly developed. Vestigial flagellum present, to 10 cm. Leaf to 2.4 m long including the petiole to 40 cm and cirrus to 1.2 m long; leaflets 4- c. 10 on each side of the rachis, irregularly grouped, broad lanceolate, plicate, armed with bristles only at the tips, the longest leaflets to 40 x 7 cm. Inflorescences to 90 cm long with 4-5 partial inflorescences, the whole appearing dead; bracts throughout the inflorescence splitting, expanding, tattering, dull pale or dark brown; male rachillae numerous, crowded, mostly partially hidden among the bracts, to c. 12 x 1.5 mm, &#177; curved; female rachillae to 25 x 4 mm, straight or curved. Mature fruit relatively large, rounded, c. 22 mm diam., shortly beaked and covered in c. 21 vertical rows of red brown scales. Seed with flesh removed &#177; oblate, 9 x 13 mm; sarcotesta sweet and juicy; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf not known (Fig. 51).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from a few collections from the 1st and 4th Divisions. Elsewhere in Kalimantan. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>A good general purpose cane for baskets and other woven objects.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. pseudoulur has been collected in kerangas and secondary forest at low altitudes. For differences between it and C. semoi see the latter</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>