<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia scortechinii</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 475</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card., Calcutta 12 (3) (1918) 118</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mal. Pen. 5 (1925) 68</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 13 (1951) 321</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>Rev. Father Scortechini - plant collector in Perak, 1845 - 1886</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan dahan, rotan semut</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering high-climbing rattan branching in the forest canopy. Stems often more than 20 m tall, by 1.0 - 1.5 cm in diameter without sheaths, 1.5 - 2.0 cm with sheaths. Inter-nodes to about 25 cm long below, much shorter near inflorescences above. Sheaths dull green rather sparsely spiny &#177; entirely covered by the elongate inflated ocrea; ocrea dull pale brown up to about 20 cm long by 4 cm in diameter, shorter and proportionally wider on sheaths by the inflorescences, covered with scattered short spines, not exceeding 8 mm in length and usually much less, and caducous chocolate-coloured scales, sometimes almost unarmed. Ants usually abundant in ocrea. Whole leaf up to 2.5 m on juvenile stems, usually shorter on mature climbing stems; petiole about 10 cm, cirrus up to about 1.25 m; up to 11 leaflets on each side, rather narrowly rhomboid, up to 30 cm long by 5 cm wide, the upper V* only praemorse, dark dull green above, whitish below but not densely so. Up to 6 of the uppermost nodes producing inflorescences, each with up to 10 flower bearing branches to 25 cm long by 8 mm in diameter. Flowers not known. Mature fruit described by Furtado as being 20 mm long by 9-11 mm wide, covered in 16-18 vertical rows of scales.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Penang, Perak, Pahang, Selangor, Negri Sembilan, Malacca, Singapore: Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Apparently widespread and possibly overlooked, in lowland and hill Dipterocarp forest up to 900 m altitude (at Genting Highlands), apparently favouring lower hillslopes rather than ridge tops.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane apparently durable but of poor appearance.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>K. scortechinii has been confused with K. echinometra', the latter species has highly inflated, less elongate ocrea armed with shining massive spines to 8 cm long, and bears even more narrowly lanceolate leaflets. Furthermore K. echinometra seems to be a plant of ridge-tops or poor soils rather than lower hillslopes. I have never seen the two species growing together.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>