<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus setulosus</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 343</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Setulosus - with small brjstles, referring to the bristles on the undersides of the leaflets</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan kerai (incorrectly "rotan getah")</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender ? clustering rattan. Stem without sheaths about 7 mm in diameter, with sheaths to 1.1 cm; internodes 8.5 cm long. Sheaths, in dried specimen, dull straw-coloured with scattered dark indumentum and various spines, usually reflexed, scattered, rather sparse, 1-10 mm long. Knee conspicuous with short 2 mm long spines along keel; petiole base unarmed on abaxial face; spines around leaf sheath mouth conspicuous, upward pointing. Ocrea inconspicuous. Flagellum about 60 cm. Leaf to 85 cm long, ecirrate; petiole to 11 cm long, armed with short spines to 2 mm long spaced evenly along the margins; leaflets about 60 on each side of the rachis, narrow, regular, close, the largest to 13 cm long by 1 cm wide; leaflets bristly on 3 nerves above and along margins, and very densely bristly along 5 nerves below. Inflorescence, only female known, to 105 cm long with a long terminal flagellum and three partial inflorescences to about 7 cm long; immature fruit somewhat wider than high, about 5 mm high, 4 mm wide covered in 21 vertical rows of reflexed brownish scales.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Perak: known from two collections only. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species has been recorded once from a low hillside and once from forest on limestone.
 It seems closest to C. balingensis but may be distinguished by its much smaller size, the narrow bristly leaflets, and the spine-free petiole base.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>