<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Areca (Palmae: Arecoideae) in Borneo</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 39, No. 1, pp 1-22</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1984</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Areca chaiana </name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 39: 10 (1984)</citation>
<type>Borneo, Sarawak, 2nd Division, Lubok Antu, Sg. Jelok, near Bukit Sengkajang, Lanjak-Entimau Protected Forest; Paul Chai; S 33986</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi BH, KEP, L, SAR</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>montana ad sectionem Microarecam ut videtur pertinens sed inflorescentia spicata basi triades numerosos con- gestosque ferenti, floribus staminatis complanatis petalis latis statim dis- tinguibilis.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Erect, solitary undergrowth palm. Stem to 2-5 m tall, c. 1-8 cm diam., internodes c. 1.7-2 cm, bearing caducous chocolate brown scales; nodal scars to 4 mm wide. Crownshaft well-defined, light greenish yellow when fresh, drying mid-brown, 27 x 3 cm; leaf sheaths neatly abscising, c. 17 cm long, longitudinally striate, bearing sparse, minute, brown scales; ligule to 3 cm, soon tattering. Leaf pinnate, excluding sheath to 85 cm, including petiole to 15 x 0.3 cm; leaflets about 10 on each side of the rachis, ± close, mostly 1-4 ribbed except for the broader terminal pair which may be 4-8 ribbed, con- colorous, drying greenish brown, proximal leaflets c. 26 x 2.3 cm, mid-leaf leaflets c. 36 x 0.7-2.5 cm, apical pair c. 20 x 2.5-5.5 cm, all acuminate except for apical leaflets which are lobed; minute scales abundant on both surfaces. Inflorescences infrafoliar, simply spicate, to c. 15 cm, arcuate; prophyll winged, (only fragments available); peduncle short c. 20 x 7 mm diam. (at insertion of prophyll) greenish cream when fresh, drying dark, bearing scattered pale scales, proximal c. 1/3 of axis bearing numerous spirally arranged triads, distal portion bearing spirally arranged, solitary or paired staminate flowers, subtended by relatively conspicuous triangular rachilla bracts c. 1 x 1 mm. Staminate flower rather irregularly flattened due to close packing; calyx base stipitate, c. 1 x 0.5 mm, flattened, glabrous; calyx lobes narrow-triangular, c. 2 x 0.5 mm, keeled, the margins minutely ciliate; petals variable, striate c. 9 x 2-3.5 mm; stamens 6, ± epipetalous, filaments c. 2 x 0.2 mm, anthers medifixed, ± divergent at tip and base, c. 5.5 x 0.5 mm, latrorse; pistillode absent. Pistillate flower sessile; sepals 3, ovate, imbricate, cucullate, minutely scaly, striate, c. 8 x 4 mm; petals 3, ovate, imbricate except at the very tip, minutely ciliate at margins, c. 7 X 3 mm; staminodes ?6, minute; ovary ± fusiform, c. 6 x 1.2 mm. Mature fruit ± fusiform and somewhat curved at the tip, c. 30 x 8 mm, with apical stigmatic residue c. 2 mm diam.; pericarp drying dull brown, longitudinally striate; seed basally attached filling a space c. 20 x 6 mm, shrinking to 12 x 5 mm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Borneo, Sarawak, 2nd Division, known only from the type</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Near river bank on slope in open place. Altitude 2000 ft a.s.l.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This curious species is the only member of the genus with a truly spicate inflorescence. So anomalous did the aspect of the palm appear to me in the herbarium, that at first I thought it might be a species of Nenga; however, examination of the flowers and fruit indicates affinity with Areca rather than Nenga and it must be regarded as an aberrant member of section Microareca. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>