<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Revision of Wallichia (Palmae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Henderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">A.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Taiwania 52(1) 1-11</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Wallichia nana</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<citation>Calcutta J. Nat. Hist. 5: 488 (1845)</citation>
<type>INDIA. Assam, “lower Assam, in woods about Gowahatty”, no date; Jenkins; s. n.</type>
<type_loc>Holotype CAL; isotypes A!, K!, NY!, P!</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Harina nana</name>
<author>(Griff.) Griff.</author>
<bibref>(Griff.) Griff., Palms Brit. E. Ind.: 176 (1850)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Didymosperma nanum</name>
<author>(Griff.) H.Wendl. &amp; Drude in O.C.E.de Kerchove de Denterghem</author>
<bibref>(Griff.) H.Wendl. &amp; Drude in O.C.E.de Kerchove de Denterghem, Palmiers: 243 (1878)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Blancoa nana</name>
<author>(Griff.) Kuntze</author>
<bibref>(Griff.) Kuntze, Revis. Gen. Pl. 2: 727 (1891)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Arenga nana</name>
<author>(Griff.) H.E.Moore</author>
<bibref>(Griff.) H.E.Moore, Principes 4: 114 (1960)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Ipathi (India).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Stems clustered, to 0.6 m tall, to 2 cm diameter, stems bearing staminate and pistillate inflorescences about equal in length. Leaves arranged spirally; sheaths to 20 cm long, fibrous, with a fibrous ligule to 8 cm long; petioles 0.1-0.28 m long; rachis 0.15-0.5 m long; pinnae 3 per side of rachis, regularly arranged, spreading in the same plane, pinnae from middle of leaf 9-20 cm long, 6.5-10 cm wide, lanceolate, with two lobes. Inflorescences unisexual, subtended by smaller leaves, the pistillate terminal and the staminate lateral; staminate inflorescences to 30 cm long, erect; prophyll not seen; peduncle to 20 cm long; peduncular bracts several, sheathing the peduncle; rachillae 1-4, to 13 cm long, 2 mm diameter, densely brown tomentose; staminate flowers to 5 mm long; sepals 2 mm long, connate into a cupular calyx, deeply lobed, the lobes not imbricate; petals 5 mm long, purple; stamens 9; pistillate inflorescences 20-30 cm long, erect; prophyll not seen; peduncle 11-15 cm long; peduncular bracts several, sheathing the peduncle; rachillae 1-3, often only one well-developed, 8-12 cm long, 3-4 mm diameter, densely brown tomentose; pistillate flowers 2-3.5 mm long; sepals 0.5 mm long; petals 2-3 mm long; gynoecium 2-3 mm long; fruits ellipsoid, to 1.2 cm long, to 1.0 cm diameter, white. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>India (Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Meghalaya).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rainforest at low elevations.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>No uses recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species was transferred by Moore (1960) from Wallichia to Arenga, presumably based on its staminate sepals. Wallichia and Arenga are morphologically similar, and the only difference between the two is the form of the staminateflowers. Wallichia is said to have the sepals of the staminate flowers connate into a tube, and Arenga to have free and imbricate staminate sepals (Uhl and Dransfield, 1987). As found in this study, species of Wallichia have cupular staminate sepals, either lobed or not lobed at the apex. In those species with lobed apices, the lobes are sometimes briefly imbricate. In all species of Arenga, the staminate sepals are free and imbricate. In this scenario, Arenga nana clearly belongs in Wallichia. Griffith (1850) reported ‘about 14’ stamens, although only nine have been counted in this study. Staminate and pistillate inflorescences are borne on the same stem, with a terminal pistillate inflorescence followed by staminate inflorescences. Direction of anthesis amongst inflorescences is basipetal. Distal inflorescences are subtended by smaller leaves. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>INDIA. Assam: Duphla Hills, 12 Dec 1874, Lister 59 (P); banks of the Duking and Dhumsiri rivers, Mar 1890, Anon s. n. (K) Meghalaya: Khasia, Nowgong, 22 Jul 1850, J. Hooker &amp; J. Thomson s. n. (K, P). </p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>