<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus whitmorei</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 337</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary slender rattan climbing to 3 m only. Stem without sheaths 7 mm in diameter, with sheaths to 1.3 cm with internodes to 12 cm long. Sheaths dull brown green armed rather densely with horizontal densely grey hairy brown spines to 2 cm long; spines around leaf sheath mouth erect to 10 cm long. Knee rather poorly developed; flagellum absent Leaf ecirrate to 1.2 m long with petiole to 50 cm long; petiole and rachis densely covered in floe-culentgrey indumentum. Leaflets to 15 on each side, distant &#177; regular, very strongly opposite and divaricate above, subopposite below, the largest near base to 25 cm by 1.5 cm. Infl. male and female superficially similar, to 40 cm long with up to 6 partial inflorescences; peduncle to 20 cm, armed with sparse lateral spines; bracts with tattering limbs to 15 cm long, densely armed with flocculent grey indumentum; partial inflorescence somewhat reflexed, to about 6 cm long; rachillae to about 2 cm. &#177; mature fruit reddish brown rather shortly beaked, about 7 mm in diameter covered in 18 vertical rows of scales. Seed about 5 mm in diameter rounded, slightly flattened on one side; endosperm homogeneous.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Trengganu: G. Padang. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species was collected in montane forest at 1,300 altitude.
 This very slender rattan appears to be the only properly climbing (as opposed to sprawling) rattan in the C. perakensis complex. It is easily distinguished by the presence of a knee of the leaf sheath, albeit poorly developed, and the few very divaricate leaflets scarcely longer than 25 cm.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>