<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus praetermissus</name>
<author>J. Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 36: 802 (1982)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 165 (1984)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Overlooked</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering moderate high-climbing rattan with stems to 25 m or more; stem without sheaths to 18 mm (usually less), with sheaths to 35 mm; internodes to 18 cm. Sheaths dark green, armed with abundant brown, pale green-based spines, usually of two types, large scattered spines to 30 &#215; 7 mm and smaller spines to 7 &#215; 3 mm, the smaller frequently arranged in partial whorls or oblique groups (rarely the spines of only one type); pale brown indumentum abundant. Knee conspicuous, armed with small spines. Ocrea inconspicuous, low, membranous. Flagellum to 3 m, heavily armed. Leaf ecirrate, curving, to 1.2 m including petiole 10-20 cm; petiole usually armed with short lateral spines; leaflets 12-20 one each side of the rachis, curving, regularly arranged, rather distant, usually lanceolate, rarely linear; proximal leaflets to 35 &#215; 2 cm, middle leaflets 35-45 &#215; 3-7 cm, apical leaflets to 23 &#215; 2.5 cm; lower leaflet surface bristly along main veins; transverse veinlets conspicuous. Male and female inflorescences superficially similar, flagellate, usually pendulous, to 3 m, bracts tubular, tightly sheathing, scabrid; male rachillae to 5 cm, somewhat zigzag, bearing distichous male flowers; female rachillae 10-14 cm with very sparse female flowers. Ripe fruit ovoid to 12 &#215; 9 mm with a beak to 2.5 mm, and covered in 15 vertical rows of pale brown, darker-margined scales. seed to 9 &#215; 7 &#215; 5 mm, deeply pitted, the endosperm subruminate. Seedling leaf unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Local throughout Brunei. Elsewhere in Sabah and E Kalimantan.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded, though the cane appears to be of good quality.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. praetermissus is characteristic of lowland dipterocarp forest at altitudes up to 500 m. It is easily distinguishes by the italicised characters.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Stockdale 43; Amo, Wong 1735; Amo, K.Belalong, Dransfield J. 6630; Amo, Kuala Belalong, Stockdale 27.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>