<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus senalingensis</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 342.</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>Named after the type locality</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary rattan climbing to 15 m. Stem without sheaths to 9 mm in diameter, with sheaths to 1.7 cm with internodes to 25 cm. All parts drying pale green or straw-coloured. Sheaths pale green covered with grey indumentum when young and with upward pointing black tipped spines, to 5 mm long. Knee present but not very conspicuous. Ocrea inconspicuous. Flagellum to 1.5 m long. Leaf ecirrate, to 1 m long, with a short petiole in juvenile state no petiole in adult. Leaflets about 15 on each side of the rachis, irregularly arranged in the juvenile, subregular in adult with lowermost 3-4 leaflets in adult swept back across the stem. Lowermost leaflet 10 cm long by 7 mm wide largest leaflets to 35 cm long by 2 cm wide, with heavily thickened margins, and moderately conspicuous lateral veins; leaflets &#177; unarmed. Inflorescence only old female known to 1.5 m long with 4 partial inflorescences to longest to 25 cm long. Inflorescence bracts shortly armed with reflexed spines; rachillae reflexed, curved, about 6.5 cm long bearing rather distant flower scars. Bracteoles unarmed. Flowers and fruit unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Negri Sembilan: known only from Bt. Senaling near Kuala Pilah.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>I had confused this species with Calamus moorhousei, itself only known from one collection from Kuala Pilah, but this latter species, although imperfectly known is quite distinct from C. senalingensis. Superficially C. senalingensis is like C. laevigatus in its reflexed leaflets but of course C. laevigatus does not bear flagella and the leaves are cirrate.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>