<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Ravenea albicans</name>
<author>(Jum.) Beentje</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 49: 663 (1994)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Masoala; Perrier; 11939</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Louvelia albicans</name>
<author>Jum.</author>
<bibref>Jum., Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 5, 1 (1): 5 (1933)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum., Cat. Pl. Madagascar, Palmae: 15 (1938)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Fl. Madagascar 30: 162 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>This tree is immediately recognizable by the white undersides of the leaflets, and the "zebra-striping" on the leaf rachis. Despite these outstanding characters, it remained uncollected for about seventy years after the first collection by Perrier. The Latin name refers to the white leaflet undersides.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Hoza-tsiketra (Betsimisaraka)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender undergrowth palm; trunk 3-6 m, DBH up to 11 cm, covered in marcescent, litter-trapping sheath bases. Leaves c. 8 in the crown, porrect, 3-4 m long; sheath c. 72 cm, with brown-velvety tomentum over green; petiole 0-34 cm, proximally about 5 x 4 cm across, distally 3.7 x 3.3 cm across, canaliculate; rachis c. 3 .7 m long, in midleaf 2-2.2 cm wide with 8 mm wide keel, with transverse ('zebra') striping especially abaxially; leaflets stiff, in one plane, 45-47 on each side of the rachis, the proximal 62-65 x 2.2-2.5 cm, median 75-83 x 6.6-7.2 cm (the protologue gives 50-60 x 2-2.5, but in the type the apices are broken off and the leaflets are folded) (interval 4.5-5 cm), distal 20-25 x 0.8- 1.5 cm; abaxially with continuous white tomentum. Staminate inflorescences solitary, interfoliar, branching to 1 order, hardly exserted, mostly hidden among sheaths and leaf remnants; peduncle distally 12 x 6 mm, dense white-puberulous; with 3(-4?) bracts, the first being destroyed at anthesis, the ones seen 25 cm, 30 cm, 32-35 cm; rachillae 5-8 cm long, 2.5 mm across; calyx reduced to 3 small triangular teeth &#60; 2 mm; petals elongated, triangular and acuminate, 5.5-6.5 mm, free or hardly connate at the base; episepalous stamens with large filament, appearing free among the spread petals; epipetalous stamens with filament connate to inner side of petals, the anthers therefore appearing sessile. Pistillate inflorescences solitary, interfoliar, erect, 126-150 cm, branched to 1 order; peduncle 94-120 cm, proximally 2.5-3.4 x 1.2-1.7 cm across, distally 1.5 x 0.8 cm; prophyll c. 18 x 7.5 cm; peduncular bracts seen 27 cm, 34 cm, 46 cm; rachis 8-12 cm; rachillae 8-13 in number, 17-29 cm long; pedicels 1- 2 mm; flowers unknown. Fruit unknown. Eophyll bifid, with the characteristic white abaxial surface of the leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>NE Madagascar; the protologue says common between Fenerive (Fenoarivo) and Antalaha, but does not cite any specimens for this distribution. The palm is certainly not common nowadays.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Moist forest at 100-400 m alt.; steep mid slope on ultramafic soil.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Endangered. Only known from two recent localities, in one of which where we counted 40 trees with trunks, about a hundred young ones without trunks, and several seedlings. The distribution area was very limited. The second locality only came to light when the book was going to press.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Heart edible.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>We believe that this species only flowers and fruits at intervals, i.e. not every year, since all the trees we checked in Mananara Biosphere Reserve over a period of two years were sterile, with only ancient inflorescences.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Masoala, presumably near Antalaha, no date (stam.), Perrier 11939 (Holotype P); Mananara: W of Antanambe, April 1992 (old pist.), Beentje et al. 4630 (K), 4643 (K, MO, P, TAN); idem (seedling), Beentje et al. 4644 (K); idem, Oct. 1994 (dead pist.), Beentje &amp; Dransfield 4812 (K, TAN), and (seedl.), 4814 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>