<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A New Species of Calamus (Palmae) from Taiwan</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Henderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">A.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Taiwania 50(3) 222-226</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2005</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus beccarii</name>
<author>A.J.Hend.</author>
<citation>Taiwania 50: 222 (2005)</citation>
<type>Taiwan. Pingtung: Bankinsing, no date; A. Henry; 521a</type>
<type_loc>Holotype NY; isotype K</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Tu-teng.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Ab omnibus speciebus generis Formosae flagello praesenti et cirrho absenti differt.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Stems clustered, to 50 m long and 4 cm diameter (with leaf sheaths). Leaf sheaths brown, covered with black, needle-like, horizontally spreading spines to 2.5 cm long, these arranged in short rows, interspersed with shorter spines to 0.5 cm long; knees obscure; ocreas present, densely spiny; flagella present, to 2.5 m long, with groups of grapnel-like spines abaxially; petioles to 22 cm long, sparsely covered with stout, yellowish spines to 1 cm long; rachis to 0.8 m long, abaxially with solitary, recurved, grapnel-like spines; pinnae 30-62 per side of rachis, linear, closely spaced to 2 cm apart, to 40 cm long and 1.5 cm wide, with minute spines on the veins abaxially and adaxially; cirri absent. Inflorescences to 3 m long; staminate inflorescences branched to two orders, flagellate, the bracts closely sheathing the main axis and with curved spines abaxially; rachillae 5-9 cm long, inserted above the mouth of the sheathing bract; rachillae bracts distichously arranged; floral bracteole cupular, tomentose along the margins; staminate flowers to 4.5 mm long, to 38 per rachilla, arranged alternately and distichously along the rachillae; calyx 4 mm long, tubular except for the 3-lobed apex; corolla 4 mm long, with 3 valvate petals free to the base; stamens 6; anthers dorsifixed; pistillode 1 mm long, 3-lobed; pistillate inflorescences branched to two orders; rachillae 4-10 cm long; rachillae bracts distichously arranged; distal floral bracteole with a small lateral depression bearing sterile staminate flower; pistillate flowers to 22 per rachilla, borne alternately and distichously along the rachillae; sepals to 4 mm long, connate basally, lobed above; petals to 3 mm long, free; fruits globose-ellipsoid, to 2 cm long includin g a short beak, to 1.2 cm diameter; scales fringed, yellowish-brown; endosperm homogeneous. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Taiwan, in Kaohsiung and Pingtung counties.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>In lowland rainforest at low elevations.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>By its climbing habit, flagellum, tubular inflorescence bracts, sessile rachillae, and homogeneous endosperm this species appears to belong in Beccari's (1908) Group V. This large group of species is widespread throughout the Asian tropics. Calamus beccarii appears most similar morphologically to two Group V species from China (C. rhabdocladus Burret and C. walkeri Hance). Calamus beccarii differs from these in its  flattened spines) and its larger fruits (to 2 cm versus 1.4 cm long). </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Taiwan. Kaohsiung: Shenping, 12 Dec 1987, Chang 1897b (K). Pingtung: Chunjih Hsiang, Chachayalaishan Protection Area, 29th Compartment 1 Mar 1992, Liao 209 (A); “ Formosa”, no date, Henry 521 (NY); Bankinsing, no date, Henry 521b (K).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>