<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Notes on Pinanga (Palmae) in Sarawak</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 46, No. 4, pp. 691-698</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1991</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pinanga cucullata</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 46: 691 (1991)</citation>
<type>Borneo, Sarawak; Dransfield et al.; JD6072</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi BH, BO, L, PNH, SAR</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>P. tomentellae Becc. pagina inferiore laminae tomentella calyce floris pistillati connato affinis sed lamina profunde bifida, habitu dense caespitoso distinguibilis.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender colonial palmlet spreading by short rhizomes or stolons; stem erect, rarely exceeding 60 cm long, 4-8 mm diam., internodes 3-4 cm long, the surface covered with dark brown scales and white hairs, adventitious branching sometimes occurring from the middle of the internodes. Crown of about 8 leaves, the sheaths forming an elongate crownshaft; leaf sheaths c. 11 x 1.4 cm, smooth, almost succulent when fresh, striate on drying, bearing scales and hairs as the internodes, distally with 2 short rapidly disintegrating auricles 6 x 3 mm; petiole very short, c. 20 x 2.5 mm, bearing scales and hairs as the sheath; blade when fresh, dark shiny green adaxially, grey hairy abaxially, deeply bifid, the costa c. 5 cm only, the two lobes conspicuously cucullate, to 25 x 3 cm, with about 5 ribs, the tips entire rather than lobed, adaxial surface glabrous, abaxial surface densely grey-scurfy, particularly along the folds. Inflorescence unbranched or bifid, pendulous or porrect, to 8 cm; prophyll not preserved; peduncle very short, not exceeding 8 mm, c. 4 mm diam. near the base; rachilla c. 2 x 1 mm diam., pale cream, thickening and becoming red at fruit maturity, rather densely covered in caducous branched scale-like trichomes, and bearing strictly distichous triads of flowers. Staminate flowers (based on one very imperfectly preserved flower) c. 4 x 3 mm; calyx c. 0.5 mm high, irregularly 3-lobed; petals c. 4 x 2 mm, unequal; stamens at least 4 (exact number not known), filaments 0.5 mm, anthers elongate, 1.3 mm; pollen not known. Pistillate flower globular, c. 2 mm diam.; calyx gamo- sepalous, striate, c. 1.5 mm high, shallowly 3-lobed; petals imbricate, ovate, c. 1.5 x 1.5 mm, the margins minutely ciliate; staminodes absent; ovary ellipsoid, c. 2 x 1 mm, tipped with an irregularly lobed stigma. Mature fruit black, ellipsoid, c. 13 x 5 mm. Seedling not known.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>It seems always to be found in 'kerangas' (Bornean heath forest) and, although all collections are from the same locality, I have observed it else- where in the 1st Division at Semengoh Forest Reserve near Kuching and in Sempadi Forest Reserve on the Bau-Lundu Road. Although abundant where it occurs, it is, like many kerangas palms, a shy flowerer.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This is a pretty species, very distinctive in its cucullate bifid leaves of a curious almost succulent texture, adaxially shiny green and abaxially grey-hairy. It seems most closely related both in vegetative and floral details to P. tomentella Becc.; the latter, however, is immediately distinguishable by its entire, lanceolate, scarcely bifid leaf.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BORNEO. Sarawak: 1st Division, Serian District, Sabal Tapang Forest Reserve, Dransfield et al. JD6072 (holotype K; isotypes BH, BO, L, PNH, SAR), Dransfield et al. JD4656 (BH, K, KEP, L, SAR), Ilias Paie S.5397 (K, SAR).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>