<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis caudata</name>
<author>Beentje</author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 254 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Antalavia; Dransfield et al.; JD6478</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypus TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A very distinctive species with its long-acuminate, even caudate leaflet tips (hence the name), which are pendulous at almost right angles to the main part of the leaf. The custard yellow flowers are particularly attractive.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>a ceteris speciebus 6-staminatis caulibus caespitosis foliolis fasciculatis ovatis abrupte caudati distincta.</p></div> 
<div type="description"><p>Clustering palm. STEMS 1-3 m, 0.5-1.5 cm diam.; internodes 1-6 cm, green when young, later blackish, distally with dark scales; crownshaft indistinct. LEAVES 6-11 in the crown; sheath c. 10 cm long, pale green with dense dark scales or later with scattered scales; petiole 6-20 cm long, 2-3 mm diam., rusty-scaly, becoming more glabrous; rachis 25-46 cm long, in mid-leaf 2-2.5 mm wide, rusty-scaly; leaflets 11-15 on each side of the rachis, in groups of 2-4, group interval 4-7 cm, proximal 8-10 x 0.5-1.5 cm, median 8-14 x 1.5-2.2 cm, distal 6-8 x 1-2.2 cm, narrowly obovate, with abrupt and pendulous drip-tips 2-4 cm long, main vein 1, with scattered scales on the minor veins and when young with bands of scales on the adaxial midrib, and on the margins (especially on the distal margin), distal pair joined for &#60; 1 cm, dentate over c. 10 mm. INFLORESCENCE branched to 1 order, custard orange-yellow; peduncle c. 31 cm long, c. 1.5 mm diam., scaly; prophyll 19-29 cm long, 4-7 mm wide, opening in the distal 1 cm only, with scattered scales; peduncular bract inserted at c. 16 cm from the base of the peduncle, c. 11 cm long; non-tubular peduncular bract 2-4 mm long; rachis c. 7 cm long, with c. 11 branches; rachillae orange, 4-5.5 cm long, c. 1 mm diam., minutely puberulous and scaly. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.7-0.8 x 0.7-0.8 mm; petals orange, 1.5-1.7 x 1.4-1.5 mm; stamens 6, biseriate (offset 0.2 mm), filaments 0.6-0.8 mm, thin; anthers 1-1.2 x 0.7 mm; pistillode c. 0.8 x 0.3-0.4 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.7-0.8 x 0.6-1 mm; petals orange, 2.2-2.3 x 1.5-2.4 mm; staminodes 6, c. 0.4 mm; pistil c. 2.2 x 1.5 mm. FRUIT orange, 8-11 x 3.5-5 mm. SEED c. 7 x 3.5 mm, with homogeneous endosperm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Masoala Peninsula, known from a single site.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest; steep slope or valley bottom; 50-300 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Critical. Only known from a single site, in an unprotected area. Numbers are thought to be low.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Probably related to D. linearis but very distinct in its leaflets with their long drip-tips.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Maroantsetra: Antalavia, Feb. 1988 (fl., y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6478 (Holotype K; isotype TAN); idem, April 1988 (fr.), Gentry &amp; Schatz 62179 (K); idem, Nov. 1989 (bud), Dransfield et al. JD6741 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>