<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Pritchardia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Hodel</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms 51(4) Special Supplement S-1-53</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pritchardia schattaueri</name>
<author>Hodel</author>
<citation>Principes 29: 31. 1985</citation>
<type>Papa, S. Kona, Hawaii, Hawaii; Moore; 10570</type>
<type_loc>Holotype BH!</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>To 25 m tall; proximal margins of petiole with abundant fibers; leaf blade slightly undulate, divided 1/3-2/S, abaxial surface incompletely covered with scattered lepidia, segment tips droopingi inflorescences composed of 1-4 panicles, shorter than or about equaling petioles in flower and fruit, panicles branched to 2 orders, rachillae glabrous; fruits 30-50 x 30-40 mm, globose to obovoid. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Moist forest on gentle slopes, South Kona, Hawaii, 600-800 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Pritchardia schattalleri can be distinguished by its leaf blades incompletely covered abaxially with lepidia and divided to more than onethird with pendulous segment tips, inflorescences shorter than or about equaling the petioles, glabrous rachillae and large fruits. It is similar to P. gordonii but the latter differs in having leaf blades with narrower and more deeply bifid segment tips (resulting in the tips appearing more conspicuously pendulous), slightly longer inflorescences equaling or exceeding the petioles in fruit, and oblate fruits. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>U.S.A. Hawaii. Hawaii. South Kona: Papa, Hoomau Ranch, Hadel 169 (PTBG), Moore 10570 (BH), Woad 372 (PTBG); Honomalino, Bishop 1832 (HAW). CULT. U.S.A. Hawaii. Oahu: Waimea Valley Audubon Center, 76s454, Zona 1001 (HAW). </p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>