<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus polystachys</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Dot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1908) 383</citation>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 75 (1956) 54</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p> Polus - many, stachus  - an ear of corn, referring to the presence of more than one rachilla at each bract in the inflorescence</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan sabong</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>High climbing rattan clustering to form rather dense clumps or thickets. Stems without sheaths 1-2 cm in diameter, with sheaths to 3.5 cm. Internodes about 15 cm often much longer in juvenile stems. Sheaths with conspicuous knee; sheath bright green bearing numerous whorls or partial whorls of fine black horse-hair-like spines, the bases of which united to form green collars encircling the stem, some of the collars upward pointing, others reflexed, at least some collars interlocking in pairs to form galleries usually occupied by ants. Leaves to 2.5 m long with cirrus to 80 cms and petiole 6 cm only on mature stems, longer in juveniles. Leaflets about 60 on each side of the rachis bright green, regularly arranged, rather narrow about 30-40 cm long by 1 cm wide, bristly on both surfaces. Inflorescence emerging from mouth of leaf sheath, about 50 cm long, without terminal flagellum, with 7-8 partial inflorescences on each side of the axis, the partial inflorescences subtending sparsely spiny or inerm bracts each on subtending 3 flower-bearing branches; male and female flowers both small, distichous. Fruit at maturity ovate not exceeding 6-8 mm in diameter covered in 18 vertical rows of ivory-coloured scales; seed grooved and pitted. Seedling leaf with 4 leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Pahang near Mentakab and Pulau Tioman. Sumatra, Borneo, Java.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Only collected twice, this rattan has probably been overlooked. In Sumatra and Java it is a common rattan of lowland swampy secondary habitats (see Dransfield and Manokaran in press).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>