<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A review of the genus Pritchardia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Hodel</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">D.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms 51(4) Special Supplement S-1-53</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pritchardia arecina</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Webbia 4: 224. 1913</citation>
<type>Honomanu, Maui (E. Maui), Hawaii; Rock; 8821</type>
<type_loc>Holotype FI; isotypes BISH!, GH</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Styloma arecina</name>
<author>(Becc.) O. F. Cook</author>
<bibref>(Becc.) O. F. Cook, J. Wash. Acad. Sci. 5: 241. 1915</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>To 15 m tall, emergent; proximal margins of petiole with moderate to abundant fibers; leaf blade slightly undulate to nearly flat, divided 1/4-1/3, abaxial surface completely covered with lepidia and appearing silvery grayish while to somewhat reddish brown, segment tips stiff; inflorescences composed of 1 or 2 panicles, equaling to exceeding petioles in flower, exceeding petioles or equaling leaf blades in fruit, panicles branched to 2 orders, rachillae permanently clothed with dense, felt-like to nearly woolly indumentum; fruits 45 x 38-40 mm, ellipsoid. </p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Wet forest on the north and northeastern slopes of Haleakala, East Maui, 450-1300 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Pritchardia arecina is distinguished by its petioles with an abundance of fibers proximally, leaf blades completely covered abaxially with lepidia, and large fruits. It is I similar to the highly variable P. martii, but the latter differs in its petioles with irregularly shaped, papery ligules or wings or only a few fibers proximally. It is also somewhat similar to P. woodii, which occurs not too far to the southwest in East Maui but in slightly drier areas; P. wDodii, however, differs in its leaf blades incompletely covered abaxially with lepidia and petioles with only a few fibers proximally.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Specimens Examined. U.S.A. Hawaii. Maui (E. Maui): above Hana, Forbes 2692, 2693 (BISH); Honomanu, Forbes 2592, 2593, 2594 (BISH), I Rock 8821 (BISH); Kawaipapa, Wood 7980, 7989, 7990, 7991, 7997, 8000 (PTBG); Waikamoi, Forbes 2621 (BISH). CULT. U.S.A. Hawaii. Oahu: Foster Garden ex Nahiku, E. Maui, Potter s. n., 27 Feb. 1958 (BISH). </p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>