<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops verticillaris</name>
<author>(Griff.) Mart.</author>
<citation>in Hist. Nat. Palm 3 (ed 2) (1850) 206 and 329</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 470</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12 (1911) 166</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mal. Pen. 5 (1925) 45</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns. Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 144</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus verticillaris</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<bibref>Griff., in Calc. J. Nat. Hist. 5 (1845) 63</bibref>
<bibref>Griff., Palms Br. Ind. (1850) 73</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops stipitata</name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 142 </bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops verticillaris (Griff.) Mart. var. stramineus </name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 147</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Verticillaris - whorled, referring to the spine whorls</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan sabong</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Very variable, usually solitary rotan with stems rarely exceeding 15 m in length, often flowering when much less. Stems without sheaths to 2 cm in diameter, with sheaths to 3 cm or more. Internodes rather short rarely more than 12 cm long. Sheaths bright green densely armed with interlocking pairs of collars and single collars of short black horse-hair-like spines, rarely more than 2 cm long intermingled with large laminar yellowish green to blackish spines to 6 cm long; interlocking collars forming galleries inhabited by ants. Dark brown indumentum abundant on young sheaths. Knee present but mostly obscured by spines. Leaf to 3 m long with petiole to 40 cm and cirrus to 1 m. Petiole armed with large reflexed spines in whorls and minute bristles in small groups. Leaflets very regular, close &#177; 45 to 60 on each side of the rachis, longest leaflets to about 40 cm long by 2.3 cm wide, sparsely bristly on mid-vein and some lateral veins below. Inflorescences male and female superficially similar but male more highly branched. Peduncle short to long, very sparsely armed bracts thin finely black bristly. Male flowers tightly packed, distichous; female flowers much larger but also markedly distichous. Fruit rounded sessile or shortly stalked, at maturity to 15 mm in diameter very shortly beaked, covered in 15 vertical rows of pale straw to red-brown scales, with dull brown marginal lines. Seed rounded, somewhat pitted. Endosperm ruminate. Seedling leaf pinnate with few close-set leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Kelantan, Trengganu, Pahang, Perak, Selangor, Negri Sembilan, Malacca, Johore. Thailand. Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Rarely used as a source of a rather poor quality cane.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>"Rotan sabong" is one of the commonest Malayan rattans, though absent from the N.W. of the Peninsula. It is found in a wide range of habitats from the margins of swamps in the lowlands to ridgetops at 1000 m or more altitude in the highlands, being found both on hillslopes and in valley bottoms.
Furtado separated the populations from Kelantan and Trengganu as a separate species, D. stipitata on the distinguishing characters: fruit shortly pedicellate, large thorns on sheath blackish and with 3-5 rows of bristles on the leaf underside. However, I have found a whole range of intermediates between the two extremes and feel I cannot justify retaining two species. The variety stramineus was separated from D. verticillaris by Furtado based on the presence of dirty straw coloured rather than reddish fruit scales - here again, such a range of colours is found that the variety is not regarded here as being sufficiently distinct.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>