<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia ferox</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Malesia 2: 73 (1884)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 138 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 36: 178 (1981)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 17 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 91 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Fierce</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Uwai Selika (Dus.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Robust clustering and branching rattan climbing high into the forest canopy; stem without sheaths to 2 cm diam. or more, with sheaths to 4 cm diam., internodes to c. 30 cm. Sheaths dull green with caducous chocolate-coloured scales and abundant triangular pale brown spines, but usually quite obscured by the ocrea of the preceding leaf; ocrea closely sheathinguntidily tattering, densely armed with pale to dark brown spines to 6 cm. Leaf to 2.5 m including cirrus to 1 m and petiole to 30 cm; leaflets 6-8 on each side of the rachis, broad diamond-shaped, the largest to 30 &#215; 15 cm, on stalks to 1 cm, bright green on the upper surface, whitish or orange-brown on the undersurface. Inflorescences produced from the topmost up to 5 nodes, robust, to 50 cm, with many pendulous rachillae to 10 &#215; 1.2 cm, reddish-brown hairy. Fruit somewhat top-shaped, 2 &#215; 1.2 cm covered in 15 vertical rows of reddish brown scales. Seed 1.5 &#215; 9 mm; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf strongly discolorous. (Fig. 3).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Local, known from scattered localities. Widespread in Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>K. ferox is one of the largest species in the genus and occurs in lowland and hill dipterocarp forest up to c. 300 m altitude.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a large durable cane; leaves used for temporary thatch.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>It is the only species with large closely sheathing tattering and spiny ocreas.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Kuala Belalong, Stockdale 28. TUT: Lamunin, Ladan Hills F.R., Dransfield J. 6884; Rambai, Tasek Merimbun, Bernstein 131.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>