<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus pogonacanthus</name>
<author>Becc. ex H. Winkl.</author>
<citation>H. Winkler in Engl. Bot. Jahrb. 48: 91 (1912)</citation>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 106 (1913)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 113 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 111 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Bearded spines</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Uwai Taut (Dus.), Wi Tut (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering moderate very variable rattan climbing to 30 m or more; stem without sheaths to 15 mm diam., with sheaths to 25 mm diam., internodes to 30 cm. Sheaths dull to bright green, covered with deciduous brown scales and scattered spines with concave bases and black hairy margins, the spines varying from 2-30 mm on the same sheath or, more often, rather uniform, 10-25 mm; knee conspicuous; ocrea inconspicuous, to 5 mm with few small spines. Vestigial flagellum present, erect, to 30 cm. Leaf cirrate, to 2 m long, including the short petiole to 10 cm and the cirrus to 80 cm, cirrus bearing scattered rather than neatly grouped spines; leaflets c. 20-25 on each side of the rachis, irregularly arranged, usually subregular near the base and grouped in 3&amp;rsquo;s or 4&amp;rsquo;s near the cirrus, rarely &#177; regular throughout, the longest to 40 &#215; 2 cm, armed with scattered bristles along the main veins on both surfaces. Inflorescences superficially similar, to c. 1.5 m with up to 8 lax partial inflorescences arranged rather regularly; main bracts tubular, armed with scattered spines, scarcely splitting; male rachilla to 30 &#215; 3 mm, female to 150 &#215; 4 mm; bracts and bracteoles dull dirty brown. Mature fruit spherical or somewhat depressed, to 8 &#215; 10 mm, tipped with a beak to 1.5 &#215; 1.5 mm and covered with 24 vertical rows of pale straw-coloured scales; seed c. 8 mm diam.; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf bifid. (Fig. 39.).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread throughout Brunei and the rest of Borneo; endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a good quality cane which is used locally when rotan sega (Calamus optimus) is unavailable.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. pogonacanthus is widespread both in the lowlands and uplands up to 900 m elevation, often favouring river banks and slightly disturbed sites. This is a very variable species, particularly in the arrangement of the leaflets and the degree of armature of the sheaths; the presence of a vestigial flagellum together with the only slightly tattering inflorescence bracts will serve to identify it, but sterile, its moderate size and coarse irregular leaflets will indicate C. pogonacanthus rather than C. semoi. the taxonomy of the group of Calamus spp with vestigial flagella is still very poorly understood and requires more careful observations of variation in the field - see also comments under C. semoi.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Melilas, Ulu Ingei, Sands 5918. TEM: Amo, Ashton A 286; Amo, Stockdale 18; Amo, Bt.Retak, Wong 903; Amo, K.Belalong, Dransfield J. 6657; Amo, K.Belalong, Wong 265; Amo, Kuala Belalong, Stockdale 50; Amo, Ulu Belalong, Dransfield J. 7363. TUT: Lamunin, Ladan Hills F.R., Dransfield J. 6893; Lamunin, Dransfield J. 6809; Rambai, Tasek Merimbun, Bernstein 32. Without prov.: BRUN 15125.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>