<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus comptus</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 45: 98 (1990)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 183 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus nematospadix</name>
<author>sensu Dransfield, not Beccari</author>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 159 (1984)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Neat</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Uwai Pios (Dus.), Wi Tunggal (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary or very rarely clustered slender or moderate rattan with stems to 10 m or more; stems without sheaths 10-18 mm diam., with sheaths to 27 mm diam., usually less, internodes c. 7 cm long. Sheaths bright green armed with scattered short broad triangular &#177; reflexed black spines to 6 &#215;6 mm with swollen yellowish bases and black hairy fringes along the margins, usually with slight swellings in between the spines and abundant brown indumentum; knee conspicuous, armed as the sheath; ocrea membranous, to 5 mm, quickly disintegrating, reddish when young. Flagellum to 2 m. Leaf ecirrate, to 90 cm including petiole to 30 cm, the rachis very densely covered with rusty-brown hairs when young; leaflets 35-40 on each side of the rachis, very close and regular, rather limp, to 30 &#215; 1.3 cm, conspicuously bristly on 3 nerves on the upper surface, along the margins and along the main vein on the undersurface, transverse veinlets inconspicuous. Inflorescence relatively very long, to c. 6 m, with a peduncle to 3 m, the bracts closely sheathing and bearing abundant short triangular spines; partial inflorescences c. 3-4, each to c. 1 m, and bearing lax rachillae; female rachillae to 15 &#215; 0.2 cm with densely crowded flowers. Mature fruit rounded, to 7 mm diam., tipped with a short beak to 1 mm, and covered with 15 vertical rows of pale ivorycoloured scales with dark tips. Seed slightly flattened on one side, to 5 &#215; 5 &#215; 3 mm; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf pinnate with c. 4-5 leaflets on each side of the rusty-hairy rachis. (Fig. 67).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread throughout the lowlands of Brunei. Elsewhere in Sabah and Sarawak. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane is of good appearance but tends to be rather short. Used for weaving carrying baskets.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. comptus occurs in lowland dipterocarp forest. Previously we had confused this species withC. nematospadix. With greater field experience and more material to study we have realised that this species is distinct and that, perhaps, it is as close to C. rugosus of Peninsular Malaysia as toC. nematospadix. When sterile, it may be distinguished from C. nematospadix by the frequent presence of ridges between the spines on the sheaths and the very dense rusty hairs on the rachis; in fruit, the rachillae are very much longer, wider and straighter than those of C. nematospadix and the primary and secondary bracts are more densely armed.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Stockdale 20; Amo, Stockdale 45; Amo, Stockdale 69; Amo, Wong 1693; Amo, Bt.Belalong, Wong 1389. TUT: Rambai, Tasek Merimbun, Bernstein 13.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>