<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Genera Palmarum. The evolution and classification of palms</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Uhl</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">N.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Asmussen</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Baker</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">W.J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Harley</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2008</mods:dateIssued><mods:publisher>Kew Publishing, Royal Botanic Gardens Kew</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="genus">
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Monotypic fan palm found only in Belize and Guatemala, distinct in the long-pedicellate flowers and large pale green fruit.</p></div>
<nomenclature>
<name>Schippia</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<citation>Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Berlin-Dahlem 11: 867 (1933b).</citation>
<type>Type; Schippia concolor; Burret.</type>
</nomenclature>
<div type="etymology"><p>Commemorating William A. Schipp (1891–1967), who collected many plants in Belize, including Schippia.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Moderate, solitary, unarmed, pleonanthic, hermaphroditic or polygamo-monoecious palm. Stem slender, longitudinally striate, rough, with raised, close, oblique leaf scars. Leaves induplicate, palmate to very shortly costapalmate; sheath split basally, densely tomentose, disintegrating to form a thick fibrous network; petiole very long, narrow, adaxially channelled and abaxially keeled basally, biconvex distally, sparsely to densely tomentose, margins acute; adaxial hastula triangular or rounded, rather large, abaxial hastula a low rounded ridge; blade divided to below the middle into narrow, tapering, single-fold segments, with pointed, unequal, very shortly bifid apices, lighter coloured beneath, appearing glabrous on both surfaces, midrib conspicuous abaxially, transverse veinlets inconspicuous, very short. Inflorescences solitary, interfoliar, much shorter than the leaves, branched to 2 (rarely 3) orders; peduncle moderate, dorsiventrally flattened; prophyll tubular, elongate, adaxially flattened, abaxially rounded, 2-keeled laterally, pointed, splitting unevenly apically, densely tomentose; peduncular bracts 3, ± like the prophyll but ± keeled dorsally; rachis about as long as the peduncle, glabrous; rachis bracts tubular, pointed, splitting adaxially, densely tomentose; other bracts membranous, pointed, small and inconspicuous; first-order branches adnate above the subtending bracts; rachillae short, narrow, spirally arranged, spreading, becoming smaller distally, bearing small triangular bracts each subtending a solitary flower. Flowers of two kinds, one hermaphoditic, the other staminate; calyx and receptacle forming a long pseudopedicel, calyx tubular basally with 3 triangular-lanceolate lobes; petals 3, distinct, much larger than the calyx, slightly imbricate; stamens 6, filaments distinct, elongate, anthers linear, sagittate basally, dorsifixed, versatile, latrorse; gynoecium unicarpellate, ovoid, style elongate, tubular, open distally with stigmatic area around the rim, ovule basal, probably hemianatropous. Pollen ellipsoidal, with slight to obvious asymmetry; aperture a distal sulcus; ectexine tectate, finely rugulate and micro-channelled, aperture margin psilate or scabrate; infratectum columellate; longest axis 30–35 µm [1/1]. Fruit globose with apical stigmatic scar; epicarp smooth, mesocarp thin, fleshy, endocarp smooth, membranous with anastomosing bundles. Seed globose with indistinct basal raphe, endosperm homogeneous; embryo nearly apical. Germination remote; eophyll simple. Cytology: 2n = 36.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>One species in Belize and Guatemala.</p></div>
<div type="relationships"><p>There are two different hypotheses on thephylogenetic position of Schippia in the Cryosophileae.Schippia is weakly supported as sister to Cryosophila (Roncal etal. 2008) or as sister to a clade of Zombia, Coccothrinax,Hemithrinax, Leucothrinax and Thrinax with low support (Baker et al. in review). </p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Occasionally cultivated.</p></div>
<div type="taxonomic accounts"><p>Burret (1933b); see also Balick and Johnson (1994). </p></div>
<div type="fossil record"><p>No generic records found.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Pinheiro (2001) describes the remote germination ofSchippia. During germination, the cotyledonary axis elongatesrapidly, followed by translocation of food reserves from theendosperm into the cotyledonary axis, which then becomesswollen; the first foliar organs then emerge through thecotyledonary sheath.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Pimento palm. </p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Occurring in the undergrowth of tropical rain forest.</p></div>
<div type="anatomy"><p>Leaf anatomy not studied, roots (Seubert 1997), floral (Morrow 1965).</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>
