<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus delessertianus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11:276. 1908 &amp; Appendix PL 101. 1913</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Probably a cluster-forming climber; stem unknown. Leaves ecirrate; petiole about 50 cm long; rachis subtrigonous on upper side, slightly concave below; leaflets equidistant, closely set on rachis, ensiform, 5-nerved; intermediate leaflets 32 - 35 cm long, 2 - 2.2 cm broad at middle, bristly at margins; midnerve and lateral nerves bristly. Female inflorescence slender; upper primary bract elongate, tubular at base; partial inflorescence 30 cm or more long with its base enclosed within the respective basal bract; rachillae distichous with their base attached to the axis on basal cushion just above the mouth of tubular, truncate respective basal bracts; basal rachillae about 6 cm long with about 90 flowers on each side; involucrophorum non-pedicelliform; female flowers 3 mm long; neuter flowers as long as female flowers. Fruits unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>South India.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Unknown</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>An understanding of this species is based on the original description. No old herbarium collections are available for study. A recent collection from the Silent Valley of Kerala appeared close to the description of Calamus dellessertianus. Beccari (1908) noted "it is curious that this species which was found in the time of Roxburgh has not been collected again by modern botanists. It seems to me that Calami in lower India are more scarce now than in the past time, perhaps on account of greater extension given to cultivation and owing to destruction of forest".</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Kerala: Palghat Dist. Silent Valley, 850 m. 12.10.1979. Nair 64536 (2 sheets in Madras).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>