<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis plurisecta</name>
<author>Jum.</author>
<citation>Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 3, 6 (1): 35 (1918)</citation>
<bibref>Jum., Bull. Ac. Malgache 6: 14 (1923)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum., Cat. Pl. Madagascar, Palmae: 14 (1938)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Fl. Madagascar 30: 46, fig. 12 (1945)</bibref>
<type>Probably from the Maroantsetra area; Perrier; 11966</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A fairly non-descript species, even though it is only known from the type - but under the microscope a most amazing feature becomes apparent: the stamens have the locules pendulous from a broad connective. These socalled 'geonomoid' stamens are known from very few Dypsis species, and resemble those of the genus Geonoma from South America (see page 125). The name 'plurisecta' is Latin for 'divided into several segments'.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Habit unknown. Distal internodes 0.5-1 cm long, c. 0.7 cm diam. LEAVES with the sheath 5-7 cm long, mostly glabrous but distally with scattered scales; petiole absent or up to 5 mm long; rachis 16-24 cm long, with scattered scales, in mid-leaf 1-1.5 mm diam., with c. 1 mm broad wings between the leaflets; leaflets 5-6 on each side of the rachis, regular or nearly so, opposite or occasionally one pair not opposite, the proximal 5-7 x 0.6-1.1 cm, median 10-15 x 1-2 cm, distal 6-10.5 x 1-2.2 cm, slightly sigmoid with attenuate apices, main veins 2-3, with minute scattered white scales on the minor veins, distal pair joined for 3-4 cm, dentate over c. 1 cm. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, branched to 1 order; peduncle 15-18 cm long, c. 1 mm diam, with scattered scales; prophyll 9-10 cm long, c. 3 mm wide, open in the distal 1 cm; peduncular bract insertedat 7-11 cm from the base of the peduncle, 5-7 cm long, open in the distal 1-2 cm; rachis 5-7 cm long, with c. 9 rachillae; rachillae 2.5-3 cm long, c. 1 mm diam., with scattered scales. STAMINATE FLOWERS in bud with sepals 0.5-0.7 x 0.6-0.8 mm; petals c. 1 x 0.8 mm; stamens 6, biseriate, the inner inserted higher up, filaments c. 0.2 mm long, anthers 0.3-0.4 x 0.3-0.4 mm, the locules pendulous from a broad connective (sub-geonomoid); pistillode c. 0.2 mm, conical. PISTILLATE FLOWERS unknown. FRUIT unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Uncertain, possibly Maroantsetra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Unknown.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Presumed extinct; not seen for over seventy years.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The protologue describes the stamens as three in number, with short filaments, a broad connective, and pendulous locules. All this is quite correct, except for the number of stamens, which is six. In a table on  p. 29 of the publication which contains the protologue, there is a description of the leaf sheath anatomy. This type of stamen also occurs, within Dypsis, in D. fasciculata, D. lokohoensis and D. thouarsiana, all species with three stamens.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Probably Maroantsetra ("label lost, without a doubt from the Maroantsetra area"), date unknown (before Aug. 1919), Perrier 11966 (Holotype P).   C</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>