<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Synopsis of the Rattans (Arecaceae: Calamoideae) of Laos and Neighbouring Parts of Indochina</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Evans</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">T.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Sengdala</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">K.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Thammavong</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">B.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Viengkham</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">O.V.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2002</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 57, No. 1 (2002), pp. 1-84</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus flagellum var. furvifurfuraceus</name>
<author>S. J. Pei &amp; S. Y Chen</author> 
<citation>Acta Phytotax. Sin. 27(2): 133 (1989);</citation>  
<type>China, Yunnan; S. Y Chen &amp; S. Q. Tong; 18990</type>
<type_loc>holotype HITBC</type_loc>
<bibref>Evans et al., Rattans Lao PDR: 55 (2001).</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="distribution"><p>China (South Yunnan) and Vietnam (Central Annam). The variety is only reported from Indochina.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>China (South Yunnan): Mengla, Mengdan, 20 March 1984, (pist.), Chen, S. Y. &amp; Tong, S. Q. 18990 (HITBC) and 20 May 1984, (ster.), Chen, S. Y. 18991 (HITBC). VIETNAM (CENTRAL ANNAM): Bach Ma town, 30 Jan. 1990, (stam.), Newman, M. 178 (K).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>At 1350 m in Vietnam</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>In the protologue this variety was diagnosed on the basis of the slightly grouped uppermost and lowermost leaflets, the petiole, rachis and sheath with dense brown indumentum and the smaller fruit. One specimen from the protologue, Xu, Y &amp; Zhang, YE Z. 14327, does not fit the diagnosis and we place it in the nominate variety, whilst Chen, S. Y. &amp; Yu, C. 6471 (also cited by Pei et al. 1989) was not seen. Grouped lower leaflets and extensive, dense, dark indumentum are not shown by specimens placed in the nominate variety, but the relevant part of the rachis is seldom preserved in any case. The type specimen of this variety has no fruit and the fruits of two others in the original description are not especially small, so we suggest that this character be disregarded. Although maintained here it seems likely that fuller field observations will show that the two varieties given here are synonymous, their apparent distinctness resulting from individual variation combined with collection of fragmentary material. For example, leaflet grouping is often seen in Calamus species on leaves from near the base of the stem even when the leaflets on upper leaves are regularly arranged (personal observations); it is particularly tempting to collect such unrepresentative leaves on a plant as huge as C. flagellum. Furthermore, indumentum tends to be thickest on young stems and freshly emerged organs, thinning out later.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Unknown.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>

