<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus insignis Griff. var. insignis</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<citation>Calcutta J. Nat. Hist. 5 (1844) 59</citation>
<bibref>Griffith in Palms Br. Ind. (1850) 69</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 459</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1908) 364 (in part)</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns. Bull. Singapore 15 (1956) 189 (in part?)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus spathulatus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc. in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 459</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1908) 360</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns. Bull. Singapore 15 (1956) 192</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Insignis - striking</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan batu</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering high climbing slender to moderate-sized rattan. Stems without sheaths to 7 mm; with to 1.5 cm, with internodes to 20 cm. All parts dry pale. Sheaths dull green armed with scattered upward-pointing pale yellow bulbous-based black-tipped spines to 3 mm high and scattered brownish scales. Knee prominent. Ocrea sometimes conspicuous. Flagellum to 2 m. Leaf ecirrate or subcirrate, or in some forms in the juvenile stage with a short cirrus. Petiole very short or to 15 cm long. Leaflets to 6 on each side, the terminal pair sometimes united or often only one terminal leaflet present and this much reduced; leaflets dull green, cucullate, thick in texture with prominent close lateral veins about 1.0 mm distant, the longest leaflet to 25 cm long by 7 cm wide, with a prominently thickened margin. Inflorescences male and female superficially similar to about 1.5 m long with up to 8 partialinflorescences to 12 cm long. Rachillae about 8 cm long. Ripe fruit oblong to 10 mm by 7 mm with a prominent beak to 2 mm long covered in 15-18 vertical rows of pale yellowish straw coloured scales. Seed oblong to 9 mm long by 5 mm wide, shallowly pitted. Endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf forked, the two leaflets joined for about 1/5 their length below, shiny green with prominent lateral veins.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Kedah, Perak, Pahang, Selangor, Trengganu, Negri Sembilan, Johore: Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Excellent small diameter cane entering the market as "rotan batu". Extensively used by "Orang Asli" as binding material and for fine basket ware.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This taxon is found in both lowland and hill Dipterocarp forest from sea-level to altitudes of nearly 800 m. It can be found at the edge of swamps and on ridgetops; it appears to be rather catholic in its ecological requirements.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>