<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sabah. Sabah Forest Records 13.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1984</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Sabah Forest Department</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops elongata</name>
<author>Bl.</author>
<citation>Rumphia 3: 16 (1847)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutt 139(1911)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Elongate, probably referring to the peduncle</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Moderate clustering rather short-stemmed rattan with stems rarely exceeding 4 m; stem without sheaths c 1 cm diam., with sheaths to 2 cm diam.; internodes rarely exceeding 6 cm. Leaf sheaths dark green rather densely covered with chocolate-coloured indumentum and armed with abundant scattered or partially whorled black reflexed or erect spines to 30 mm, usually much less, with pale bases; spines around leaf sheath mouth erect papery to 12 cm. Knee poorly developed. Leaf to 1.2 m, usually with a short cirrus to 30 cm with only a vestige, petiole to 40 cm, armed with distant, regular, large later to 5 cm, sometimes much shorter, and scattered shorter spines along the mid line of the abaxial surface; leaflets up to c 20 on each side of the rachis, regularly arranged below, irregularly arranged above; largest leaflets to 40 x 2 cm, armed with 3 rows of bristles on the upper surface, one row beneath, and along margins. Inflorescences male and female superficially similar, with rusty tomentose axes in very short stemme individuals with a long stalk to 30 cm, in climbing individuals with a much shorter stalk; all bracts quickly falling except for the first which may persist, to c 12 x 3 cm, brown, armed with distant groups of spines; male rachillae to 1 cm, female rachillae to 5 cm. Mature fruit relatively small, usually &#177; globose, up to 10 mm diam., covered in 15-19 vertical rows of straw-coloured scales (green when immature); seed globose, c 6 mm diam.; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Scattered throughout the lowlands of Sabah; elsewhere throughout endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>D. elongata is found in lowland Dipterocarp forest, usually on hill-slopes. D. elongata is usually separable on the basis of the irregularly arranged leaflets, the short stature, the long petiole spines and the usually rounded fruit.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>