<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus perakensis Becc. var. niger J.Dransf.</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 335</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary shortly climbing moderate rattan with stems to 5 m tall. Stem without sheaths 1.3 cm in diameter, with sheaths about 3 cm in diameter. Internodes about 20 cm long. Sheaths pale green with scattered pale brown spines to 4 cm long arranged in lateral groups of up to 7 (almost whorled) or solitary, and densely covered in caducous chocolate coloured scales; spines around leaf sheath mouth of two types, one type as the sheath spines but much longer, horizontally aligned and the second type papery, erect, deep purplish brown, to 30 cm long. No knee. Noflagellum Leaf ecirrate to 1.25 m long including petiole; petiole 40 cm armed with short lateral spines and densely covered with chocolate coloured scales. Leaflets about 35 on each side of the rachis, rather distant, &#177; divaricate, the lowermost longer than the rest, to 40 cm long by 2 cm wide, shortly brown bristly on 3 nerves on upper-side, minutely toothed along nerves below. Inflorescences male and female superficially similar, erect or arcuate, to 1.25 m long with 5 partial inflorescences peduncle to 30 cm &#177; unarmed. Bracts very large and conspicuous, tubular below, expanded and split to give a limb about 40 cm long by 5 cm wide, with few scattered triangular spines to 1 mm high and very dense chocolate-brown scales. Partial inflorescences very crowded, to 15 cm long with distichous rachillae; female to 7 cm long, the male to 1.5 cm. Flowers and fruit and seedling leaf unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Johore: endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Differs from the type variety in being solitary and erect and bearing greatly expanded bract limbs, the sheaths, petioles, leaf rachis and bracts all covered in dense chocolate - black scales.
This variety is quite common along swamp margins in east Johore.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>