<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops longistipes</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<citation>Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Mus. Berlin-Dahlem 15: 798 (1943)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 36: 810 (1982)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 68 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 57 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops elongata var. montana</name>
<author>Becc. ex L. S. Gibbs</author>
<bibref>J. Linn. Soc. Bot. 42: 169 (1914)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops pleioclada</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<bibref>Burret, Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Mus. Berlin-Dahlem 15: 797 (1943)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>With a long stalk</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering to moderate montane rattan climbing to 10 m, usually less, rarely flowering when &#177; stemless; stem without sheaths to 10 mm diam., with sheaths to 30 mm diam., internodes short, generally not exceeding c. 8 cm. Sheaths yellowish-green, covered with dark brown indumentum and very abundant black spines to 1-20 mm, in short lateral groups, the spines fragile and breaking off, leaving short stubs on old sheaths, spines around the sheath mouth erect and papery, to 6 cm; knee well developed. Leaf cirrate to 2.5 m long (much less in slender forms) including cirrus to 80 cm and petiole to 40 cm; petiole armed with horizontal spines to 1.5 cm; leaflets regularly arranged, to c. 45 on each side of the rachis, the longest to 35 &#215; 2 cm, armed with scattered bristles or unarmed on the upper surface, armed with a row of bristles along the main vein beneath. Inflorescences arching, to 30 cm, with a peduncle 5-15 cm long; bracts closely tubular at first, splitting and falling at anthesis; male rachilla rusty tomentose to 1 cm, female similarly tomentose, to 8 cm. Mature fruit ovoid or depressed globose, to 13 &#215; 15 mm, covered in 15-21 vertical rows of reflexed straw-coloured scales. Seed globose, c. 10 mm diam.; endosperm ruminate. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 15).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Abundant in lower montane forest G. Pagon and Bt. Retak. Elsewhere in Sabah and Sarawak. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a strong cane; it is not known whether it is of any commercial significance.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species is one of the most conspicuous rattans of montane forest in the headwaters of the Temburong River at altitudes of 1,200-1,800 m above sea level. It is variable, some forms being very slender. It is closely related to D. korthalsii and other members of the complex of D. hystrix.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Wong 1914; Amo, Bt. Pagon, Wong 1756; Amo, Bt. Retak, Wong 789.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>