<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus marginatus</name>
<author>(Bl.) Mart.</author>
<citation>Hist. Nat. Palm. 3: 342 (1853)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2: 208 (1902)</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 326 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 36: 793 (1982)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 183 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops marginatus</name>
<author>Bl.</author>
<bibref>Bl. in Rumphia 3: 24 (1847)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus rostratus</name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<bibref>Furtado in Gard. Bull. Str. Settlements 8: 257 (1935)</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus regularis</name>
<author>Burret</author>
<bibref>Burret in Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Mus. Berlin-Dahlem 15: 816 (1943)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Margined</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Uwai Pagit (Dus.), Wi Matahari (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary, rarely clustering, moderate to robust rattan climbing to 15 m or more, but frequently flowering when only 3-4 m tall; stem without sheaths to 18 mm diam., with sheaths to 20-35 mm diam., internodes generally rather short, not usually more than 10 cm. Sheaths dull dark green, densely armed with scattered triangular flattened black spines, 3-40 mm (in montane forms spines around the leaf sheath mouth crowded, erect, very long, to 140 mm), black indumentum abundant between the spines; knee grossly swollen; ocrea membranous, to 7 mm, usually obscured by spines. Flagellum to 5 m, heavily armed with reflexed spines. Leaf ecirrate, distinctly curved, to c. 1.5 m including the petiole to 35 cm; petiole strongly channelled on upper surface, armed with regular groups of spines 5-20 mm along the margins, and a central row of spines to 20 mm on the lower surface; leaflets 40-60 on each side of the rachis, curved, very regular, c. 3 cm apart, the longest to 35 &#215; 1.5 cm, leaflet margins slightly but distinctly thickened, unarmed on the upper surface, lower surface with 3-5 main veins armed with close very short bristles, transverse veinlets conspicuous. Inflorescence flagellate, very long, to 5 m or more, bearing up to 5 very distant pendulous partial inflorescences, to 1 m or more long, in male partial inflorescences branching twice to give short dark brown rachillae to 2 cm, bearing dense distichous flowers, in female branching once to give rachillae c. 20 cm long, bearing lax distichous flowers. Mature fruit ovoid, c. 16 &#215; 12 mm, tipped with a beak to 2 mm and covered in 15 vertical rows of reddish-brown scales. Seed to 12 &#215; 8 &#215; 7 mm, deeply pitted; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf pinnate with 6 very narrow leaflets held in a fan. (Fig. 68).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread throughout Brunei. A common Bornean rattan, also known from Sumatra and Palawan.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces a coarse but durable cane of poor appearance, much used for the frameworks of carrying baskets.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This is one of the most widespread of Bornean rattans, occurring from sea level to 1,800 m altitude, and also one of the most variable.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>District not traced: Jalan Tengah, Stockdale 64. BEL: Bukit Sawat, Sg.Mau- Sg. Belait confluence, Wong 1622; Sukang, Sungai Paleh Bangawong, Kirkup 661; Sungai Liang, Sungei Liang Arboretem, Wong 142. TEM: Amo, Bt.Retak, Wong 790. TUT: Rambai, Tasek Merimbun, Bernstein 338.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>