<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus vattayila</name>
<author>Renuka</author>
<citation>Curr. Sci. 56 : 1012. 1987</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Vattayila, Ottoman (Mai.).</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A high climbing rattan; stem cluster-forming, 15 m or more long, with leafsheath 2.5 cm in diameter; naked stem 1.8 cm in diameter; internodes to 27 cm long. Leaves ecirrate, to 1 m long; leafsheath dark green, sparingly spiny, spines 2 cm long, upwardly pointed, infrequent; leafsheath knee conspicuous; ocrea 5 mm long; leafsheath flagellum dark green, 4 m long, petiole to 25 cm long, armed with about 1 cm long spines; rachis armed below with digitate claws; leaflets dark green, alternate, oblong, 40 x 10 cm, prominently 6 nerved, bristly at apices. Inflorescence flagelliform; axial part near base 1 cm in diameter; partial inflorescences about 5 in number, 28 cm long, once branched, with closely shehating subtending bracts; each bract lanceolate at upper free part; axial part of inflorescence armed with 3 mm long spines; rachillae 5 cm long, with distinct alternate cup-like bracts. Female flowers 5 mm long. Fruit oblong, falsely pedicellate with distinct columnar 4 mm long beak, 2.8 cm x 1.4cm., fruit scales light brown, minute, without channelled at middle, arranged in 25 longitudinal rows; 1-seeded, seed sculptured on one side, oblong, 1.5 cm x 8 mm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Grows in the evergreen forests of Thenmala, Ranni and Wynad. Sporadic in distribution between 200-750 m.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Introduced in the experimental plots of Kerala Forest Research Institute, Peechi, Kerala.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Unknown.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>