<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
		<mods:name><mods:namePart>Dransfield, J and Beentje, H.</mods:namePart></mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Lemurophoenix halleuxii</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 46: 62 (1991)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Maroantsetra; Dransfield et al.; JD6453</type>
<type_loc>Holotype K; isotypes BH, MO, NY, P, TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>This majestic palm, probably the grandest palm of the whole island, occurs in a steep-sided valley below the long ridge leading eastwards from the village of Sahavary, northeast of Maroantsetra. The valley is at about 350-450 m above sea level. There is a great abundance of palms in the forest here, yet there is little peculiar about the habitat. Furthermore Lemurophoenix does not occur in similar valleys nearby. As one drops down from the crest of the ridge, suddenly one becomes aware of immense palms in the forest canopy in the valley bottom, the huge grey-ish-pink crownshafts and vast bunches of fruit standing out amidst the surrounding dull green. There are about 30 mature individuals and about 20 juveniles in various stages of development. Beneath the mature trees lie thick carpets of bare endocarps, either newly fallen or rotting. Seedlings are distinctive but very scarce. It appears that there is little effective dispersal and very limited regeneration. Recently a single mature tree has been discovered in a deep valley further south on the Masoala Peninsula.  ; As one of the most beautiful and spectacular palms of Madagascar, Lemurophoenix halleuxii, the red-lemur palm, has been much sought after. Seeds are harvested regularly from the Sahavary locality, most of them exported to palm enthusiasts and nurserymen. However, it has proved to be difficult to grow so far. Growing conditions that mimic the natural habitat would seem to be the most likely to lead to success. The species was named for Dominique Halleux who was among the team of people who first located the palm in the mid 1980s.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Hovitra vari mena (Betsimisaraka).</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Massive solitary unarmed monoecious pleonanthic tree palm. TRUNK bare to 20 m tall, c. 1 m diam. at very base, c. 50 cm d.b.h., tapering somewhat distally, ringed with leaf scars. Crownshaft well developed, to 1.5 m long, c. 50 cm diam. LEAF with sheath greyish-pink when newly exposed, bearing white wax and dark brown scales; petiole c. 25 cm long, c. 10 cm wide, c. 5 cm thick, channelled adaxially, rounded or ridged abaxially, densely covered with caducous chocolate-brown scales; rachis to 4.25 m long, adaxially somewhat channelled near the base, ridged distally, abaxially rounded or flattened, scaly as the petiole; leaflets c. 60 on each side of the rachis, regularly arranged, linear-lanceolate, long acuminate except near the tip where bifid, the proximal to 65 x 2 cm, mid-leaf leaflets to 95 x 6 cm, decreasing abruptly to 17 x 0.7 cm near the leaf tip, adaxial leaflet surface glabrous, abaxial bearing a few large dark brown ramenta near the base on the main vein and more numerous small ramenta on secondary veins, pale brown peltate scales abundant on all veins; transverse veinlets not visible; emerging rachis crimson, expanding blade flushed red. INFLORESCENCE massive, to 2 m long, infrafoliar, branched to 3 orders, the whole inflorescence exposed long before anthesis, protandrous; peduncle c. 50 cm long, grossly swollen and winged to 35 cm wide at the base, decreasing to 10 x 4.5 cm; prophyll to 90 x 30 cm, inserted c. 15 cm above base of peduncle, abaxially bright crimson, cream-coloured within, splitting along one side; peduncular bract to 120 x 30 cm, inserted c. 10 cm above prophyll, otherwise similar; first-order branches c. 12-15, widely spreading, the basal few devoid of branches in the basal 20-25 cm, to 4-5 cm thick, then branched to the third order, the distal first-order branches branched to the second order or unbranched; rachillae c. 110, elongate, pendulous or spreading, to 40 cm long, c. 8-9 mm diam., cream-coloured when newly emerged, becoming green, somewhat swollen, with flowers partially embedded in shallow pits c. 6-10 mm apart, rachilla surface minutely papillose and scaly; rachilla bracts rather obscure, 2 x 8 mm, forming the lower lip to the pits; floral bracteoles minute, included in the pits. FLOWERS borne in triads of a central pistillate and two lateral staminate for about two-thirds the rachilla length, and in pairs of staminate flowers in the distal third. STAMINATE FLOWERS in bud &#177; bullet-shaped, greenish brown, c. 8 x 5 mm; sepals c. 3.5 x 6 mm, strongly keeled and gibbous; petals; c. 7 x 3 mm, pale brown; stamens 52-59, borne on the dome-shaped receptacle, filaments terete, 2-4 x 0.1 mm, straight or contorted in bud, anthers c. 2 x 0.5 mm; pistillode columnar, c. 1.5 x 0.2 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS known only in immature bud, c. 4.5 mm diam.; sepals c. 3.5 x 4.5 mm; petals c. 3.5 mm long; staminodes 0.4 x 0.2 mm; gynoecium c. 2.5 x 1.5 mm. FRUIT chestnut brown, c. 50 mm diam. at maturity, usually borne in abundance, globose, the epicarp cracked polygonally into low corky warts less than 1 mm high, 2-5 mm across; mesocarp c. 8 mm thick, whitish, rather spongy, easily separable from the endocarp; endocarp spherical, c. 33 mm diam., with a basal heart-shaped pale brown button 11 x 11 x 7 mm. SEED endosperm very shallowly and sparsely ruminate. EOPHYLL bifid.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Masoala Peninsula and environs.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Growing on steep slopes and in a deep narrow valley in primary forest at 200-450 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Endangered. Only known from two populations; numbers very low (c. 50); not protected.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Maroantsetra, Andranofotsy River, Sahavary, hills east of village, Andilampananina, Oct. 1986 (fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6402 (BH, K, MO, NY, P, TAN); idem, Feb. 1988 (fl., fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6453 (Holotype K; isotypes BH, MO, NY, P, TAN); Masoala Peninsula, Nov. 89 (fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6742 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>