<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A Synopsis of the Genus Korthalsia (Palmae: Lepidocaryoideae)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 1, pp. 163-194</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1981</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia merrillii</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 128 (1918)</citation>
<bibref>Becc., Philip. J. Sci. 14: 342 (1919)</bibref>
<bibref>Brown &amp; Merr. in Brown, Minor Products Philip. Forests 1: 212 (1920)</bibref>
<bibref>Merr., Enum. Philip. Fl. Pl. 1: 146 (1922)</bibref>
<type>Philippines, Palawan, Malampaya Bay; Merrill; 9410</type>
<type_loc>Holotype PNH†; isotype FI</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p></p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Endemic to Palawan, where it appears to be frequent in the area near Puerto Princesa (pers. obs.).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>This species seems to be confined to soils derived from ultrabasic rock</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Ripe fruit of this species were not available to Beccari. A more recent collection from Palawan (Reynoso PNH 87810) in Kew and Leiden consists of stems bearing leaves and infructescences which certainly belong to K. merrillii, and loose ripe fruit. The fruit are mentioned in the accompanying field notes so there is strong likelihood that they belong to K. merrillii; however they are so extraordinary in scale structure, that, though they are obviously Korthalsia fruits I hesitate to ascribe such characters as a specific diagnostic feature, when they may only be a monstrous development. New fruiting material is required. The fruit in the Reynoso collection are described thus: Fruit 18 x 14 mm diam., abruptly tipped by the stigmatic remains to 1.5 x 0-5 mm; scales pale shiny brown, arranged in 14-15 vertical rows, the mid line of each scale being very deep, with the area of scale on either side strongly convex; scale tip deeply impressed into the mid line of the scale beneath. These curious, deeply grooved scales have not been noted in any other species.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>