<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Species of Pinanga (Palmae : Arecoideae) from Luzon Island, Philippines</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Fernando</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">E.S.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 49, No. 4, pp. 775-784</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1994</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pinanga sierramadreana</name>
<author>Fernando</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 49: 780 (1994)</citation>
<type>Luzon, Quezon Prov., Nakar, Sierra Madre Mountains, Sitio Sablang; Fernando; 521 </type>
<type_loc>Holotypus LBC; isotypus K</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>P. isabelense Becc. habitu, magnitudine et characteribus infructescentiarum fructuumque similis sed indumento squamoso vaginis foliorum cineraceo-brunneo, foliolis brevioribus subtus subglaucis in siccitate brunneolis differt.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary slender unarmed pleonanthic monoecius undergrowth palm, to 5 m tall. Stem to 2.5 cm diam.; internodes 2.5-8 cm long. Crownshaft elongate, cylindrical, slightly swollen, to 34 cm long. Leaves to 5 in crown; sheath to 27 cm long, greyish-green, covered with greyish-brown scaly indumentum; leaf without sheath to 90 cm long; petiole c. 16-35 x 0.7 cm, flattened or only slightly channelled adaxially, convex abaxially, covered with indumentum as the sheath; rachis angular, bifacial adaxially and nearly glabrous, obtusely rounded abaxially and covered with brown scaly indumentum. Leaflets 6- 10 on each side of the rachis, unequal, ? sigmoidal, inequidistant, c. 2.5 - 7.5 cm apart, the costae above sharply elevated, slightly glaucescent below when fresh, but drying brownish, ramentae present along the main costae below; basal leaflets 1-2-costate, c. 10-16 x 0.8-1.7 cm; middle leaflets 1-6-costate, c. 17-25 x 1.3-7 cm; apical leaflets 6-9-costate, c. 14 x 8 cm, joined at the base to 10 cm along the rachis, + cuneiform, the tips incised to as many lobes as there are costae, the lobes to 2 cm long and further incised at their tips to 8 mm deep. Inflorescence infrafoliar, pendulous; prophyll not known; peduncle c. 3-5 x 0.5 cm, flattened; main axis to 4.5 cm long, tapering distally; rachillae often 6-8, rarely to 11, borne 0.7-2 cm apart, each c. 11-19 cm long, flattened and ± straight, to 2 mm wide, 1 mm thick when dry; the subtending bract very narrowly annulate, shortly apiculate at middle part to 0.5 mm; peduncle and rachillae purplish-red when young. Staminate and pistillate flowers not known. Infructescence pendulous. Fruiting perianth depressed-cupular, 2 mm high, 3 mm across, with a flat base and contracted mouth, the sepals and petals free and imbricate, subequal, glabrous, glossy when dry; the subtending bract a very low explanate, semi-annular collar. Fruit distichous, c. 8-13 mm apart, green ripening red then purplish-black, fusiform-ellipsoid or ovoid, c. 1.2 x 0.6 cm, shortly beaked; epicarp drying light brown and finely striate; mesocarp thinly fibrous; seed ovoid, c. 1.0 x 0.5 cm, acute at tip, caudiculate at base; endosperm ruminate; embryo basal.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Luzon (Nueva Vizcaya and Quezon Provs.)</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>In dipterocarp forest; c. 800 m. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species resembles P. isabelensis in growth habit and size and in general features of the infructescence and fruits, but differs in the glaucescent greyish- brown scaly indumentum of the leafsheath and in the leaflets much shorter, glaucescent on the undersurface and drying light brown. A sheet at PNH (Gutierrez 61-289) collected from Sancad, Palanan in nearby Isabela Province probably also belongs here. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>LUZON. Nueva Vizcaya Prov., Mt Caraballo, Vidal 3951 (K); Quezon Prov., Nakar, Sierra Madre Mountains, Sitio Sablang, Fernando 521 (holotype LBC; isotype K), 526 (LBC), 705 and 707 (K, LBC), Sitio Kabanbanan, Fernando 767 (BH, K, LBC), and 860 (K, LBC).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>