<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the Rattans of Andaman and Nicobar Islands</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Renuka</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kerala Forest Research Institute, India</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops kurzianus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>in Hook f., Fl. Brit. Ind. 6: 463. 1893</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12 : 60. 1991</bibref>
<bibref>Basu, Rattans in India Monogr. Rev.: 44. 1992</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Sanka beth</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering large diameter rattan. Stem 20 m long or more, with sheaths 5 cm in diameter, without sheaths 4 cm in diameter. Leaf 3 m long or more, cirrate; sheath yellowish green, densely armed with spines; spines brown, dimorphic, larger ones 2.5 cm long,, base 0.8 cm broad, flat, triangular, papery, brownish with upraised base, smaller ones 1.5 x 0.2 cm, spines above the knee uniform, 1.5 x 0.2 cm, mouth of the sheath with numerous, papery spines, spines to 6 cm long; knee prominent; ocrea riot seen; petiole long, margins spiny; spines to 1 cm long, 3 cm broad; rachis with a single row of reflexed spines at the lower side, upper side with small spines, spines to 0.5 cm long; leaflets regular, the largest to 50 x 3 cm, margins with bristles, midrib prominent, lateral veins ciliate above towards the distal end. Inflorescence erect, covered by an armed sheath; partial inflorescence to 15 cm long; primary sheath long, broad, free, unarmed; rachilla to 7 cm long. Fruit globose, ca. 1.7x 1.5cm; scales in 18 vertical rows, orange yellow on ripening, border dark brown, deeply channelled in the middle; endosperm ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Common species of cane in evergreen forests at South Andamans.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Flowering November-December. Fruiting April-June.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Extensively used in furniture industry.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Tharmugali, Wondoor, South Andamans, 8.4.1988, fr., Renuka 4062 (KFRI).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>