<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Pogonotium moorei</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Principes 26: 174 (1982)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>H. E. Moore Jr., 1917 - 1980, eminent palm botanist</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary, low, short-stemmed erect rattan, not exceeding 2 m tall. Stem without sheaths c. 10 mm diam., with sheaths c. 18 mm diam., internodes c. 5 cm long. Sheaths armed with abundant, close, oblique and horizontal combs of black or straw-coloured spines, 1-22 mm long and abundant pale brown tomentum; ear-like processes c. 8.5 x 1.5 cm, gradually tapering, convex, armed as the sheath on the outer surface, the inner surface unarmed. Leaf to 1.1 m, ecirrate or with a minute vestige of a cirrus; petiole to 50 cm, scabrid, armed with scattered reflexed spines; leaflets few, distant, regularly arranged, c. 9 on each side of the rachis, &#177; divaricate, the longest c. 32 x 2.5 cm, the apical pair much smaller, the margins sparsely bristly, otherwise bristles lacking; young leaves tinged pink. Inflorescence, only female known, very small and inconspicuous, held erect between the auricles; peduncle very short or absent, the prophyll c. 12 cm long, split opposite the leaf sheath (?always), hairy and bearing abundant spines and spicules as the sheath; other bracts small. Flowers small, glabrous. Mature fruit obpyriform, c. 13 x 9 mm, tipped with a short beak and covered in 15 - 16 vertical rows of pinkish-brown, scarcely channelled scales. Seed ellipsoid, c. 11 x 7 mm, the sarcotesta thin. Seedling leaf with 2 very small widely diverging leaflets tipped with bristles (Fig. 98).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>A very rare palm known only from G Gaharu on the border with Kalimantan in the 1st Division; endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>P. moorei is so far known only from a few individuals observed near the summit of G Gaharu at c. 600m altitude; it grows in very mossy, submontane kerangas forest on sandstone. It is very inconspicuous and could be passed over as a seedling of a species of Calamus or Daemonorops. From the other two species of Pogonotium it is immediately distinguishable by the very few leaflets and the top-shaped fruit.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>