<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis coriacea</name>
<author>Beentje</author> 
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 311 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Sahavary; Dransfield et al.; JD6459</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi P, TAN</type_loc>			
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A very attractive small palm with thick shiny leaves. This species was known as 'leather-leaf' among collectors, and the Latin name is a straight translation of this. The entire leaf dries pale green, which is most distinctive.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Gregem palmunculorum 6-staminatorum foliis integris pertinens D. lucenti affinis sed rachillis lepidotis et folio glabro multo coriaceo differt.</p></div>  
<div type="description"><p>Solitary or clustering palm. STEM(S) 1-2 m, diam. &#60; 1 cm; distal internodes 2-4.5 cm, pale green with dense to scattered reddish pubescence; nodal scars c. 1 mm. LEAVES 6-9 in the crown, entire or with 4 leaflets; sheath 4-9 cm long, closed, pale brown with reddish scales and without or with auricles to 8 mm long; petiole 1-12 cm long, channelled, c. 2 mm diam., with scattered scales; lamina entir e, leathery, rich shiny green and occasionally metallic-tinged, 15-41 x 6-8 cm, lobes 5-12 x 1.5-4 cm; main vein 1, with sparse red and white scales on the midrib, otherwise with few scattered scales to glabrous, the lamina often white-punctate, often with a single deep (to 6 cm) lacuna, in the distal quarter the margins toothed, the teeth to 16 mm long. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, unbranched, spreading; peduncle 8-28 cm long, 2-3 mm diam., glabrous; prophyll 5-16 cm long, 4-6 mm wide, opening in the distal 1cm only, with scattered scales to almost glabrous; peduncular bract inserted at 5-13 from the base of the peduncle, 3-12 cm long, open in the distal 1-1.5 cm, with scattered scales, quickly deciduous; non-tubular peduncular bract 2-2.5 mm; rachilla 3-26 cm long, 1-2 mm diam., densely pubescent to puberulous, with distant triads. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.8-1.5 x 0.7-1.6 mm, ciliolate, with scales; petals white, 1.8-2.4 x 1-1.7 mm, striate; stamens 6, uniseriate or very slightly biseriate, filaments 0.8-1.5 mm, thin, anthers 0.8-1.6 x 0.3-0.6 mm, versatile; pistillode 0.7-1 x 0.3-0.5 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.8-1.2 x 1.4-1.7 mm; petals 2.1-4 x 1-2.8 mm; staminodes 6, c. 0.5 mm; ovary c. 2 x 1.3 mm. FRUIT when young narrowly ovoid, 11-15 x 4.5-6 mm, obtuse, with fleshy mesocarp and fibrous endocarp. SEED c. 12.5 x 4 mm, with homogeneous endosperm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Masoala, Maroantsetra and Mananara.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest; on steep slope near stream, or on ridgetops; 200-400 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Vulnerable. The species has a limited distribution area, most of which is unprotected and under some threat.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The species somewhat resembles D. lucens but the leaf veins are glabrous and there are no ramenta; the rachilla is puberulous. It also resembles D. catatiana, but has versatile stamens (not didymous ones). There is some variation in the degree of lobing and the length of the rachilla.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Maroantsetra: Hiaraka, Ampanga R., Oct. 1986 (bud), Dransfield et al. JD6382 (K, TAN); Sahavary, Feb. 1988 (fl., y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6459 (Holotype K; isotypes P, TAN); Antalavia, Feb. 1988 (fl.), Dransfield et al. JD6482 (K, TAN); Andronabe, feb. 1992 (fl.), Zjhra &amp; Hutcheon 120 (K). Mananara Avaratra, Antanambe, April 1992 (fl., y.fr.), Beentje et al. 4617 (BH, K, MO, P, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>