<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis fanjana</name>
<author>Beentje</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 258 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Mananara Avaratra, Antanambe; Beentje; 4453</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi BH, MO, TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>Rather like D. faneva, but with entire or hardly dissected leaves. The name comes from the local name for the species.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Fanjana (Betsimisaraka)</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>D. mangorensi simillima sed petiolo breve antheris didymis differt.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering palm in tufts of 3-4, occasionally appearing solitary. STEMS 2.5-5 m high, 1-1.5 cm diam.; internodes 2.5-6.5 cm long; stem occasionally with basal aerial roots to 20 cm long. LEAVES 6-11 in the crown, spirally inserted, entire or rarely with a few leaflets, arching; sheath green, 12-15 cm long, pale reddish-brown when dry, with few scattered scales, with c. 5 mm high ligules; petiole absent or up to 8 cm long; lamina entire and 57-62 cm long, with scattered scales on the minor and major veins, the midrib 20-21 cm long, the lobes 34-39 x 4.3-8.5 cm, the apices narrowly dentate; or pinnate with rachis 18-24 cm long; 2 (-3) leaflets on each side of the rachis, the proximal 15- 56 x 0.5-5.3 cm, the distal 40-44 x 3-4.1 cm, main veins 5, with scattered scales on minor and major veins, proximal leaflets acuminate, distal ones dentate over c. 5 mm, distal pair joined for c. 7 cm. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, branching to 1 order, porrect with pendulous rachillae; peduncle 24-47 cm long, with a few scattered scales; prophyll 22-27 cm long, opening in the distal 2-4 cm, with scattered scales; peduncular bract inserted at c. 20 cm from the base of the peduncle, c. 16 cm long, opening in the distal 3 cm, with scattered scales; rachis 2-13 cm, with 3-7 rachillae; rachillae 16-25 cm long, green, puberulous in the triad depressions, with distant yellow buds. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.7-0.8 x 0.6-0.7 mm; petals 1.2-1.6 x 0.9-1 mm; stamens 6, biseriate (offset c. 0.2 mm), didymous, connate for c. 0.3 mm, filaments c. 0.5 x 0.4-0.5 mm, anthers c. 0.3 x 0.5 mm; pistillode 0.3-0.4 x 0.4 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS unknown. FRUIT unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from Mananara Biosphere Reserve.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest, steep mid slope; 115-250 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Endangered. Known from a   single site, outside the protected area, where we have seen less than fifty individuals.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Remarkably like D. mangorensis - but for the short petiole, the more slender rachillae with less conspicuous bracts and the didymous anthers. Close but not the same is Perrier 12038 (P), Antalaha: Marambo, Oct 1912 (young bud), which has larger staminate sepals. The stamens are too young to study.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Mananara Avaratra: Antanambe, Oct. 1991 (bud), Beentje 4453 (Holotype K; isotypes BH, MO, TAN); idem, Oct. 1991 (old infl.), Beentje 4459 (BH, K, MO, P, TAN); idem, Oct. 1994 (bud), Dransfield &amp; Beentje JD7506 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>