<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>A synopsis of the Genus Physokentia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Moore</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Principes 13(4) 120-136</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1969</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Physokentia tete</name>
<author>(Beccari) Beccari</author>
<citation>Martelli, Atti Soc. Tosc. Sci. Nat. Pisa, Mem. 44:153 [reprint 42]. 1934</citation>
<type>New Hebrides, Banks group: Vanua Lava, 1000 m.; A. E. Harland;</type>
<type_loc>Type FI; type BH</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Cyphosperma ? tete</name>
<author>Beccari</author>
<bibref>Beccari, Webbia 3:137. 1910</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>tete</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Trunk 6-7 cm. in diam. Leaves probably regularly pinnate; central pinnae lanceolate-sigmoid, obliquely truncate and praemorse-toothed at the apex(?), ca. 60 cm. long, 5.5-6 cm. wide, with a prominent elevated mid-nerve and a prominent secondary nerve on each side, dull green above, the lower surface somewhat paler with minutely puncticulate nerves, the midnerve and 2 prominent lateral nerves also with rather prominent, brown, basifixed, membranous scales. Inflorescence short-pedunculate, broader than long, the axes with rather dense, substellate, brownish or white scales in bud, glabrous in fruit; upper bract brown, very thin; rachis angled, sinuous, with more than 7 branches; lower branches again branched into flexuous rachillae of the second order to 15 cm. long, upper branches furcate or simple; bracts subtending the triads prominent, acute; bracteoles surrounding the pistillate flowers very narrow, not conspicuously white-barbate on the upper margins. Staminate flowers ovoid, somewhat asymmetric and angled by mutual pressure, 5.5-6 mm. long, 3 mm. wide; sepals with strongly ciliolate margins; petals 2-3 times as long as the sepals; pistillode columnar, very slightly enlarged at the apex, nearly as long as the stamens in bud: pistillate flowers ovoid-conic in bud. Fruit globose, 2.5-2.6 cm. high, 2.3 cm. in diam., with excentrically apical stigmatic residue, smooth when dry; mesocarp fleshy, with few fibers; endocarp thick, slightly woody, 2.4 cm. high, 2.1 cm. wide and across, with prominent adaxial (ventral) keel, prominent abaxial (dorsal) keel, and 2 prominent ridges on each side, the surface rough and becoming rugose on each side of the adaxial keel, operculum rounded-angled; seed shaped as the endocarp, 1.7 cm. high, 1.4-1.5 cm. wide and across; endosperm homogeneous.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The type of Physokentia Tete consists of a fruiting panicle, an inflorescence in bud, and two unattached pinnae. The pinnae appear to be praemorse at the apex, as described by Beccari and noted by myself when I examined the type. With further experience, I now wonder whether the pinnae are truly praemorse or merely appear so because of fraying, a not infrequent occurrence but not de-terminable from the photographs. New collections are required before a complete description can be provided, yet the species is abundantly distinct in the characteristics of the endocarp alone.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>NEW HEBRIDES, BANKS GROUP: VANUA LAVA; 1000 m., A. E. Harland (FI, type; BH, photos and fragments).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>