<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus nematospadix</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Rec. Bot. Surv. India 2:204 (1902)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 83 (1908)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>With thread-like inflorescences</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Variable slender, solitary or clustered rattan climbing to 5 m tall, rarely more; stem without sheaths 5-10 mm diam., with sheaths 10 - 20 mm diam., internodes rather short, rarely more than 12 cm. Sheaths green, armed with sparse to very dense triangular flattened black spines to 15 mm with hairy margins, sheaths drying reddish-brown; knee conspicuous; ocrea short, membranous. Flagellum to 2 m. Leaf ecirrate to 90 cm long, usually less, including the petiole to 45 cm, rachis sparsely red hairy; leaflets 15 - 30 on each side of the rachis (9 only in one extreme form - see below), regularly arranged, linear or lanceolate, the longest to 30 x 2 cm, but usually smaller, armed with scattered spines along margins and nerves on the upper surface, very sparse beneath, transverse veinlets close, sinuous conspicuous. Inflorescence to 3 m with c. 3 partial inflorescences; male rachillae 2-20 mm long, thread-like', female rachillae to 40 x 2 mm. Mature fruit rounded, c. 5 mm diam., beaked, covered in 12 - 13 vertical rows of straw-coloured scales with dark margins. Seed &#177; rounded; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known (Fig. 89).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Widespread in 1st Division. Rare in Kalimantan. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. nematospadix is found from sea level to c. 1,400 m in the mountains. It is usually associated with forest on poorer soils, including kerangas. It is very variable and I have been much perplexed by its relationships with C comptus and C psilodadus. I have tentatively identified as C. nematospadix two collections (Dransfield et al JD 6100 and JD 5908) from the summit of G Gaharu. This last taxon is a very slender rattan with nine slightly irregular leaflets and inflorescences developing into new shoots at their tips. In flower and fruit it seems not to differ from C. nematospadix and may represent an extreme form developed on very poor soils in submontane kerangas.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>