<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis hiarakae</name>
<author>Beentje</author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 286 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Ambanizana, Oct 1986 (y. fr.); Dransfield et al.; JD6398</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypus TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>A slightly nondescript medium-sized palm from rain forest in the north. The name refers to a village on the west coast of Masoala.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Sinkiara, Tsirika (Tsimihety).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>palma solitaria folio irregulariter pinnato pinnis fasciculatis inflorescentia in 2 vel 3 ordines ramificanti flore staminato 6 staminibus antheris versatalibus endospermio homogeneo distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm. STEM 3-6 m, 1.2-2.5 cm diam., sometimes stilt-root-ed at the base; internodes 1.5-6 cm long, pale green, &#177; glabrous. LEAVES 7-9 in the crown, arching, pinnate; sheath 18-22 cm long, 2/3 closed, pale green with few scattered scales, denser distally, with ragged margins; petiole 15-17 cm long, 5-8 x 2-4 mm diam., adaxially flat, with scattered brown scales; rachis 35-67 cm long, in mid-leaf 2-4 mm wide, with scattered scales; leaflets 12-21 on each side of the rachis, in groups of 2-5, slightly fanned, the group interval 5-12 cm, leaflet interval 0.5-0.9 cm, the proximal 18-24 x 0.3-0.9 cm, median 15-31 x 1.5-5 cm, distal 10-25 x 1.3-4.5 cm, main veins 1-3 (in the distal pair 3-5), with scattered scales on the major and minor veins, and sometimes with long ramenta, apices attenuate, distal pair joined for 1-5 cm, with the apices dentate over a width of 5-10 mm. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, branched to 2 (rarely 3) orders, erect with numerous arching to hanging rachillae; peduncle 7-37 cm long, proximally c. 12 x 4 mm, distally 3-6 x 3.5-5 mm, densely scaly; prophyll 10-19 cm long, 8-12 mm wide, borne at 1-4 cm above the base of the peduncle, with scattered scales, open in the distal 1-3.5 cm; peduncular bract inserted at 9-14 cm from the base of the peduncle, 14-26 cm long, open for most of its length, beaked for 3 cm, glabrous, rapidly deciduous; rachis 7.5-17 cm long, glabrous or nearly so with 7-10 branched and 5-8 unbranched first order branches, the proximal of these with an axis of up to 7 cm with up to 6 rachillae; rachillae 17-27 cm long, 1-2 mm diam., glabrous to puberulous. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 1-1.2 x 1-1.2 mm; petals 2.8-3 x 1.5-2 mm; stamens 6, biseriate, filaments c. 1 mm, anthers 1.3-1.5 x 0.6 mm, parallel and dorsifixed; pistillode c. 1 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.9-1.4 x 0.6-1.5 mm; petals 1.5-2.1 x 1.6-2.4 mm; staminodes 6, 0.3-0.5 mm. FRUIT red, ellipsoid with a rounded apex, c. 9 x 5 mm. SEED 6.5-7 x 3.5 mm, obtuse at both ends, with homogeneous endosperm.  
NOTE: This species seems closest to D. confusa, but is distinct in the long rachillae.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Manongarivo, Masoala and Mananara Avaratra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland to submontane rain forest; ridgetop or flat slope; 240-600 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Rare, possibly vulnerable. Numbers are probably less than a few hundred.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Stems used to make blowpipes in Manongarivo.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Ambanja: Ambalafary, Feb. 1992 (fr.), Beentje et al. 4578 (BH, K, MO, P, TAN); Amtsahakolany Valley, June 1923 (fl.), Decary 2139 (K, P). Maroantsetra: Hiaraka, Oct. 1986 (bud), Dransfield et al. JD6378 (K, TAN); Ambanizana, Oct. 1986 (y. fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6398 (Holotype K; isotype TAN). Mananara   Avaratra: Antanambe, Oct. 1994 (bud), Dransfield &amp; Beentje JD7508 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>