<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops lewisiana</name>
<author>(Griff.) Mart.</author>
<citation>Hist. Nat. Palm 3 (1850) 327</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 465</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12 (1911) 77</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mal. Pen. 5 (1925) 38</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 78</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops pseudosepal</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc. in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 465</bibref>
<bibref>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12 (1911) 79</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley Fl. Mai. Pen. 5 (1925) 40</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 87</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Daemonorops tabacina</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc. in Hook, f., FL Br. India 6 (1893) 446</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12 (1911) 93</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 14 (1953) 94</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>T. Lewis - administrator in Malacca during the time of W. Griffith</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>lumpit kecil</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering thicket-forming, very short-stemmed apparently hapaxanthic palm, with stems rarely more than 2 m tall, &#177; stemless in vegetative state. Rosette leaves ecirrate to about 4 m long with petiole to 2.2 m; sheaths pale greeny brown armed with scattered black spines to 3 cm long and chocolate-coloured indumentum; knee absent in rosette leaves. Leaflets about 80 on each side of the rachis, regular, rather narrow, the largest to about 45 cm long by 1.5 cm wide, sparsely armed with bristles on the 3 nerves above, along the margins, and on the main nerve beneath. Sheaths of flowering stem with slight knee, armed as other sheaths. Upper leaves short, rarely more than 40 cm long including a cirrus to 15 cm and petiole to 10 cm; leaflets about 15-20 on each side. Inflorescences decreasing in size from below upwards, the lower inflorescences about 15cm long by 7 cm wide, the uppermost to 5 cm long by 1.5 cm wide; beak varying from about 2-7 cm long. Outermost bract enclosing all the others, with black spines to 3 cm long by 3 mm wide in lower inflorescences, in upper inflorescences almost unarmed; bract often densely chocolate-coloured indumentose. Ripe fruit rounded or somewhat oblong about 2 cm in diameter covered in 15-16 vertical rows of scales, bright green, later turning yellowish brown to cinnamon brown, variously with pale or dark margins. Seed rounded about 1.2 cm in diameter. Endosperm deeply ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Kedah, Penang, Perak, Johore, Singapore. Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This very short-stemmed species approaches D. calicarpa but the inflorescences are not nearly so crowded, and have quite different armature. The great decrease in size of inflorescences from below upwards is highly suggestive of hapaxanthy. In Penang this species is found on ridgetops and steep slopes from near sea level to about 700 m alt.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>