<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus nagbettai</name>
<author>Fernandez &amp; Dey</author>
<citation>Indian Forester 96: 223. 1970</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Nag betta, Nag bet, Nag betha.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A robust climber; stem cluster forming, without leafsheath to 3 cm in diameter, smooth, often marked with distinct black blotches near about the base. Leaves curate, with cirrus about 5 m long; cirrus 2.5 m long, armed with 7-8 pointed claws; leafsheath often scurfy outside, armed with 2 - 3 cm long black, flattened, subulate, reflexed spines, intermingled with short bristles; petiole armed with laterally confluent, flat, subulate spines; rachis armed on dorsal side with greyish black hooks and upwardly bent marginal spines; leaflets numerous, ensiform, opposite to sub-opposite or alternate, to 30 cm long, 1.5- 1.7cm broad at middle, filiform at spices, spinulose at margins, prominently 1-nerved at middle, armed on both sides with bulbous based deep brown bristles. Inflorescence non-flagelliform; primary bract armed with reflexed to recurved spines and small claws. Fruits ovoid, oblong, 11-15 mm x 9 mm; fruit scales wedge shaped, in 17 -18 series, channelled at middle, hyaline, lacerated along brown band; seed oblong, piano convex, 9x6 mm, rugose on convex side; endosperm shallowly ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (Karnataka). Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Infrequent in the moist forest of Kodagu District at 450 m.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Experimental cultivation exists in the Kodagu forest range.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane is strong and durable and used by the local people for making baskets.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Karnataka : South Kanara, Coorg, 10.2.1966 Dey 64 (DD); Mangalore, May, 1967, Fernandez 4579 A (DD).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>