<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans of the Western Ghats. A Taxonomic Manual.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Renuka</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kerala Forest Research Institute</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus prasinus</name>
<author>Lakshmana &amp; Renuka</author>
<citation>J. Econ. Tax. Bot. 14:719</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Kannada: Ontibetha</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary, high climbing canes. Stems with sheaths to 3 cm in diameter, without sheaths to 1.2 cm. Sheath pale green, densely armed with spines to 1 cm long-, knee conspicuous. Leaf ecirrate, to 2.5 m long including the petiole; petiole to 30 cm long, biconvex, armed with small prickles, underneath with recurved spines; rachis triangular, underneath with recurved spines, petiole and rachis when cut exudes milky latex; leaflets ca 50 x 2.5 cm, terminal pair united basally, shiny green, underneath with shallow linear pits when fresh, 3- veined, veins ciliate on the upper half, lateral veins ciliate above, midvein ciliate beneath, cilia upto 1 cm long. Inflorescence long, pendulous; primary sheath tightly sheathing, two-keeled, tip lacerate, spiny; partial inflorescence to 18 cm long; secondary sheath unarmed , tubular, tightly sheathing; rachillae to 5 cm long, arched and recurved, arising from just above the mouth of the sheath; involucrophorum stalked, to 3 mm long, attached above the mouth of the sheath; involucre disc shaped. Fruit globose. Scales in 26 rows, deeply channeled along the middle, yellow, shiny, bright green when young. Endosperm ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Evergreen forests at about 530 m. Mangalore Forest Division and Sampaje (Fig. 5).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Flowering November-December. Fruiting May-June.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>A good quality cane, used in furniture industry.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Sampaje, 20.5.88, fr, Renuka 4082 (KFRI); Magunde, 17.3.89, fr.,Renuka 4092 (KFRI).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>