<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Synopsis of the Rattans (Arecaceae: Calamoideae) of Laos and Neighbouring Parts of Indochina</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Evans</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">T.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Sengdala</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">K.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Thammavong</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">B.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Viengkham</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">O.V.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2002</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 57, No. 1 (2002), pp. 1-84</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus poilanei</name>
<author>Conrard</author>
<citation> Notul. Syst. (Paris) 7: 28 (1938)</citation>
<type>Vietnam, South Annam; Poilane; 23754</type>
<type_loc>Lectotype P; isotype K</type_loc>
<bibref>Evans et al., Rattans Lao PDR: 32 (2001)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="distribution"><p>Indochinese endemic, Thailand (North and North-east), Laos (Central and North) and Vietnam (South Annam and probably North Annam).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>THAILAND (NORTH): Phrae, undated, (pist.), Vongkaluang, I. 370 (K, VONG); (NORTH-EAST): Petchaboon, undated, (ster.), Vongkaluang, I. 271 (K, VONG). LAOS (NORTH): Oudomxay Province, La Distr., Phou Pud, 6 March 1998, (ster.), Bounyong BY 127 (FRCL, K). (CENTRAL): Xaysomboun Special Zone, Phoune Distr., Phu Sair, 25 April 1998, (fr.), Khamphone KP 143 (FRCL, K). VIETNAM (NORTH ANNAM): [Ha Tinh Province, Huong Son Distr., Nga Doi, 19 May 1998, (ster.), Hiep, N. T et al. 738 (MO, K)]. (SOUTH ANNAM): Nhatrang, Dong Bo Massif, undated, (fr.), Poilane 2715 (P); Nhatrang, La Mere et l'Enfant, 4 Nov. 1922, (fr.), Poilane 5025 (BM, P); Col de Braian, undated, (pist.), Poilane 23754 (K, P).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Evergreen forest. In Laos at 300 - 1300 m, in Thailand at 600 - 700 and in South Annam at 500 m.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Care needs to be taken in distinguishing infertile material from the superficially similar (but cirrate) C. ceratophorus.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>wai thoon (Lao Loum), blong thoon (Khamu), gaparl (Phong), wai kruh (Thailand), probably also wai khom (Lao Loum), blong chang (Khamu), wai nampung (Thailand).</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Calamus poilanei is the most economically important rattan in Laos, dominating the export trade in raw cane and being the preferred species used by Lao artisans for the frames of furniture. The shoot is also edible. There are plantations of unknown extent in Vietnam (Nguyen Truong Thanh &amp; Ngo Thi Min Duyen 1997).</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Of high conservation concern. Listed as Threatened- Rare in Vietnam (Phan Thuc Vat 1996). Although relatively widespread within Indochina, high harvesting pressure has already caused the collapse of many populations (e.g. in Laos, pers. obs.) and declines are undoubtedly continuing. Stem harvesting is the main threat, but shoot harvesting may threaten some remnant populations. The solitary habit hinders regeneration and harvests have been so thorough in many areas that very few mature fruiting stems remain.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>

