<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis hovomantsina</name>
<author>Beentje </author>
<citation>in J.Dransfield &amp; H.Beentje, Palms of Madagascar: 149 (1995)</citation>
<type>Madagascar, Antalavia; Dransfield et al.; JD6744</type>
<type_loc>Holotypus K; isotypi P, TAN</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>An impressive tree; we found a second site only three months before the book went to press. The leaf-sheaths are distinct from any other, with their lower parts white-waxy and a golden-brown furry part at the very top. The name comes directly from the local name, which means stinking and refers to the smelly palm-heart.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Hovomantsina (Betsimisaraka; 'mantsina' means stinking)</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>inter species maximas foliolis aggregatis vagina folii versus basim glabra ceracea apice brunneo-tomentosa staminibus 6 endospermio homogeneo distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary palm. TRUNK 6-15 m tall, 20-30 cm, diam., near the crown 15-20 cm diam.; internodes 10-35 cm, pale to reddish-brown basally, grey-green distally, nodal scars 1-1.5 cm, pale brown; crownshaft well-developed, 1-1.2 m, c. 25 cm diam., grey-green and covered in white wax except distally, where red-brown furry. LEAVES spirally inserted, occasionally tristichous, 6-7 in the crown, curved, with an untidy look, the leaflets held in all directions; sheath pale green to whitish, proximally waxy and glabrous, with distal dense soft pale reddish brown persistent tomentum, adaxially peachcoloured; petiole 10-56 cm, 7 x 5.5 cm diam., channelled with sharp edges, with dense red-brown indument; rachis 3-3.5 m long, in mid-leaf 3.5 cm wide, with keel; leaflets 80-96 on each side of the    rachis, grouped and fanned in 3s-6s, the group interval 3-7 cm, bent downwards at two-thirds of their length, the proximal 120-242 x 0.7- 2.4 cm, median 123-135 x 3.3-4 cm, distal 22-50 x 0.6-2 cm, connate for 1.5-4 cm, with a few large laciniate ramenta, without scattered scales. INFLORESCENCE infrafoliar, c. 0.5-1 x 0.5-1 m, branched to 2-3 orders; peduncle 18-26 cm, diam. 7 x 3 cm; prophyll 21-30 cm, borne at 3-4 cm above the base of the peduncle; peduncular bract deciduous, inserted at 9-11 cm from the base of the peduncle, 45-66 x 10-12 cm, not beaked or briefly beaked with triangular beak, split for 90%; non-tubular peduncular bract occasionally present on upper peduncle, to 20 cm; rachis 48 cm, with 14 branched and 10 unbranched first order branches; rachillae stiff or sub-pendulous, green to yellow-green, 16-40 cm long, 4-8 mm diam., glabrous, with dense flowers. STAMINATE FLOWERS only known in rather young bud, with sepals 2.1-3 x 2.5-2.8 mm, very hooded; petals &#60; 1.5 mm; stamens 6, &#60; 1.3 mm, probably versatile. PISTILLATE FLOWERS only known from the young fruit stage, with sepals 2.7-3.1 x 3-3.3 mm; petals 3.5-3.8 x 3-4 mm; staminodes 6, flat, tooth-shaped, 0.5 mm. FRUIT not known, except for the fibrous endocarp. SEED obovoid with pointed base, 9-10 x 7-8 mm, with homogeneous endosperm. EOPHYLL entire, deeply bifid.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from Maroantsetra and Mananara.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Rain forest, steep slopes either near valley bottom or near ridge crest; 50-300 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Critical. Only known from two sites, both of which are under pressure from agricul- ture; populations consist of few individuals.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Palm-heart smelly but still eaten; no other uses.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Possibly closest to D. tokoravina, but with a totally different leaf sheath.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Maroantsetra: Antalavia, Feb. 1988 (y.fr.), Dransfield et al. JD6473 (K, P, TAN); idem, Nov. 1989 (bud), Dransfield et al. JD6744 (Holotype K; isotypes P, TAN). Mananara Avaratra: Antanambe, Oct. 1994 (fl., fr.), Beentje &amp; Dransfield 4819 (K, TAN); idem, Oct. 1994 (bud), Beentje &amp; Dransfield 4827 (K, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>