<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus ulur</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1913),  Supplement 133</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>ulur - probably from the Malay ular, a snake</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering rattan climbing to 10 m tall. Stem without sheaths to 1 cm in diameter, with sheaths to 2.5 cm in diameter. Internodes to 20 cm. Sheaths dull green armed with scattered triangular concave hairy-edged spines 3 by 2 mm to 18 by 7 mm and abundant sinuous lateral rough ridges to 0.2 mm high; grey indumentum abundant between the spines. Knee conspicuous armed as the leaf sheath. Vestigial flagellum to 15 cm long present on most sheaths. Ocrea inconspicuous. Leaf cirrate to 1.75 m long including the cirrus to 1 m long; petiole short, not usually more than 5 cm long; cirrus armed with scattered rather than distinctly grouped reflexed spines. Leaflets about 25 on each side of the rachis, grouped in 5 groups of up to 8 leaflets but arranged regularly within each group, the leaflets to 35 cm long by 2.5 cm wide, plicate &#177; unarmed above rather densely armed with short black bristles on 5-6 nerves. Inflorescence male and female superficially similar, to 1 m long with 3-4 partial inflorescences, in the female to 15 cm long, in the male to 60 cm long; all bracts loosely tubular and tattering, giving the inflorescence a dead appearance. Male rachillae enclosed within bracts about 1.5 cm long, female rachillae recurved to about 5 cm long. Young fruit with scales in 23 vertical rows. No other parts known.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Johore: Panti East Forest Reserve. Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Calamus ulur is a common rattan in the swamp forests at the foot of G. Panti in Johore, where it forms large clumps. It has been found nowhere else in Malaya. The type was collected in Sumatra. It belongs to the same peculiar group of Calamus as C. endauensis in which a vestigial flagellum occurs and the inflorescences are covered in tattering bracts. C. endauensis differs in not having the characteristic minute ridges on the sheaths, in different leaflets structure and arrangement and in smaller laxer male inflorescence.
 This is the first record of C. ulur for Malaya. The group of C. ulur is in need of careful revision, but the G. Panti plant seems very close to the type from S. Sumatra and has hence been assumed to be conspecific.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>