<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Synopsis of the Rattans (Arecaceae: Calamoideae) of Laos and Neighbouring Parts of Indochina</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Evans</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">T.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Sengdala</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">K.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Thammavong</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">B.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Viengkham</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">O.V.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2002</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 57, No. 1 (2002), pp. 1-84</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus rudentum</name>
<author>Lour.</author>
<citation>Fl. Cochinch. (1" ed): 209 (1790)</citation>
<bibref>Lour., (2'd1 or Willd. ed): 260 (1793)</bibref>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. (Calcutta) 11 (1): 139 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Gagnep. &amp; Conrard in Gagnep. (ed.), Fl. Indo-Chine 6: 1025 (1937)</bibref>
<bibref>Sounthone &amp; Sengkhamyong in Rao &amp; Rao (1997: 82);</bibref>
<bibref>Evans et al., Rattans Lao PDR: 56 (2001).</bibref>
<type>Vietnam, lower Cochinchina, Dian-lau-me; Pierre; 4846</type>
<type_loc>Neotype P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="distribution"><p>Thailand (all except North-east and West), Laos (Central and probably South) and Vietnam (Cochinchina). Probably also Cambodia (Gagnepain &amp; Conrard 1937) and possibly also in northern Peninsular Thailand (Saw, L. G. pers. comm. 2000).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>THAILAND (NORTH): Nakawn Sawawn, Me Wong, 25 May 1922, (stam. &amp; fr.), Kerr A. 6016 (K, BK). (CENTRAL): Nakorn Nayok Province, Muang Distr., Nahng Rawng Falls, 16 Sept. 1972, (fr.), Maxwell, J. E 72 - 386 (BK). (EAST): Pakchong, 2Jan. 1924, (fr.), Marcan, A. 1594 (K, BM). (SOUTH- EAST): Chonburi Province, Siricha Distr., Kow Khieo, 5 Jan. 1975, (fr.), Maxwell, J. E 75 - 1 (BK). (PENINSULAR): Trang, undated, (fr.), Vongkaluang, 1. 340, (K). LAOS (CENTRAI,): Vientiane Municipality, Hadxaiphong Distr., Ban Nongpen-Nua, April 1997, (fr.), Renuka RE 104 (FRCL, K). (SOUTH): [Attapeu Province, Sanamxay Distr., Dongbark, 8 April 1992, (ster.), Sounthone ST 12 (FRCL, K)]. VIETNAM (COCHINCHINA): Vung Tau Province, Con Dao, 17June 1989, (fr.), Averyanov, L. &amp; Kudryavtzena, E. 508 (LE, K); lower Cochinchina, Dian-lau-me, undated, (fr.) Pierre 4846 (P).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>In Laos recorded in scrub at 200 m, and probably also in lowland evergreen forest. In Thailand in evergreen forest at 100 - 400 m.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>We follow Merrill (1935), Gagnepain &amp; Conrard (1937) and other authors in accepting Beccari's interpretation of Loureiro's sketchy protologue. Sterile material of this species is difficult to separate with any confidence from Calamus flagellum. The vegetative differences noted in the key are often hard to detect on herbarium material. The much more robust rachillae, larger fruit and ruminate endosperm of C. flagellum allow confident identification when available. Our current, limited knowledge suggests that they differ greatly in altitudinal preferences in Indochina but identification cannot be based upon this fact alone. Magalon (1930) reports that this species is found almost throughout Vietnam up to 1000 m. Unfortunately aspects of the description (e.g. the leaflets in groups of 3 - 6 and male rachillae 1.5 - 1.8 cm long) suggest that he is referring to another species. He may be referring to C. rhabdocladus but the cane diameter of up to 50 mm and the petiole armed only on the underside do not really fit. One of Magalon's specimens in P (Magalon 13 undated, from Bana near Danang) is named C. rudentum but is actually a Plectocomia, perhaps P pierreana. Since his description does not fit P pierreana either (sheath spines numerous, black, flexible, laminar, 2 - 8 x 50 mm, no mention of the expanded secondary bracts of Plectocomia) it is best to regard the whole account as an amalgam of more than one species</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>wai boun, boun, (Lao Loum), wai pong (Thailand), probably also wai tabong, boun dam, boun khao (Lao Loum).</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane is of high quality and suitable for trade. The shoot is edible and the fruits are sometime sold as food. There are reportedly plantations for cane production in Vietnam (Nguyen Truong Thanh &amp; Ngo Thi Min Duyen 1997).</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Unknown. Reportedly a preferred species for trade in Vietnam, so harvesting pressures may be high.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>

