<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Dransfieldia (Arecaceae)—A New Palm Genus from Western New Guinea</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Baker</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">W.J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Zona</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Heatubun</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">Ch.D.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">K.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">K.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Maturbongs</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">R.A.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Norup</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.V.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Systematic Botany, 31(1): pp. 61–69</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2006</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dransfieldia micrantha</name>
<author>(Becc.) W. J. Baker &amp; Zona,</author>
<citation>Syst. Bot. 31: 62 (2006)</citation>
<type>Indonesia, Papua, Sorong Regency, Ramoi, Jun 1872; Beccari; 424</type>
<type_loc>Holotype FI! sheets 11191 and 11191A–G; isotype K! fragment </type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Ptychosperma micranthum</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Malesia 1: 52. 1877.</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Rhopaloblaste micrantha</name>
<author>(Becc.) Hook. f. ex B. D. Jacks.</author>
<bibref>(Becc.) Hook. f. ex B. D. Jacks., Index Kew. 2: 713. 1895 (non Rhopaloblaste micrantha Burret, Notizbl. Bot. Gart. Berlin-Dahlem 15: 10. 1940, nom. illeg.).</bibref>
</synonymy>
<synonymy>
<name>Heterospathe micrantha</name>
<author>(Becc.) H. E. Moore</author>
<bibref>(Becc.) H. E. Moore, Principes 14: 92. 1970</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>Dransfieldia is named for Dr. John Dransfield, former Head of Palm Research at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, and friend and mentor to all authors of this paper, in recognition of his monumental contributions both to Malesian palm systematics and to global knowledge of palm biology as a whole.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Ititohoho (Jamur), Kapis (Biak-Raja Ampat), Tama’e (Wondama).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering or rarely solitary, slender understory tree palm. Stem to 10 m in height, 2–5 cm diam., surface smooth, often reddish when young then turning brown, internodes 4.0–19.5 cm. Leaves 4–7 in crown, new leaves emerging reddish but soon turning green, 1–2 m long including petiole; sheath 30–45 cm long, crownshaft 50–60 x ca. 6 cm, green with white bloom, sometimes orange-red near the apex and extending into the abaxial side of the petiole, dark scales especially abundant at sheath mouth; petiole 10–20 cm long, 12–14 x ca. 11 mm at base; leaflets 12–27 on each side of rachis, borne 55–69 mm apart, concolorous, ramenta ca. 5 mm long; mid-leaf leaflet 52–76 x 2–5 cm; apical leaflets 18.0–36.0 x 0.8–1.7 cm. Inflorescence 34–60 cm long including peduncle and rachis, all axes red to purple at anthesis; peduncle 12–26 cm long, 9–13 x 5–8 mm at base; prophyll 11.5–27.0 x 1.4–2.0 cm, brown at anthesis; peduncular bracts 2–3, first peduncular bract 20.0–24.0 x 1.7–3.5 cm, remaining peduncular bracts 0.5–25.0 x 5.0–12.0 mm; rachis 9–17 cm long; primary branches 11–14, to 35 cm, with up to 7 rachillae each; rachillae 8.5–29.0 cm long, 1.5–3.5 mm diam. at anthesis, irregularly curvaceous, triads 15–28 per 5 cm; floral bracteoles spathulate, to 1 mm long. Staminate flowers 4.5–5.5 x 2.2–3.4 mm in bud near anthesis, purple; sepals 1.8–2.1 x 1.7–2.6 mm; corolla united in basalmost 0.5–1.4 mm, corolla lobes 4.2–4.8 x 1.7–2.5 mm; stamens 15–19, white, filaments 1.5–3.1 x 0.1–0.2 mm, anther 1.0–1.3 x 0.3–0.7 mm; pollen grains 30–40 mm long; pistillode less than 0.5 mm long. Pistillate flowers 3.8–4.3 x 3.3–3.9 mm in bud near to anthesis, purple; sepals 2.5–3.5 x 2.3–3.0 mm; petals 3.1–3.5 x 2–2.5 mm; staminodes ca. 3, 0.3–0.5 mm; gynoecium ca. 3.0 x 1.6 mm including stigmas ca. 0.7 mm. Fruit 15.0–15.9 x 7.6–9.5 mm; epicarp black when ripe, epicarp and mesocarp 0.7 mm thick, endocarp 0.3 mm thick, brown. Seed 8.9–11.0 x 6.1–7.0 mm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Restricted to far western Papua province in Indonesian New Guinea. Known from Waigeo Island in the Raja Ampat Archipelago, the Kepala Burung (Sorong and Bintuni Bay), the lower slopes of the Wondiwoi Mountains and the vicinity of Etna Bay. Although records are relatively few, a consequence of low collection densities, we have no reason to believe that the species is not more widespread between these localities. Palm growers have reported that the species occurs in Papua New Guinea (Migliaccio 2001). We have seen no confirmation of this and suspect that a misinterpretation of the origin of the seed source has been made.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland forests and forest on slopes and ridge tops, 10–180 m elevation.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Near Threatened. Dransfieldia micrantha meets criterion B1 for threat category ‘‘Vulnerable’’ because its extent of occurrence is less than 20,000 km2, but it does not qualify for the requisite two out of three subsequent criteria B1a–c (IUCN 2001). However, the impact of widespread logging, both legal and illegal, suggests that D. micrantha will potentially meet the requirements of criteria B1a and B1b in the near future.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Stems used for harpoons. Leaves used for thatch. Unspecified parts used for sewing thatch. The species is grown as an ornamental in the USA and Australia, but is not yet widely available in the horticultural trade. Its colorful new leaves and inflorescences, along with its slender habit, make this palm highly desirable among palm collectors (Migliaccio 2001).</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Rhopaloblaste micrantha Burret (1940) is a later homonym of Rhopaloblaste micrantha (Becc.) Hook. f. ex B. D. Jacks. Moore (1970) recognised this and accordingly published a nomen novum, R. dyscrita H. E. Moore. This name is now placed in synonymy with R. ceramica (Miq.) Burret (Banka and Baker 2004).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>INDONESIA, PAPUA. Sorong Regency:Ramoi, Jun 1872, Beccari 424 (holotype FI!, isotype fragment K!); Raja Ampat Islands, Waigeo Island, Mamiai area near Yesner Village, 25 Jun 1997, Heatubun 97 (K!, MAN); Warsamson, NE of Sorong town, 28 Jan 2002, Maturbongs et al. 702 (BO, K!, LAE). Manokwari Regency: Wasior District, Sikama River, 3 km SE of Wosimi River at Senderawoi, 26 km SSE of Wasior (S 2˚57' 2.7", E 134˚ 34' 22.5"), 26 Feb 2000, Baker et al. 1066 (BO!, FTG!, K!, L!, MAN!); same locality and date, Heatubun et al. 321 (AAU!, BO!, FTG!, K!, MAN!); same locality, 27 Feb 2000, Baker et al. 1067 (BO!, FTG!, K!, L!, MAN!); near British Petroleum’s Saengga Camp, 14 Feb 2002, Maturbongs &amp; Siwana 718 (BO, K!). Fak-Fak Regency: Etna Bay, Waribun, km 28 on P. T. Kaltim Hutama road, 31 Jan 2002, Heatubun et al. 328 (FTG!, K!, MAN)</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>