<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops ruptilis var. acaulescens</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 81: 23 (1980)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 82 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 85 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Stemless</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Tulang (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Stemless clustering rattan with short decumbent subterranean stem to c. 40 mm diam. without sheaths, with sheaths to 60 mm diam., internodes very short. Leaf ecirrate, to 3.5 m long including the petiole and sheath; sheath to 40 cm long, without knee, armed with oblique whorls of flattened pale brown spines to 30 &#215; 4 mm, and densely armed with reddish-brown indumentum; petiole to 1 m, armed with scattered or partially whorled spines to 4 cm; leaflets c. 40 on each side of the rachis, regularly arranged, to 60 &#215; 3 cm, &#177; unarmed except for a few marginal bristles and a few bristles on the lower surface of the mid vein. Inflorescences up to c. 1 m long, with up to 5 partial inflorescences, the male with crowded rachillae, the female with lax &#177; divaricating rachillae; peduncle to 60 cm or more; primary bracts dull brown, quickly falling; secondary and tertiary bracts all conspicuous, persistent, irregularly splitting; male rachillae to 8 cm, bearing crowded, strictly distichous flowers; female rachillae to 15 cm with rather more distant flowers. Mature fruit rounded to short cylindrical, to 14 &#215; 12 mm, tipped by a beak to 5 &#215; 2 mm, and covered with 15 vertical rows of pale brown scales. Seed 11 &#215; 7 mm; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 30).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>In Brunei widespread in Belait district. Elsewhere known only from 4th Division, Sarawak and parts of Sabah.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The fruit and habit of this variety are consistently different from those of the type variety. D. ruptilis var. acaulescens is a plant of ridges in lowland dipterocarp forest at altitudes up to c. 350 m above sea level.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Labi, Bt.Telingan, Dransfield J. 6829; Sungai Liang, Andulau F.R, Wong 494.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>