<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name><mods:namePart>Dransfield, J.</mods:namePart></mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Ceratolobus kingianus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>in Hook, f., Fl. Br. India 6 (1893) 477</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12 (2) (1918) 9</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mal. Pen. 5 (1925) 46</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 13 (1951) 352</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>After Sir George King</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan jere landak</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering rattan with stems 5-8 m long to 15 mm in diameter with sheaths, 8 mm in diameter without sheaths; internodes to 20 cm long. Leaf sheaths densely covered with greyish-white powder and partial-whorls of minute spicules to 2 mm long, easily detached to leave fine ridges; ocrea inconspicuous. Leaf to 1.5 m including cirrus; petiole 12-20 cm long; cirrus 30-55 cm long. Leaflets 4-6 on each side, the lowermost larger than the rest, fish-tailed, to 25 cm long by 11 cm wide, usually smaller, finely folded, dark green above, sparsely powdery white below. Inflorescence sessile, erect; bract 21-31 cm long by A-6.5 cm wide. Fruit rounded, about 1.5 cm in diameter. Seed slightly depressed laterally; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Perak, Trengganu, Pahang. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane no market value, no local use, though apparently durable (according to "Orang Jakun").</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Apparently a rare rattan, collected only 7 times; each time from lowland localities. Ecological preferences not completely known; inland from Kuala Rompin, Pahang, growing in seasonally flooded freshwater swamp forest. When sterile, C. kingianus might be confused with Korthalsia spp. or species of Calamus with rhomboid leaflets (Calamus tomentosus and C. blumei). These Calami however all have flagella rather than cirri and the upper leaf margins are smooth and not jagged. Korthalsia spp. all have well-developed conspicuous ocreas and never have leaf sheath knees; furthermore only one species of Korthalsia (K. hispida) bears spicules and it bears very conspicuous ocreas, and no known Korthalsia has pinkish young leaves.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>