<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus tomentosus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>in Hook, f., Fl. Brit. Ind. 6 (1893) 455</citation> 
<bibref>Beccari, in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1908) 338 and Supplement (1913) 61</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mai. Pen. 5 (1925) 52</bibref>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 75 (1956) 71</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Tomentosus - densely covered in small hairs</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan tukas</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering rattan climbing to 20 m tall. Stem without sheaths to 1 cm in diameter, with sheaths to 2.5 cm, with internodes to 35 cm long. Sheaths with scattered rounded swellings each tipped with black upward pointing spine to 2 mm long, densely covered throughout with silvery flocculent indumentum drying yellowish, and caducous chocolate-coloured scales. Knee prominent. Ocrea to 1 cm high indumentose as the sheath. Flagellum to 1 m long. Leaf ecirrate or with a minute (1 cm long) cirrus vestige. Petiole to about 30 cm long. Leaflets 5 on each side of the rachis in mature leaves, diamond-shaped to 35 cm long by 18 cm wide, with no obvious stalk &#177; unarmed except for short bristles near the tip, with 7-9 major nerves; whole leaflet drying dirty yellowish green-brown. Inflorescence, male and female superficially similar, to 80 cm long with up to 5 partial inflorescences the largest to 35 cm long; male rachillae about 3 cm long; female to 8 cm long. &#177; mature fruit rounded to slightly oblong about 2.5 cm long 2.2 cm wide, shortly beaked, covered in 18 vertical rows of mid-brown scales. Seed ovate, about 1.8 cm long by 1.3 cm wide. Endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling leaf bifid with 2 broad diamond-shaped leaflets.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Perak, Trengganu, Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane has a good appearance but it is probably too rare to be of any significance. Calamus tomentosus is a rare rattan found on steep slopes in hill forest up to about 800 m altitude.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>It may be distinguished from the other rhomboid leafleted Calamus blumei by the yellowish colour of the sheaths on drying, the sessile leaflets with 7-9 ribs and the yellowish-brown tinge to the dried leaves.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>