<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Sarawak</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department Sarawak, Malaysia and Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Daemonorops draco</name>
<author>(Willd.) Bl.</author>
<citation>Rumphia 3: 8 (1849)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 12(1): 105 (1911)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus draco</name>
<author>Willd.</author>
<bibref>Willd., Sp. Pl. 2: 203 (1799)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>A dragon</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>wiondo (Selak.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering rattan climbing to 15 m tall; stem without sheaths c. 15 mm diam., with sheaths to 30 mm diam., internodes c. 15 cm long. Sheath bright green, bearing chocolate-coloured indumentum when young, armed with rather irregular short partial whorls of black spines andspinules, to 20 mm long, usually much less; knee well developed, armed with scattered black spines; ocrea absent. Leaf cirrate, to 2.5 m long including the petiole to 30 cm and cirrus to 1 m long; petiole armed laterally with groups of short spines to 6 mm long; leaflets c. 20 on each side of the rachis, &#177; regularly arranged, rather distant, linear-lanceolate, long acuminate, the longest to 40 x 2.5 cm, armed with long bristles on the main vein and 2 laterals on the undersurface; transverse veinlets minute but easily visible. Inflorescences pendulous, much shorter than the leaves, c. 45 cm long with c. 3 partial inflorescences; bracts rather thick and woody, falling at anthesis; rachillae very short. Mature fruit (not known in Sarawak) &#177; ovoid, 28 x 20 mm, covered in 16 vertical rows of scales, heavily encrusted with dragon's blood. Seed &#177; rounded; endosperm deeply ruminate. Seedling not known (Fig. 17).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known in Sarawak from a single collection from Pueh Forest Reserve, 1st Division. Elsewhere known (in the sense of Beccari's interpretation) from a few collections from S  Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane appears to be of good quality.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>D. draco was collected in Sarawak in a valley bottom in lowland dipterocarp forest at 50 m altitude. This specific name has been applied in several senses; Beccari's interpretation (Beccari 1911) is followed here. D. draco approaches D. micracantha but the leaf sheath spines are more robust and the leaflets fewer and larger; the inflorescence bracts of D. draco are also very much thicker than those of D. micracantha.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>