<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Plectocomia elongata var. elongata</name>
<author>Mart. ex Bl.</author>
<citation>in J. A. &amp; J. H. Schultes, Syst. Veg. 7: 1333 (1830)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 23 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Madulid, Kalikasan 10: 45 (1981)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 36 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 218 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Plectocomia griffithii</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc.in Hooker f., Fl. Br. India 6: 478 (1893)</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 12(2): 27 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 55 (1979)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Elongate</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Robust, solitary rattan climbing to 50 m; stem without sheaths to 6 cm diam. near the base, to 10 cm or more in upper parts, with sheaths to 20 cm diam., internodes to 30 cm long; lower parts of old stems frequently with bulbil-like shoots from the nodes. Sheaths dull green armed with horizontal or oblique combs of golden brown or deep reddish-brown spines to 4 cm long, and abundant white or buff-coloured indumentum; knee absent. Leaf very large, to 7 m long including the cirrus to 3 m and petiole to c. 30 cm; leaflets to c. 60 on each side of the rachis, arranged irregularly in 2s-7s and fanned within the groups. bluish green on the upper surface, whitish beneath. Inflorescences produced from the top 7-10 nodes, to c. 80 cm long and bearing c. 12 crowded pendulous branches to c. 1 m; bracts chestnut brown, c. 7 &#215; 5 cm, with triangular tips but scarcely truncate. Male flowers up to c. 20 within each bract; female flowers 3-9 within each bract, &#177; completely concealed. Mature fruit about 8 within each bract (if fewer, then fruit larger), very crowded, c. 1.5 cm diam., with reflexed stigmas and covered in c. 50 vertical rows of fimbriate-margined reddish-brown scales. Seed c. 1 cm diam. Seedling leaf lanceolate, undivided. (Fig. 83).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known only from Bt. Retak. Elsewhere rare on Kinabalu and G. Mulu, abundant in Peninsular Malaysia, Sumatra and Java; a variety known in Palawan.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>See under genus.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This is an imperfectly known species in Borneo. Large plants of P. mulleri from sites on good soil may appear very similar. Apart from the extreme poor soil form of P. mulleri, the two taxa can only be told apart with certainty if fertile material is available.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>TEM: Amo, Bt.Retak, Wong 450.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>