<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus pseudofeanus</name>
<author>S.K.Basu</author>
<citation>Journ. Econ. Tax. Bot. 13(1)133. 1989</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A slender climber; stem without leafsheath smooth, light yellow in colour, 2 -4 cm in diameter near base; internodes smooth, to 20 cm long. Leaves ecirrate; leafsheath with flagellum; rachis slender, bifaced, upper margins of rachis infrequently armed with 2 mm long broad-based hooks; under surface armed with scattered, broad-based 1 mm long spines; leaflets alternate to subopposite; inequidistant, lower leaflets oblanceolate, to 30 cm long, 5 cm broad at widest part, wedge-shaped at base, apiculate at apices, prominently 5-nerved, nerves slightly bristly on upper side, spinulous at margins; middle leaflets elliptic to broadly lanceolate, to 20 cm long, 6 cm broad at middle, narrowly cuneate at base; upper leaflets sometimes 2-3 lobed at distal part; terminal leaflets irregularly connate at base, sometimes one attached slightly above the other. Female inflorescence flagelliform; partial inflorescences twice branched; rachillae scorpioid, to 8 cm long, 16 - 20 in number, each attached about 1 cm above the mouth of the respective basal bracts; secondary bracts funnel shaped; involucrophorum not pedicelliform, with a neuter flower on one side; involucre disc-like. Fruit globose to sub-globose, 1.5 x 1 cm, abruptly beaked with 3- distinct stigmatic projections; fruiting perianth cup-like at base; fruit scales deep yellow, wedge-shaped with lip-like postichous part, distinctly channelled at middle; seed ovoid, 10x8 mm; endosperm ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (Tamil Nadu). Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>The original specimens were collected from moist forests of Coimbatore.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>The cane is strong and can be suitably utilised for making furniture. Intensive survey of this species is needed for assessing its cultivation prospects.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Tamil Nadu : South Coimbatore, 17.10.1905,DFO s.n.(13sheets in CAL and 10 sheets in MH).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>