<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>New Species of Calamus (Palmae) from Lao and Myanmar</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Henderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">A.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Henderson</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">F.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Taiwania 52(2): 152-158</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2007</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus meghalayensis</name>
<author>A.J.Hend.</author>
<citation>Taiwania 52: 155 (2007)</citation>
<type>INDIA. Meghalaya: Gari in the Garo Hills, no date; C. Clarke; s. n.</type>
<type_loc>Holotype FI-B n.v., holotype image in Beccari 1913</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus floribundus var. depauperatus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. (Calcutta) 11: 79. 1908.</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Risigin, tairu, rita (India).</p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Stems to 2 m long and 0.5-0.6 cm diameter (with leaf sheaths). Leaf sheaths green with brown tomentum, sparsely covered with brown, flattened, horizontally spreading spines to 1 cm long; knees present; ocreas present, less than 0.5 cm long, densely bristly; flagella present, to 2 m long; petioles 6-18 cm long, sparsely covered laterally and abaxially with recurved spines to 0.5 cm long; rachis 9-24 cm long, abaxially with few, recurved, solitary spines; pinnae 4-5 per side of rachis, lanceolate, arranged in distant groups or solitary, 13-23 cm long, 2-3.5 cm wide, minutely spiny along the margins, the apical pair free or briefly joined at their bases; cirri absent. Inflorescences to 1 m long, flagellate; partial inflorescences inserted above the mouth of the partial inflorescence bracts; partial inflorescence bracts closely sheathing the main axis, with recurved spines, bristly at the apex; staminate inflorescences branched to two orders, with up to 3 partial inflorescences; rachillae 0.5-1 cm long; rachillae bracts distichously arranged, to 1 mm long, more or less glabrous; floral bracteoles to 0.5 mm long; staminate flowers to 2 mm long, to 20 per rachilla, arranged alternately and distichously along the rachillae; calyx 1.5 mm long, tubular except for the 3-lobed apex; corolla 2 mm long, with 3 valvate petals free to the base; pistillode 1 mm long; pistillate inflorescences branched to two orders, with up to three partial inflorescences, each with up to 12 rachillae; rachillae 1-2.5 cm long; rachillae bracts distichously arranged, to 2.5 mm long, with brown hairs; pistillate flowers to 20 per rachilla, borne alternately and distichously along the rachillae; sepals to 3 mm long, connate basally for ca. two-thirds their length, lobed above; petals to 3 mm long, free; fruits not seen, according to Basu (1992) globose, to 1 cm diameter, yellowish.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Northeastern India (Meghalaya).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland forest at low elevations in the Khasi Hills.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>No uses recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Although the type specimen has not been seen, Beccari’s (1908) description and photograph (Beccari, 1913, plate 48) of C. Clarke s. n. shows it to be clearly distinct from C. floribundus, as suggested by Beccari himself (1908). Not only is it (and the specimens cited below) smaller in all dimensions, but the leaf sheath spines are quite different from those of C. floribundus. The name C. meghalayensis is given here because the eipthet depauperatus is preoccupied (Calamus depauperatus Ridl.)</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Additional specimens examined: INDIA. Meghalaya: Nenkra, Garo Hills, 6 Jan 1930, Parry 837a (K); Bamanigaon, in swamp, near sea level, 20 Nov 1949, Thakur Rup Chand 2493 (BH); Rani, 4 Feb 1952, W. Koelz 29229 (BH).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>