<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Novelties of the Genera Parajubaea and Syagrus (Palmae) from Interandean Valleys of Bolivia</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:namePart type="family">Moraes</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.</mods:namePart>
<role>
<roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
<roleTerm type="code">aut</roleTerm>
</role>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Novon 6: 85-92</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1996</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Parajubaea torallyi var. torallyi</name>
<author></author>
<citation></citation>
<type>Bolivia. Chuquisaca: Oropeza, Garcilaso, near town; A. d'Orbigny; 51</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p></p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p></p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The type collection consists only of endocarps that are smaller than those from Pasopaya stands. Alcides d'Orbigny gathered them from cultivated trees grown in Garcilaso, which lies in the north of the city of Sucre. These five trees still are alive and were estimated to be more than 300 years old. When Cárdenas (1970) described the palm forests of the Bolivian high Andes, he noted two different fruit sizes of the Bolivian endemic species of Parajubaea, P. torallyi. Moraes and Henderson (1990) reviewed the genus Parajubaea and concluded that different fruit sizes were probably due to variation within the wild species. Further fieldwork and new measurements were undertaken in Bolivia to determine if these were two species of Parajubaea or merely a variability within a single species. Moraes and Vargas (1994) preferred the two species hypothesis, with a distinct pattern of distribution for each. Finally, there are three distinct populations, each related to different valleys and ecosystems; they belong to three hydrographie systems that are separated by several mountain ranges and are influenced by distinctive climatic conditions. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>