<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus laevigatus Mart. var. laevigatus</name>
<author>Mart.</author>
<citation>Hist. Nat. Palm. 3: 339 (1853)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Mal. Forester 41: 334 (1978)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 138 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 102 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 103 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus retrophyllus</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<bibref>Becc., Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 (Suppl.): 123 (1913)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Smooth</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Rotan Liah (Br.,Mal.), Wi Anak (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary (very rarely clustered) moderate high-climbing rattan to 30 m or more; stem without sheaths 8-10 mm diam., with to 20 mm, internodes to 25 cm. Sheaths dull to pale green, drying very pale brownish-green, armed with sparse horizontal &#177; triangular spines borne on swollen bases, sometimes also with very faint horizontal ridges, sometimes unarmed, and with brown scales abundant on young leaf surfaces; knee conspicuous; ocrea scarcely developed. Leaf cirrate to 1 m, including the cirrus to 65 cm; petiole absent; leaflets c. 20 on each side of the rachis, concolorous, arranged irregularly, the basal up to 8 pairs on each side very close and strongly reflexed across the leaf sheaths forming a chamber in which ants frequently nest; upper leaflets in groups of 2-4 and fanned within the groups, the largest leaflets to c. 20 &#215; 0.5-2 cm, somewhat plicate, drying very pale green. Inflorescences usually about the same length as the leaves, without a terminal flagellum, and with up to 10 partial inflorescences; main bracts rather densely armed with black-tipped, pale, bulbous-based spines and brown indumentum, ultimate bracts and bracteoles with abundant minute spines producing a rough feel. Mature fruit rounded, c. 12 mm diam., with a short beak and covered with 15-19 vertical rows of pale straw- to whitish-coloured scales, sometimes flecked with red. Seed rounded, c. 10 mm diam., deeply pitted; endosperm slightly ruminate. Seedling leaf bifid. (Fig. 35, Pl. 10D).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Throughout Brunei. Elsewhere throughout Borneo and Peninsular Malaysia, rather rare in Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Produces an excellent cane of the same diameter as rotan sega but as the plant is usually solitary, harvests are not great.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. laevigatus var. laevigatus is a very widespread species occurring at altitudes up to 850 m above sea level and on a variety of soils. This is a very variable taxon. Some forms have very narrow leaflets. This species can easily be seen from the Labi Road in Andulau Forest Reserve.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Sungai Liang, Andulau F.R, Fuchs 21153. TEM: Amo, Belalong, Stockdale 11; Amo, Bt.Belalong, Dransfield J. 7111. TUT: Lamunin, Dransfield J. 6805.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>