<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name><mods:namePart>Basu, Shyamal K.</mods:namePart></mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus nambariensis</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11:433.  1908 &amp;Appendix PI. 193, 194. 1913</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A robust climber; stem cluster forming, with leafsheath to 4 cm in diameter. Leaves cirrate, to 3 m long; leafsheath with distinct knee, armed with broadly subulate, subseriate, horizontal to deflexed spines; petiole about 30 cm long, flattened upper, armed at margins with 2 - 3 cm long subulate spines; rachis with strong digitate claws on lowerr side; leaflets lanceolate, ensiform, variously spreading, remotely subequidistant; each about 50 cm long, 4 cm broad at middle, usually 5-nerved, nerves more or less smooth. Male inflorescence simply decompound; partial inflorescences with alternatre, 3 - 4 cm long rachillae; each with distinct cushion at the base, arching above; male flowers 3 mm long, 14-15 male flowers on each side of the rachillae; female rachillae sinuous, incurved, about 6-10 cm long, attached at the mouth of the basal bract. Fruit globose, 2.5 cm in diameter; fruit scales in 21 series; fruiting perianth pedicelliform.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (Assam). Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Infrequent in the moist forests of Assam Valley.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Not cultivated.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane is strong, exported from Assam to other states for making furniture frames.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Assam : Jeypore, Feb. 1877, Nambar forest, Silviculturist (CAL); Assam : Jeypore, 15.12.1896, Silviculture Range (one sheet in DD). No recent collection available.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>