<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus flabellatus Becc. Becc.</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Malesia 3: 62 (1886)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11: 176 (1908)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 45:87 (1990)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield,Ratt. Sarawak 150 (1992)</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus flabelloides</name>
<author>Furtado</author>
<bibref>Gard. Bull. Singapore 15: 173 (1956)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 195 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 145 (1984)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Flabellate, fan-shaped</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Takong (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender clustering rattan climbing to 20 m or more; stem without sheaths to 6 mm diam., with sheaths to 12 mm, internodes to 15 cm. All parts drying dark dirty-coloured. Sheaths dark green with scattered reflexed broad-based spines to 5 mm; knee prominent; ocrea inconspicuous. Flagellum to 2 m. Leaf ecirrate, to 60 cm; petiole short or absent; leaflets 3-4 on each side of the rachis or leaf bearing a single pair of leaflets, lowermost pair of leaflets, where more than 1 pair, to 10 &#215; 1.5 cm, reflexed across the stem; mid leaf leaflets to 17 &#215; 4 cm; apical pair joined for 1/3 to 2/3 their length; leaflets bristly only at the tips, surface bluish-grey tinged, transverse veinlets conspicuous. Inflorescences to c. 1.2 m with c. 6 partial inflorescences, tending to be longer in the female. Ripe fruit spherical to ovoid, to 11 &#215; 7 mm, with beak to 2 mm, covered in 10-12 vertical rows of greenish scales. Seed ovoid, shallowly pitted; endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 56).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Scattered throughout Brunei. Elsewhere throughout Borneo, local in Peninsular Malaysia and Sumatra.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>An excellent small-diameter cane, useful for binding or weaving.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. flabellatus is primarily a plant of lowland dipterocarp forest at altitudes up to c. 500 m above sea level. Some forms retain the juvenile leaves consisting of a single pair of broad leaflets, even in high-climbing stems. This form was described by Beccari asC. flabellatus. Furtado named those forms with several pairs of leaflets as C. flabelloides. We now have a wide range of specimens of both forms and intermediates have been collected. It is noteworthy that inflorescences have never been found on the form with a single pair of leaflets. This species could be confused with C. javensis and its allies; the inflorescence of C. flabelloides is much finer, young leaves are pale green rather than pinkish and the curious dull bluish-green cast to the leaves of C. flabelloides is absent in C. javensis. C. gonospermus is superficially similar but has well defined petioles.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6592. TEM: Johns 6520; Amo, Bt.Belalong, Wong 1383; Amo, Bukit Tudal, Davis 460. Without prov.: BRUN 15123; BRUN 15484.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>