<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus nanodendron</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 45: 90(1990)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 135 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Dwarf tree</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Mata Hari (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Massive solitary short-stemmed rattan with erect or sometimes decumbent stem to c. 1 m only; stem without sheaths to c. 5 cm diam., with sheaths to 10 cm diam., internodes very short, to 3 cm only. Sheaths tubular at first, later splitting opposite the petiole for much of their length, dull green, densely covered with robust triangular green spines 5-70 &#215; 3-6 mm, and scattered deciduous scale between the spines; spines around the sheath mouth sometimes more slender and erect; knee absent; ocrea inconspicuous. Flagellum absent. Leaf robust, ecirrate, arching, to 2.5 m long including the petiole to 50 cm; petiole deeply channelled, densely armed with horizontal spines 5-60 &#215; 3-6 mm with swollen bases; leaflets c. 50 on each side of the rachis, narrow, very regular, the longest c. 50 &#215; 2 cm in mid leaf, decreasing to c. 16 &#215; 1 cm at the tip, transverse veinlets very fine and close. Inflorescences short, rarely more than 30 cm, the male with up to 5 partial inflorescences, the female with 2 or spicate; male rachilla curved, c. 5 cm long, the female c. 5.5 cm. Mature fruit rounded or somewhat top-shaped, c. 20 mm diam., covered in c. 26 vertical rows of dull straw-coloured scales. Seed &#177; oblate, 20 &#215; 15 mm, very deeply grooved and pitted, the endosperm otherwise homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known. (Fig. 48, Pls 11B, 12A, 12B).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from a single collection from Andulau Forest Reserve. Elsewhere known only in the First Division of Sarawak. Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. nanodendron is a palm of kerangas or of forest transitional between kerangas and lowland dipterocarp forest. It is a most peculiar and distinctive species with its massive short, not climbing stem. Mature fruit has recently been collected for the first time in Sarawak.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Sungai Liang, Andulau F.R, Wong 324.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>