<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus perakensis Becc. var. crassus J.Dransf.</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 4 (1978)</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan tekokgunung</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary erect short-stemmed rattan with stems rarely exceeding 2 m tall. Stem without sheaths to 2.5 cm in diameter with very prominent nodes, and internodes to 3 cm only. Stem with sheaths to 4 cm in diameter. Sheaths dull green armed with scattered brown erect spines of length varying from 1-4.5 cm, slightly less armed at base of petiole; spines around leaf sheath mouth occasionally conspicuously longer, and erect, brownish; brown indumentum abundant between spines. Knee absent. Flagellum absent. Leaf ecirrate to 3 m tall, with petiole to 2 m armed with pale green spines. Leaflets regular, about 40 on each side of rachis the longest to 40 cm long by 2.5 cm wide conspicuously 3 nerved, armed with sparse bristles on margins and upper surface of nerves, conspicuously and rather densely armed with bristles along 3 nerves near the tip on the undersurface. Uppermost leaflets not strongly divergent. Inflorescences, male much more highly branched than female, to 1.5 m long, with peduncular portion densely spiny, to 60 cm long. Partial inflorescences to 3, rarely more. Bracts large, with tattered limb to 40 cm long by 8 cm wide, very sparsely armed; male rachillae to 1 cm long, female to 10 cm. &#177; mature fruit rounded c 6 mm in diameter very conspicuously beaked, covered in 17 vertical rows of pale brown scales. Seed rounded; endosperm homogeneous.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Trengganu: endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Can be used for making walking sticks.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>"Rotan tekok gunung" is known only from hillslopes from 100-500 m alt. in Diptero-carp forest in Trengganu. It is distinguished from other varieties of C. perakensis by the presence of the greatly expanded inflorescence bract limbs, the rather thick female rachillae and the sparse cinnamon brown indumentum.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>