<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the Rattans of Andaman and Nicobar Islands</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Renuka</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kerala Forest Research Institute, India</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus unifarius Wendl. var. pentong Becc.</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11: 458. PI.206, 1908</citation>
<bibref>Basu, Rattans in India Monogr. Rev. : 59. 1992</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Hara beth</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary, medium diameter rattan. Stem to 20 m long, with sheaths 3.5 cm in diameter, without sheaths upto 2 cm. green when exposed. Leaf 5 m long, cirrate: sheath yellowish green with numerous small spines; spines 0.5 cm long, 3-4 spines grouped together, the groups arranged vertically or horizontally; knee prominent; ocrea not seen; petiole absent; rachis spiny; leaflets alternate, regular, 35 x 6 cm, apical leaflets 40 x 4 cm, drooping.elliptic, usually 5 veined,tips and margins bristly. Inflorescence long flagellate; male inflorescence much branched; rachilla 3 cm long; female inflorescences simply decompound; primary sheaths tightly sheathing, armed with small spines; partial inflorescence to 25 cm long; secondary sheaths to 2 cm long, funnel -shaped; rachillae to 8 cm long, decreasing in length distally; involucrophorum slightly stalked, involucre disc-shaped, fruiting perianth persisting. Fruit oblong, ca. 1.5 x 1 cm, scales in 17 vertical rows, ivory white with brown border, slightly channelled; endosperm not ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Evergreen forests. Great Nicobar. (Map. 7).</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Flowering November - December. Fruiting April-May.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Used in the furniture industry. Not exploited much.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Kamorta, Nicobar Islands, Feb. 1875 Kurzs.n. (CAL) Katchal, 23.3.1997, Chakraborty 5290 (CAL); Galathea Wildlife Camp, Nicobar, 12.4.1993, fr., Renuka and Vijayakumaran 7045 (KFRI).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>