<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus cockburnii</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Malay. Forester 41 (1978) 338</citation>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>P.P. Cockburn - the collector of the type</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Very short-stemmed erect rattan. Stem without sheaths about 7.5 mm in diameter, with sheaths 1.5 cm. Sheaths rather densely armed with partial whorls of brown spines to 1.5 cm long and densely covered with buff indumentum. Knee absent. Ocrea inconspicuous. Leaf including the petiole about 90 cm long, ecirrate; petiole to 35 cm long armed with rather distant whorls of spines to 3.5 cm long. Leaflets about 30 on each side. &#177; regularly arranged, the lowermost 3 more crowded than the rest, the longest to 20 cm long by 1.4 cm wide, armed with bristles to 2 mm long on 3 main nerves above and along margins, unarmed on lower surface. Inflorescence, only female known, erect or arcuate, with peduncle to 25 cm long bearing 1-2 partial inflorescences. Partial inflorescences to 10 cm long with 3-4 distichous rachillae on each side; rachillae to 6 cm long by 3 mm in diameter; all bracts rusty tomentose. Almost ripe fruit rounded, to 10 mm in diameter tipped with a short beak to 1.5 mm long by 1 mm wide, covered in 12 vertical rows of red-brown scales. Endosperm homogeneous. Seedling leaf not known.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Pahang: endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>None known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This miniature species is known from only two collections, both from G. Tapis in Pahang, one collection from 1,200 m alt., the other from 600 m alt. This species could only be confused with C. minutus; for differences between the two, see under C minutus.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>