<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus ashtonii</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 81: 9 (1980)</citation>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 146 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>P. S. Ashton, forest botanist</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Solitary slender rattan, &amp;ldquo;stemless&amp;rdquo; or with a short erect stem to 50 cm, but rarely to 3 m or more; stem without sheaths to 10 mm diam., with sheaths to 30 mm diam., internodes very short, usually c. 10 mm. Sheath greenish-brown, &#177; unarmed or with sparse brown spines to 4 mm, except around the sheath mouth where densely armed with 2 rows of horizontal or erect brown spines to 5 cm long, the inner row generally longer and upward pointing; knee absent; ocrea absent. Flagellum absent. Leaf ecirrate, c. 85 cm long including the petiole to 20 cm; petiole armed with 2 rows of spines on each side as the leaf sheath, the spines decreasing in size towards the tip of the petiole; rachis with few reflexed spines; leaflets very regularly arranged, &#177; curved, the longest near the base c. 35 &#215; 1.7 cm, both surfaces mid green, the lower surface also with 3 rows of short black bristles. Inflorescences elongate, very slender, tending to arch out of the crown, to 2 m long, whip-like; bracts closely sheathing, tubular, not very conspicuous, armed with reflexed grapnel spines; partial inflorescences c. 3, distant, very slender, bearing sparse slender rachillae to 80 &#215; 1 mm; flowers small. Mature fruit rounded, small, c. 5 mm diam., strongly beaked and covered in 13 vertical rows of pale bright brown reflexed scales. Seed rounded; endosperm homogenous. Seedling not known. (Fig. 53).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Known from a few collections from ridge tops in Temburong and Belait; elsewhere in Sarawak. Endemic to Borneo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not known.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>C. ashtonii appears to be confined to podsolized ridge tops and kerangas forest in the lowlands. It is an attractive short rattan, easily identified by the habit, spines on the sheaths and petiole bases, the neat regular leaflets and the long whip-like inflorescences.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6578; Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6580; Melilas, Bt.Batu Patam, Dransfield J. 6603. TEM: Amo, Bukit Belalong, Stockdale 55.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>