<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Nomenclatural note - correcting errors in Palms of Madagascar</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Govaerts</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">R.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Palms, 50(4): 184</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>2006</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis anovensis</name>
<author></author>
<citation></citation>
<type>Madagascar, R Anove; Perrier; 12066</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang=""><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Slender forest undergrowth palm to 2 m tall. STEM c. 7 mm diam. (not exceeding 3 cm, fide Jumelle). LEAVES c. 6 in crown (7-8, fide Jumelle); sheaths 6.5 cm long, c. 7 mm diam., covered in caducous chocolate-coloured scales; petiole 8-15 cm long, c. 2.5 mm wide near base, covered in a thick layer of caducous pale brown scales; rachis 9-10 cm; leaflets 3-4 on each side of the rachis, &#177; regularly arranged, drying pale green, up to 2.5 cm distant, the longest to 25 cm long, c. 4-12 mm wide, mostly composed of a single fold, both surfaces with scattered punctiform scales, abaxially with broad bands of caducous brown scales. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, in bud much shorter than the leaves, but one dead inflorescence axis suggesting eventually as long as leaves (to 45 cm fide Jumelle), branching to 1 order only; peduncle 21 cm; prophyll to 8 x 0.4 cm, membranous; peduncular bract exceeding prophyll by 9.5 cm, otherwise similar (exceeding prophyll by 23 cm fide Jumelle); rachis c. 5 cm (8-12 cm, fide Jumelle) with rather dense brown scales; rachillae probably c. 14, c. 2 cm long, c. 0.5 mm diam., rather sparsely scaly, triads c. 0.5 mm apart in immature inflorescence, rachilla bract entire, inconspicuous. STAMINATE FLOWERS in very young bud, all parts at an early state of development; stamens 3 antepetalous.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Only known from the Anove River near Soanierana-Ivongo.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Rain forest at low elevation.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Presumed extinct. Not seen for more than eighty years. Most of the forest has disappeared from the Anove River mouth.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The need for the new name, Dypsis anovensis, is a consequence of the inclusion of Neophloga in Dypsis.   Dypsis anovensis is known only from its type. The combination of slender, linear leaflets and small sparsely branched inflorescence is paralleled by D. cookei from high elevation forest on Marojejy; however, the leaflet texture of the latter is different and there are consistently more leaflets on each side of the rachis, that dry dark rather than pale green. Some of the dimensions mentioned by Jumelle suggest that he had more mature inflorescences at hand than the one preserved on the type sheet in P.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Soanierana-Ivongo: near to River Anove, Sept. 1912 (buds), Perrier 12066 (holotype P).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>