<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the Rattans of Andaman and Nicobar Islands</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Renuka</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Kerala Forest Research Institute, India</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus baratangensis</name>
<author>Renuka and Vijayakumaran</author>
<citation>Rheedea 4: 141. 1994</citation>
<synonymy>
<name>C. pseiidorivalis</name>
<author>auct. non. Becc., 1908</author>
<bibref>Parkinson, For. Fl. Andm. Isl. 265,1921</bibref> 
<bibref>Basu, Rattans in India Monogr. Rev.: 90. 1992</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Malay beth, Razi beth</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering, medium diameter rattan. Stem 25 m long or more, with sheaths 2 cm in diameter, without sheaths 1.2 cm. Leaf 1 m long, ecirrate; sheath green, spiny or glabrous, spines when present brown or black.flat, short on the younger sheaths, to 2cm long on mature sheath; knee prominent: ocrea slightly developed, petiole 14 cm long, margins armed with small spines; spines 0.3 cm long: rachis with a raw of small spines underneath, spines 0.5 cm long; leaflets 30-56 x 2.5 - 4 cm gradually becoming smaller towards the tip, basal part of the terminal pair united, dark green, linear lanceolate, regular, midvein prominent. Male inflorescence long flagellate, primary sheath tightly sheathing; partial inflorescence to 55 cm long; secondary sheath funnel-shaped; rachilla 7 cm long. Female inflorescence long flagellate, primary sheath tightly sheathing, spiny along the sides; partial inflorescence 55 cm long; secondary sheath tightly sheathing; rachilla 7 cm long, decrease in length distally; involucre cup shaped; fruiting perianth 0.4 cm long. Fruits ovoid, ca. 1.25 x 0.9 cm, scales in 21 vertical rows, green when young, turns gray white on maturation, light violet on ripening, channelled at the middle: endosperm not ruminate.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>In evergreen forests of Andamans (Map. 5) Very common in Baratang island.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Flowering November-December. Fruiting April - May.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Used in furniture industry and for tying rafts.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>The species display morphological variations in the diameter of the stem and in the armature of the sheath. Rogers himself has made a note of such variations on his sheets. We have found that the diameter of the cane uarlesfrom 0.5-1.2 cm In the same clump. The younger sheaths are more spiny than the older ones.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Baratang island, Andamans, 12.4.88, fr., Renu/ca4066 (KFRI); Adajig Range, Baratang island, Andamans, 4.4.1992, fr. Vijayakumaran 6628, (KFRI); Pudumadurai, North Andamans, 30.4.92, fr., Vijayakumaran 6640 (KFRI); Mannarghat, South Andamans, 1.4.1993, male inn., Renuka and Vijayakumaran 7029 (KFRI). Rogers 48, 49 (K. cibachrome).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>