<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus latifolius</name>
<author>Roxb.</author>
<citation>F. Ind. 3 : 775. 1832</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook. f. Fl. Brit. Ind. 6 :445. 1892</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 : 406. 1908 and Appendix PI. 171. 1913.</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Korak bet, Horna bet.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A moderately robust climber; stem cluster forming; with leafsheath 3 cm in diameter. Leaves curate, 2 - 3 m long; leafsheath with prominent knee, armed with subulate, sub-regularly verticillate, dark brown, 3 cm long spines; ocrea liguliform; rachis terete in cross section, without claws on the ventral side, armed only with small spicules; leaflets not many, papery, inequidis-tant on rachis, broadly lanceolate or elliptic-lanceolate, slightly concavo-convex, to 50 cm long, 10 cm wide at broadest part, 5-7 nerved; nerves smooth on both sides. Male inflorescence simply decompound; partial inflorescences twice branched; rachillae 3 - 4 cm long with 8-12 male flowers on each side of the rachilla; the sterile basal part of rachilla enclosed within the respective basal bracts. Male flowers 5 mm long, ovoid in bud; calyx externally striated, divided up to the middle to form 3-acute lobes. Female inflorescence simply decompound, rigid, erect not very diffuse, 60- 100cm long, shorter than leaves; partial inflorescences 4 in number, 15 - 20 cm long, with 4 - 6 rachillae on each side, caudiform at their apices; rachillae inserted just at the mouth of the respective basal bracts; each 5 - 6 cm long, sinuous with 8-10 flowers on each side; involucrophorum enclosed in its bract, cupular; involucre concealed in the involucrophorum, visible only by the two projecting teeth on the side of neuter flower; female flowers 5 mm long; calyx finely striated, deeply divided into broad, semiovate, acute lobes; corolla lobes narrower than calyx lobes. Fruiting perianth not distinctly pedicelliform. Fruit globose, 1-seeded, dull brown to blackish, to 1.5 cm in diameter, fruit scales flattened, not distinctly channelled at middle; seed globosen blackish, roughly pitted.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (West Bengal, Sikkim, Assam, Arunachal Pradesh, Meghalaya, Nagaland), BANGLADESH.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>A component of the moist lower hill forests upto 1000 m mostly near the fresh water swamps.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Experimental cultivation exists under D.F.O. North Silviculture, West Bengal.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane is moderately strong and used for making rough baskets, walking sticks, and furniture frames; split canes for weaving chair bottoms.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Sikkim: 200-400 ft. Hook.f. &amp; Thomson (CAL Ace. no. 494083); Maghalaya: K.J. hills, Lisbah, River bank, 27.7.1957 Deka 10117 (CAL); Jorain, 24.7.1957, Deka 10150 (CAL); Assam : Deko valley, 30.3.1895, Herb. Wall. no. 11074 (CAL); Arunachal Pradesh: Nausa to Warmi 1441 m, 1.9.1958, Panigrahi 15027 (CAL).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>