<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus dransfieldii</name>
<author>Renuka</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 42(2): 433, 1987</citation>
<bibref>Renuka, K.F.R.I. Res. Rep. 46: 23. PI. 8, Figs. 1-5, 1987.</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A moderately robust climber; stem solitary ? or cluster-forming, to 8 m long, with leafsheath 3.5 cm in diameter, without sheath 2.5 cm in diameter. Leaves ecirrate, to 2 m long; leafsheath pale green, with distinct knee, sparingly spiny; spines 1 cm long, with bulbous base; ocrea absent; leafsheath flagellum to 6 cm long; petiole to 55 cm long, armed with 5 mm long spines; leaflets pale green, regularly disposed on rachis, narrowly lanceolate, acuminate, 45 cm x 2 cm; nerves with 2 cm long ciliae on both surface. Inflorescence flagelliform. Male and female inflorescences superficially similar, 3.5 m long; each with 4-5, about 20 cm long, once branched, partial inflorescences; rachillae to 6 cm long; subtending bracts cylindrical at base and expanded upper to form a 1.5 cm long cup. Male flowers about 8 mm long. Female flowers 4 mm long; staminodes 6, ovary 3-locular; ovule solitary in each locule: stigma recurved. Fruit globose, 1.8 m in diameter, shortly beaked, falsely pedicellate; fruit scales green to yellowish green, shinning, deeply channelled at middle.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (Kerala). Endemic.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Infrequent in the moist deciduous forests of Dhoni hills, Palghat at 275 m.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Not cultivated.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This newly described species is close to the less known rattan species Calamus delessertianus.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Kerala; Dhoni, Palghat 300 m, 31.1.1983, Nambiar &amp; Renuka 2501 (KFRI); Trivendrum: Beyond Suryakan thi, 750 m, 22.5.1979, Mohanan 63205 (MH).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>