<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>The genus Areca (Palmae: Arecoideae) in Borneo</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:publisher>Kew Bulletin, Vol. 39, No. 1, pp 1-22</mods:publisher>
<mods:dateIssued>1984</mods:dateIssued>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Areca klingkangensis</name>
<author>J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Kew Bull. 39: 15 (1984)</citation>
<type>Borneo, Sarawak, 1st Division, Sabal Tapang Forest Reserve, G. Gaharu; J. Dransfield et al.; JD 6103</type>
<type_loc>Holotype K; isotypi BH, SAR</type_loc>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p>A. klingkangensis is named after the Klingkang Range, of which G. Gaharu is one of the higher summits, the range which separates Sarawak from Kalimantan Barat.</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p></p></div>
<div type="diagnosis"><p>inter species maiores sectionis Microarecae propter florem staminatum stipitatum A. abdulrahmanii et A. ander- sonii affinis sed staminibus 9 vice c. 16 vel 6 distincta.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Erect, solitary, undergrowth palmlet. Stem to 2 m tall, c. 7-10 mm diam.; internodes green, 2.5-6 cm long, bearing scattered dull brown scales; nodal scars c. 3 mm wide. Crownshaft well-defined, pale green drying dull brown- ish, c. 25 x 1.5 cm, only slightly swollen; leafsheaths neatly abscissing, c. 10 cm long, longitudinally striate, bearing scattered dark brown scales; ligule c. 3 mm long, soon tattering and becoming lost. Leaf pinnate, excluding sheath to c. 55 cm, including petiole to 12 x 0.3 cm; leaflets 3-6 on each side of the rachis, distant, stiff, very coriaceous, narrow, 1-3-ribbed, concolorous, drying mid-brown, 22-40 x 0.7-1.7 cm, the longest near the base, the shor- test at the apex, acuminate except for the apical pair where tip minutely lobed; minute brown scales present on both surfaces, more abundant abaxially. Inflorescence infrafoliar, branching to 1 order, short, not exceeding c. 8 cm long, usually shorter; prophyll winged, c. 8 x 2 cm or less, bearing scattered scales; peduncle very short, c. 15 mm long, 5 mm wide just above the winged base; rachillae divergent, usually 3 only, to c. 6 cm long, c. 4 mm diam. at the base, tapering to the tip, bright reddish tinged, bearing abun- dant persistent low blackish scales, and sparse, caducous, chaffy hairs; triads rarely more than 2-3 at the base of each rachilla, the rachillae otherwise bearing spirally arranged paired or solitary staminate flowers. Staminate flower irregularly angled, markedly stipitate, especially those of the triads; stipitate base of calyx 0.5-2.5 x 1 mm, angled, glabrous, calyx lobes low c. 0.7 x 1 mm triangular, the margins smooth; petals valvate, glabrous broadly triangular, c. 2.5-3.5 X 1-1.5 mm; stamens 9, slightly irregular, borne on very short or obsolete filaments, anthers 1.8-2 x 0.5-0.6 mm, latrorse; pistillode lacking. Pistillate flower sessile; sepals 3, free c. 5.5 x 3.5 mm, imbricate, cucullate, sparsely hairy along the strong keel, minutely ciliate along margins; petals 3, imbricate, ovate, c. 4.5 x 5 mm, ciliate; staminodes 6, minute; ovary ± conical in bud, c. 2.5 mm diam. at base, tipped with 3 fleshy, angled stigmas. Young fruit greenish tinged; mature fruit known only in mummified condition, fusiform, 26 x 5 mm.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Borneo, Sarawak, 1st Division, known only from the type collection.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>I discovered this species growing in very wet mossy forest developed on an eroded sandstone block summit at c. 700 m altitude; for an account of its discovery see Dransfield (1982).</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p></p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species has smaller inflorescences and fruit than A. abdulrahmanii and A. andersonii, and may easily be distinguished by the pres- ence of 9 rather than 6 or c. 16 stamens. With these two species it forms a rather distinctive group within section Microareca. </p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>