<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>A Manual of the rattans of the Malay Peninsula. Malayan Forest Recirds 29.</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1979</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Department, Ministry of Primary Industries, Malaysia</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus palustris Griff. malaccensis Becc.</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Ann. Roy. Bot. Card. Calcutta 11 (1908) 405 and supplement (1913) 86</citation>
<bibref>Furtado in Gdns' Bull. Singapore 15 (1956) 90</bibref>
<synonymy>
<name>Calamus dumetorum</name>
<author>Ridley</author>
<bibref>Ridley in Mat. Fl. Mal. Pen. 2 (1907) 211</bibref>
<bibref>Ridley in Fl. Mai. Pen. 5 (1925) 63</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="la"><p>Palustris - of marshes.  (of Malacca)</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>rotan?</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering rattan climbing to 25 m tall, flowering when quite short. Stem without sheaths about 1.5 - 2 cm in diameter with internodes to 30 cm; stem with sheaths to 3.5 cm. Sheaths bright green, armed with scattered brown yellow-based spines to 3 cm long, usually less, with much smaller spines scattered in between. Reddish brown indumentum abundant on young sheaths. Knee conspicuous. Ocrea to 3 mm high, dark brown unarmed. Leaf cirrate to 2.5 m long including the cirrus to 1 m; petiole short, about 10-15 cm long, semicircular in cross-section, the upper flat surface armed with short erect spines. Leaflets to about 21 on each side of the rachis, arranged in 2's to 4's broad, spafhulate, to about 35 cm long by 4 cm wide unarmed or very sparsely armed. Inflorescence, only male known, to about 1 m long with about 12 close partial inflorescences to 25 m long, decreasing in length above. Bracts sparsely armed. Rachillae about 2 cm long.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Penang, Perak. Rare. Variety endemic, typical species in Burma and Thailand.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p></p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>This species has a beautiful yellowish glossy cane of excellent general appearance. It is not known if it is utilized, but as every known clump is near villages, there is some suggestion that it might have been planted there. Much suggests that this species has potential as a cultivated rattan.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>Calamus palustris is known from a few localities near Ipoh, found growing in belukar near the main road, Ipoh to Kuala Kangsar, and by limestone hills near Tambun, and in belukar at the edge of the Waterfall Gardens in Penang.
For differences from C. axillaris see that species. It is easily identified by means of the italicized characters.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>