<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Rattans (canes) in India. A Monographic Revision</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Basu</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">S.K.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1992</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Forest Research Institute, Malaysia</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Calamus leptospadix</name>
<author>Griff.</author>
<citation>Calc. Journ. Nat. Hist.5 : 1845</citation>
<bibref>Beccari in Hook. f. Fl.Brit.Ind. 6:44. 1892</bibref>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. Calcutta 11 :142. 1908 and Appendix PI. 14. 1913</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Dhangri bet, Rab bet, Rani bet, Mugri bet.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>A slender cluster forming climber; stem thickened at joints, with lead-sheaths 12-20 mm in diameter, naked stem smooth, 8 -10 mm in diameter at the internodes. Leaves ecirrate, delicate looking, 80-105 cm long; leafsheath with flagellum, thickly scurfy outside, armed with flattened, 15-20 mm long, subulate, half-whorled spines; ocrea persistent, prickly at margins; flagellum filiform with non-spinous base; armed distally with small, delicate claws; petiole terete; petiole and rachis armed with deflexed spines and claws; rachis delicate angular, covered thickly with greyish indumentum; leaflets closely placed, linear-ensiform, alternate to sub-opposite, to 30 cm long, distinctly 3-nerved, attenuate at base; acuminate to bristly subulate at apex; uppermost leaflets shorter. Male inflorescence flagelliform, decompound; male rachillae scorpioid, 1 -2cm long, with 6-12 closely set bifarious flowers. Male flowers 4-4.5 X 1.5 mm; calyx tubular, campanulate, divided up to middle into apiculate lobes; corolla double the length of calyx into 3 oblong segments. Female inflorescence similar to male; female rachillae erect from base, arching above, 1.5 - 2 cm long; each with 5-8 female flowers. Fruit globose, 1.5 mm in diameter, mamil-late; fruit scales yellow with reddish brown margins, channelled at middle; seed globose, endosperm homogeneous.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>INDIA (West Bengal, Sikkim, Meghalaya, Assam, Manipur, Nagaland, Arunachal Pradesh), BHUTAN.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Mostly on damp river plains, and forming big thickets. It becomes a cluster forming high climber when it grows in moist valleys among tall trees.</p></div>
<div type="cultivation"><p>Infrequent in silviculture practice. Experimental cultivation was possible in the Jalpaiguri forest division of north Bengal. Cultivated in the Indian Botanic Garden, Howrah.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Cane is thin and delicate therefore used mainly for making rough baskets. Split canes are durable and used for making chair bottoms.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p></p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p></p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>