<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>Genera Palmarum. The evolution and classification of palms</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Uhl</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">N.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Asmussen</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Baker</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">W.J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Harley</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">M.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Lewis</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">C.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo>
<mods:dateIssued>2008</mods:dateIssued><mods:publisher>Kew Publishing, Royal Botanic Gardens Kew</mods:publisher></mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="genus">
<div type="diagnosis"><p>Small, solitary or clustering palms of South American rain forests, often with entire leaves or with broad pinnae: the staminate flowers have stamens adnate to the pistillode and the fruit has basal stigmatic remains.</p></div>
<nomenclature>
<name>Hyospathe</name>
<author>Mart.</author> 
<citation>Hist. nat. palm. 2: 1 (1823).</citation> 
<type>Type; Hyospathe elegans; Mart.</type>
</nomenclature>
<div type="etymology"><p>Hyo-from hys — pig, spathe — sheath or bract, derived from the vernacular name tajassu-ubi — pig leaf or pork palm.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Small or rarely moderate, solitary or clustering, graceful, unarmed, pleonanthic, monoecious palms. Stem slender, ringed with conspicuous, sometimes oblique, rather distant leaf scars. Leaves regularly pinnate, entire and bifid, or bi- or trijugate; sheath usually forming a short to long crownshaft, not splitting opposite the petiole until shed, margin irregular, chartaceous, striate, adaxially grooved, glabrous, abaxially with scattered scales; petiole moderate, slender, abaxially rounded, with hairs or deciduous scales; rachis adaxially ridged, abaxially ridged or rounded, also scaly; leaflets lanceolate to falcate, pointed, often somewhat curved apically, alternate, single-fold, several-fold or many-fold, bearing scattered deciduous scales along abaxial ribs and sometimes basally on adaxial ribs, laterally, tapering to a rather blunt point, chartaceous, splitting surfaces similar or dissimilar in colour, midrib prominent, 1–2 pairs of dorsiventrally and apically to become bifid, inserted above the base of the parallel veins also conspicuous in some species, transverse veinlets peduncle; peduncular bracts 1–2, terete, much longer than or about as long conspicuous or obscure. Inflorescence solitary, branched to 1 order, branches as the prophyll, beaked, splitting abaxially, inserted somewhat above the stiff or pendulous; peduncle short or long, slender; prophyll 2-keeled prophyll; rachis much shorter to rarely longer than the peduncle; rachis bracts very short, obscure, subtending spirally inserted rachillae; rachillae slender, rather distant or crowded, moderate to short and stiff or long and pendulous, sometimes undulate apically, bearing spirally arranged triads of flowers nearly throughout and paired to solitary staminate flowers distally; floral bracteoles shallow, rounded. Staminate flowers lateral to the pistillate, sessile or stalked, narrow, elongate; sepals 3, united in a tube, adnate basally for at least 2/3 their length to the receptacle to form a stalk-like base, free tips short, broadly triangular; petals 3, distinct, narrowly ovate, asymmetical, curved basally, pointed distally; stamens 6, the 3 antesepalous with shorter filaments, free or shortly joined with the pistillode, the 3 antepetalous with filaments much longer, adnate to the pistillode nearly to its apex, filaments awl-shaped, anthers moderately long, dorsifixed near the base, latrorse, united throughout; pistillode narrowly ovoid with 2 stigmatic lobes. Pollen ellipsoidal, with slight or obvious asymmetry; aperture a distal sulcus; ectexine tectate, finely or coarsely perforate-rugulate, aperture margin finer; infratectum columellate; longest axis 34–39 µm [1/17]. Pistillate flower ovoid, shorter than the staminate; sepals 3, united in a cupule for ca. 2/3 their length, tips broad, pointed, striate; petals 3, distinct, ovate, moderately imbricate, striate, tips pointed; staminodes 6, small, strap-like; gynoecium ovoid, unilocular, uniovulate, narrowed to a short tubular style, stigmas 3, recurved at anthesis, ovule basal, laterally attached, form unknown. Fruit ovoid to cylindrical, pointed, asymmetrical, black at maturity, stigmatic remains basal; epicarp smooth, lightly mottled, mesocarp fibrous, endocarp thin, crustaceous. Seed narrow, ovoid, ± pointed, hilum basal, raphe branches anastomosing, endosperm homogeneous; embryo rather large, basal. Germination adjacent-ligular; eophyll bifid. Cytology not studied.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Six species ranging from Costa Rica to Peru. </p></div>
<div type="anatomy"><p>See Skov and Balslev (1989). </p></div>
<div type="relationships"><p>Hyospathe is monophyletic (Henderson 1999a). The genus is resolved as sister to the rest of the Euterpeae with moderate support (Asmussen et al. 2006, Baker et al. in review), or as sister to Neonicholsonia, Oenocarpus and Prestoea with low support (Henderson 1999a). </p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>These palms would make handsome ornamentals. </p></div>
<div type="taxonomic accounts"><p>Skov and Balslev (1989), Henderson (2004), see also Henderson (1999a). </p></div>
<div type="fossil record"><p>No generic records found. </p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>It seems surprising that their ornamental potential has not been exploited. The difference in length of antesepalous and antepetalous stamens and the adnation of the antepetalous filaments to the pistillode are distinctive and unusual in the family as a whole. </p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Hog palm, ubim palm (Hyospathe elegans). </p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>In rain forest, in swamps or on dry ground at low elevations but also on the slopes of the Andes between 1000–2000 m.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>
