<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
		<mods:mods>
		<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Palms of Madagascar</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="family">Beentje</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">H.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
		<mods:originInfo>
			<mods:dateIssued>1995</mods:dateIssued>
			<mods:publisher>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and The International Palm Society</mods:publisher>
		</mods:originInfo>
		</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Dypsis integra</name>
<author>(Jum.) Beentje &amp; J.Dransf.</author>
<citation>Palms of Madagascar: 319 (1995)</citation>
<type>Simiane (Simianona) R.; Perrier; 11944</type>
<type_loc>Holotype P</type_loc>
<synonymy>
<name>Neophloga integra</name>
<author>Jum.</author>
<bibref>Jum., Ann. Inst. Bot.-G&#233;ol. Colon. Marseille s&#233;r. 4, 6, fasc. 3: 13 (1929)</bibref>
<bibref>Cat. Pl. Madagascar Palmae: 21 (1938)</bibref>
<bibref>Jum. &amp; H. Perrier, Fl. Madagascar 30: 61 (1945)</bibref>
</synonymy>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p>The name is Latin for 'entire', since the leaf appears to be completely unlobed on the type, with a rounded apex. On close examination the leaf is seen to be slightly folded near the apex, with a small notch.</p></div>
<div type="etymology"><p></p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Clustering palm. STEMS 20 cm (Beentje 4515) to 2 m (Perrier 18047), 0.4-0.9 cm diam., internodes 1-1.5 cm long, pale green with dense red- brown scales; nodal scars c.1 mm. LEAVES 8-10 in the crown, spreading; sheaths 4.3-6 cm long, open for c. 50%, proximally pale reddish green, distally pale creamy green,   with red laciniate scales, very dense distally, with narrowly triangular ligules 3-4 mm long at the base of the petiole; petiole 0.3-2 cm, 2-2.5 mm diam., densely scaly; blade entire, narrowly obovate, 15-33 x 4-7 cm, acute at the base, the margins toothed in the distal third or half, rounded at the apex with a 3-17 mm deep notch, midrib prominent on both surfaces with laciniate scales, other veins faint with minute scattered scales in lines. INFLORESCENCE interfoliar, erect to spreading, unbranched; peduncle 12-15 cm long, 1.5-3 x 1.5 mm diam., with scattered laciniate scales; prophyll 7-11 cm, borne at 2-3.5 cm above the base of the peduncle with c. 2 mm wide wings, with a 2-sided lateral split in the distal few cm; peduncular bract inserted at 5-7 cm from the base of the peduncle, 7-12 cm long, with scattered scales, laterally split on one side in the distal 1-2 cm; rachilla 5-11 cm long, 1-2 mm diam., with scattered scales, with slightly distant superficial triads; rachilla bracts entire, rounded, at the margins with reddish laciniate scales. STAMINATE FLOWERS with sepals 0.8-1 x 0.8-1 mm, keeled, gibbous, ciliolate to ciliate, with slightly connate base, membranous; petals 2-2.2 x 1-1.3 mm, elliptic, acute, striate, almost free; stamens 6, uniseriate, equal, filaments 0.8 mm long, connate at the base in a 0.2 mm high ring, anthers 1.5-1.6 x 0.5-0.6 mm, dorsifixed, the locules parallel and blunt; pistillode 1.2-1.3 x 0.3 mm. PISTILLATE FLOWERS only known from young bud, with sepals imbricate, 1.2- 1.3 x 1-1.5 mm, ciliate, rounded; petals valvate, 1.8 x 0.7 mm; ovary 1.6 x 0.7 mm; staminodes c.0.2 mm. FRUIT unknown.</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>East Coast, between Mananara Avaratra and Vangaindrano.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>Lowland rain forest; 50-300 m.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p>Critical. The only recent collection is from Manombo Forest, which is being destroyed by fire, shifting cultivation and logging. Both of the older sites have been visited, but the species has not been seen there.</p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Not recorded.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>This species is close to D. simianensis and more material might even show the species to be synonymous.  Beentje 4515 differs from the type in the hairi greater in 4515) and the shape of the sheath (more open, and much wider in 4515) as well as in the leaf venation (transverse, sinuous veinlets clearly visible in 4515).</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>Soanierana-Ivongo: Simiane (Simianona) R., Sept. 1917 (old infl.), Perrier 11944 (Holotype P). Mahanoro: lower Mangoro basin, Oct. 1927 (bud), Perrier 18047 (P). Farafangana: Manombo, Nov. 1991 (bud), Beentje 4515 (K, MO, TAN).</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>