<taxonx xmlns:dc="http://digir.net/schema/conceptual/darwin/core/2.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<taxonxHeader>
<mods:mods>
<mods:titleInfo><mods:title>The Rattans of Brunei Darussalam</mods:title></mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name>
<mods:namePart type="family">Dransfield</mods:namePart>
<mods:namePart type="given">J.</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:originInfo><mods:dateIssued>1997</mods:dateIssued>
<mods:publisher>Ministry of Industry and primary Resources, Brunei Darussalam</mods:publisher>
</mods:originInfo>
</mods:mods>
</taxonxHeader>
<taxonxBody>
<treatment rank="species">
<nomenclature>
<name>Korthalsia echinometra</name>
<author>Becc.</author>
<citation>Malesia 2: 66 (1884)</citation>
<bibref>Beccari, Ann. Roy. Bot Gard. Calcutta 18(2): 115 (1918)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Man. Ratt. Malay Pen. 47 (1979)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Kew Bull. 36: 188 (1981)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sabah 22 (1984)</bibref>
<bibref>Dransfield, Ratt. Sarawak 28 (1992)</bibref>
</nomenclature>
<div type="introduction"><p></p></div>
<div type="etymology" lang="el"><p>Spiny pudenda</p></div>
<div type="vernacular"><p>Wi Keruk, Wi Wisro (Ib.)</p></div>
<div type="description"><p>Moderately robust clustering and branching rattan climbing to 40 m. Stem without sheaths to 2 cm diam., with sheaths to 3 cm. diam., internodes rather short to 12 cm. Sheaths bright green, sparsely armed, almost completely covered by the ocreas; ocrea to 10 &#215; 5 cm, grossly swollen, densely covered with long black spines to 6 cm long; ants abundant within the ocreas. Leaf to 1.8 m including the cirrus to 70 cm and petiole to 10 cm or more. Leaflets numerous, c. 25 on each side of the rachis, narrowly elongate, to 30 &#215; 3 cm, dark green on the upper surface, chalky- white beneath, praemorse only in the distalmost 3-6 cm. Inflorescences to c. 60 cm long, with up to 15 rachillae in each; rachillae to 20 &#215; 1.5 cm, reddish-brown tomentose. Mature fruit ovoid, 2.5 &#215; 1.5 cm, covered in 18-21 vertical rows of reddish- brown scales. Seed to 15 &#215; 10 mm; endosperm ruminate. Seedling leaf bifid with narrow leaflets. (Fig. 6, Pl. 2C, 2D).</p></div>
<div type="distribution"><p>Very widespread throughout Brunei. Elsewhere widespread in Borneo, Sumatra and the southern part of Peninsular Malaysia.</p></div>
<div type="biology_ecology"><p>It occurs in lowland and hill dipterocarp forest up to 1000 m above sea level.</p></div>
<div type="conservation"><p></p></div>
<div type="uses"><p>Much sought after for use, split, in basket weaving and for basket frames.</p></div>
<div type="discussion"><p>K. echinometra is perhaps the commonest species of the genus. It is a very distinctive species, though confusingly like a rattan other than a species of Korthalsia when viewed from a distance. The very spiny swollen ocrea and narrow leaflets are diagnostic.</p></div>
<div type="materials_examined"><p>BEL: Sungai Liang, Sungei Liang Arboretem, Wong 143. TEM: Amo, K.Belalong, Dransfield J. 6721; Batu Apoi, Bt.Gelagas (Bt.Suang), Simpson 2365. Without prov.: BRUN 15126.</p></div>
</treatment>
</taxonxBody>
</taxonx>