<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="identifiable-entities"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Identifiable Entities</title>
  </info>

  <caution>
    <title>Likely to change</title>

    <para>Globally unique identifiers, their use and implementation are still
    an unresolved topic. The implementaton of objects that are identifiable
    and resolvable in a global sense must, given an open world, reflect the
    standards and best practices being used by the community as a whole.
    Consequently this area of the CDM is likely to change to reflect
    this.</para>
  </caution>

  <section>
    <para>Some entities in the CDM extend
    <classname>IdentifiableEntity</classname>. In general there is one or two
    abstract base classes that extend
    <classname>IdentifiableEntity</classname> in each package. These classes
    represent important objects that an application might want to share with
    another application (and hence, publish globally unique identifiers
    for).</para>

    <para>Current implemetation of the GUID in the CDM is based on the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.omg.org/cgi-bin/doc?dtc/04-05-01">LSID Resolution
    Service</link> implementation of the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.cate-project.org">CATE project</link>. Each
    <classname>IdentifiableEntity</classname> has an <varname>lsid</varname>
    property. See the section on <link linkend="guid-resolution">GUID
    Resolution</link> to see how the CDM Java Library makes it easier for you
    to manage and publish your data.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <!--ben: I must admit, I think I prefer formatter to cacheStrategyGenerator, because the purpose of the property seems clearer to me-->

    <title><varname>titleCache</varname> and
    <varname>cacheStrategyGenerator</varname></title>

    <para>Classes that extend <classname>IdentifiableEntity</classname> have a
    <varname>titleCache</varname> attribute. This property is used represent
    the object (for example, in a list of objects or the title for a page
    displaying metadata about that object). The <varname>titleCache</varname>
    is also used by default when sorting lists of entities. Applications are
    free to use other properties or combinations of properties in representing
    objects and can supply their own implementations of the interfaces in the
    <package>eu.etaxonomy.cdm.strategy.cache</package> package. If you do wish
    to supply custom cache strategies, you will need to inject them into your
    data entities, overriding the default strategy (using something like
    Spring's <emphasis>spring-managed</emphasis> configuration
    mechanism).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Recording Provenance using
    <varname>originalSource</varname></title>

    <!-- ben: I must admit, I don't really understand how OriginalSource is supposed to work, but then I've not needed to use it. Perhaps someone else has a more clear vision for its use.-->
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Indicating ownership and use using <varname>rights</varname>
    property</title>

    <para>Identifiable entities are significant enough that users may wish to
    indicate ownership of the copyright of the thing that they represent, or
    to provide some statement of a licence under which that data may be used.
    This information is held in the <varname>rights</varname> element as a
    series of <classname>Right</classname> objects, each representing a single
    rights statement.</para>

    <para>Note that the assertation of rights in the data is not the same as
    access rights in terms of application-level security which is dealt with
    in a <link linkend="security">later section</link>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
