<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
      xml:id="cdm-reference-guide" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>EDIT Common Data Model Library</title>

    <subtitle>Reference Documentation (Work in Progress)</subtitle>

    <corpauthor>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="./resources/images/logo.png" />
    </corpauthor>

    <!-- Please add your names here -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>Ben Clark</personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>2.1</releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>

      <holder>EDIT - European Distributed Institute of Taxonomy -
      http://www.e-taxonomy.eu</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>The contents of this file are subject to the Mozilla Public
      License Version 1.1. See LICENSE.TXT at the top of this package for the
      full license terms.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc />

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>EDIT's Internet Platform for Cybertaxonomy is a distributed
    computing platform that helps taxonomists do revisionary taxonomy and
    taxonomic field work efficiently and expediently via the web. At the core
    of the platform lies a common data model to enable interoperability
    between the different components. The model describes all the commonly
    used data that is dealt with in the platform, and therefore covers
    taxonomic names and concepts; literature references; authors; (type)
    specimen; structured descriptive data; molecular data; related (binary)
    files such as images or compiled keys; controlled vocabularies and terms;
    and species related content of any kind like economic use or conservation
    status.</para>

    <para xlink:href="">The Internet Platform for Cybertaxonomy consists of
    interoperable but independent platform components. Platform components can
    take the form of software applications (desktop or web-based) for human
    users or (web) services. The platform as envisioned does not have a single
    user interface or website; rather, it is a collection of interacting
    components which may be combined and assembled according to the task in
    hand. To facilitate the development of core CDM Applications such as the
    CDM Community Server, the CDM Dataportals, and the Taxonomic Editor, an
    implementation of the CDM has been created in the java programming
    language. In addition to CDM model classes being modelled as
    plain-old-java-objects (<link
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain_Old_Java_Object">pojo's</link>),
    a set of java components has been created that provide common services
    across all java applications using the CDM. In addition to serving as the
    basis of core components of the Internet Platform for Cyberplatform, they
    also allow the development of other applications using the CDM.</para>

    <para>The CDM Library, as it is known, consists of four major modules that
    can be used by any java application based on the CDM. These libraries are
    used as the foundation of the Taxonomic Editor and the CDM Community
    Server. In addition, the CDM Community Server is documented here, as the
    components can be re-purposed or extended by other web applications based
    on the CDM.</para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>Common Data Model</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>Description of the model classes and their use:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="base-classes.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="annotation-and-markers.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="extensions.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="identifiable-entities.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="validation.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Persistence Layer</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part discusses the persistence layer in detail:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="basic-persistence.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="listing-sorting-initializing.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="versioning.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="free-text-search.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>API Methods</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part discusses the service layer:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="service.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="paging-resultsets.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="application-controller.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="transactions.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="guid-resolution.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="security.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>CDM Input / Output Layer</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part describes the input output routines:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="base-io-usage.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="cdm-xml-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="abcd-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="berlinmodel-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="excel-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="sdd-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="taxonx-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="tcsrdf-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="tcsxml-input-output.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>CDM Server</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part describes the cdm-server application:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="cdm-server.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="instalation.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="configuration.xml" />-->
  </part>
</book>
