<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
      xml:id="cdm-reference-guide" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>EDIT Common Data Model Library</title>

    <subtitle>Reference Documentation (Work in Progress)</subtitle>

    <corpauthor>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="./resources/images/logo.png" />
    </corpauthor>

    <!-- Please add your names here -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>Ben Clark</personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>Andreas Müller</personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>2.1</releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>

      <holder>EDIT - European Distributed Institute of Taxonomy -
      http://www.e-taxonomy.eu</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>The contents of this file are subject to the Mozilla Public
      License Version 1.1. See LICENSE.TXT at the top of this package for the
      full license terms.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc />

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>EDIT's Internet Platform for Cybertaxonomy is a distributed
    computing platform that helps taxonomists do revisionary taxonomy and
    taxonomic field work efficiently and expediently via the web. At the core
    of the platform lies a common data model to enable interoperability
    between the different components. The model describes all the commonly
    used data that is dealt with in the platform, and therefore covers
    taxonomic names and concepts; literature references; authors; (type)
    specimen; structured descriptive data; molecular data; related (binary)
    files such as images or compiled keys; controlled vocabularies and terms;
    and species related content of any kind like economic use or conservation
    status.</para>

    <para>The cyberplatform consists of interoperable but independent
    components. Platform components can take the form of software applications
    (desktop or web-based) for human users or (web) services intended to be
    used by other software applications. The platform as envisioned does not
    have a single user interface or website; rather, it is a collection of
    interacting components which may be combined and assembled according to
    the task in hand. To facilitate the development of core CDM Applications
    such as the CDM Community Server, the CDM Dataportals, and the Taxonomic
    Editor, an implementation of the CDM has been created in the java
    programming language. In addition to CDM model classes being modelled as
    plain-old-java-objects (<link
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain_Old_Java_Object">pojo's</link>),
    a set of java components has been created that provide common services
    across all java applications using the CDM. They serve as the basis of
    core components of the Internet Platform for Cyberplatform and also allow
    the development of other applications using the CDM by providing basic
    functionality that can be extended for a particular purpose.</para>

    <para>The CDM Library, as it is known, consists of four major modules that
    can be used by any java application based on the CDM. These libraries are
    used as the foundation of the Taxonomic Editor and the CDM Community
    Server. In addition a web application (the CDM Community Server) is
    documented here, as its components can be re-purposed or extended by other
    web applications based on the CDM.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>An overview of the main CDM Components</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/cdmlib-arch3.png" format="png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata contentwidth="160mm"
                     fileref="resources/images/cdmlib-arch3.png" format="png"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>The overall architecture of the EDIT Internet platform for
        Cybertaxonomy, showing the core components of the CDM Java Library,
        and their use by desktop (Taxonomic Editor) and web-based (CDM
        Dataportal, CATE) applications.</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This reference documentation is aimed at anyone who would like to
    understand the software components that make up the core of the
    cyberplatform: the CDM Java Library and the CDM Server application. More
    generic information about the applications that make up the cyberplatform,
    information for end-users of specific applications, and information on the
    EDIT project itself are beyond the scope of this document. More
    information about EDIT can be found on the <link linkend="???">EDIT
    website</link>, and more information on the specific software applications
    produced by EDIT can be found on the <link linkend="???">Work Package 5
    website</link>.</para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part of the reference documentation aims to provide simple
      step-by-step instructions to enable application developers to start
      using the CDM Java Library in their java application. To do this, we
      will create a small toy application. The CDM Java Library is packaged
      and published using the Apache Maven software project managment and
      comprehension tool. To make life easier, we'll use maven to create our
      application too. Assuming that Maven (2.0.x+) installed, we begin by
      creating a new maven application (substituting the group id, artifact
      id, and version of our application):</para>

      <screen>mvn archetype:create -DgroupId=<emphasis>org.myproject</emphasis> -DartifactId=<emphasis>myapp</emphasis> -Dversion=<emphasis>1.0</emphasis></screen>

      <para>The next step is to add the EDIT maven repository to your maven
      <emphasis>project object model</emphasis> or <emphasis>pom</emphasis>
      file, thus:</para>

      <programlisting>. . .
&lt;repositories&gt;
  &lt;repository&gt;
    &lt;id&gt;EditRepository&lt;/id&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://wp5.e-taxonomy.eu/cdmlib/mavenrepo/&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/repository&gt;
&lt;/repositories&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>We also need to add the specific dependency that we would like our
      project to include.</para>

      <programlisting>. . .
&lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;eu.etaxonomy&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;cdmlib-services&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.1.1&lt;/version&gt;<!--ben: We will need to change this to reflect the new release once it is available-->
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
&lt;repositories&gt;
. . .</programlisting>

      <para>In most cases, application developers will wish to include the
      cdmlib services (which include the data model and persistence layer
      too). In some cases, developers might wish to use components from the
      <package>cdmlib-io</package> and <package>cdmlib-remote</package>
      packages too. New releases of the CDM Java Library are published in the
      EDIT Maven Repository, and maven will download and use these artifacts
      automatically if you change the version number of the dependency
      specified in your pom file.</para>

      <para>All that remains is to set up the cdmlib services within the
      application context. The CDM Java Library is uses the Spring Framework
      to manage its components. Whilst it is not mandatory to wire the CDM
      services and DAOs using Spring, it is certainly easier to configure your
      application this way. A minimal applicationContext.xml (placed in
      <filename>src/main/resources</filename>) file might look like
      this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;import resource="classpath:/eu/etaxonomy/cdm/services.xml" /&gt;

&lt;bean id="dataSource" 
  lazy-init="true"
  class="eu.etaxonomy.cdm.database.LocalHsqldb" 	
  init-method="init"
  destroy-method="destroy"&gt;
  &lt;property name="driverClassName" value="org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="username" value="sa"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="password" value=""/&gt;
  &lt;property name="startServer" value="true"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="silent" value="true"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
    
&lt;bean id="hibernateProperties" 
  class="org.springframework.beans.factory.config.PropertiesFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="properties"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="hibernate.hbm2ddl.auto"&gt;create-drop&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="hibernate.dialect"&gt;org.hibernate.dialect.HSQLDialect&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="hibernate.cache.provider_class"&gt;org.hibernate.cache.NoCacheProvider&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The first element imports the cdmlib service definitions. The two
      other beans supply a data source and a properties object that the CDM
      library uses to configure the hibernate session factory and connect to
      the database. In this case, we're using an in-memory HSQL database, but
      the CDM can be used with many other databases. The only thing left to do
      is to start using the CDM services. In real applications, CDM services
      may well be autowired into components using Spring or another dependency
      injection mechanism. To keep this example simple, we'll initialize the
      application context and obtain a service programatically.</para>

      <programlisting>ApplicationContext context = new ClassPathXmlApplicationContext("applicationContext.xml");

INameService nameService = (INameService)context.getBean("nameServiceImpl");

BotanicalName botanicalName = BotanicalName.NewInstance(Rank.SPECIES());
botanicalName.setGenusOrUninomial("Arum");
botanicalName.setSpecificEpithet("maculatum");
UUID uuid = nameService.saveTaxonName(botanicalName);<!--ben: Again, this example reflects the 1.1.1 release, and will need to be changed slightly once the new release is available-->

System.out.println("Saved \'Arum maculatum\' under uuid " + uuid.toString());</programlisting>

      <para>In this simple example, we've covered the basics of using the CDM
      Java Library. We created a simple maven project, and added the
      repository and a single dependency to our pom file. We then created a
      simple application context that used the default CDM configuration, and
      specified a couple of objects that allowed the CDM to connect to a
      database. Finally we initialized these services by loading the
      application context, and then retrieved a specific service, and used it
      to persist a new taxonomic name.</para>
    </partintro>
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Common Data Model</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>The Common Data Model (CDM) is the domain model for the core EDIT
      cyberplatform components. The CDM is primarily based on the <link
      linkend="???"
      xlink:href="http://wiki.tdwg.org/twiki/bin/view/TAG/LsidVocs">TDWG
      Ontology</link> and in most cases there is concordance with relevant
      TDWG standards such as <link linkend="???"
      xlink:href="http://www.tdwg.org/standards/117/">Taxon Concept Transfer
      Schema (TCS)</link>, <link linkend="???"
      xlink:href="http://www.tdwg.org/standards/117/">Structured Descriptive
      Data (SDD)</link> and <link linkend="???"
      xlink:href="http://www.tdwg.org/standards/115/">Access to Biological
      Collections Data (ABCD)</link>.</para>

      <para>The CDM differs from the TDWG standards in its purpose: it is
      intended to serve as the basis of software applications in the
      cyberplatform (e.g. the taxonomic editor, the CDM Dataportals) rather
      than being a standard for data exchange between any resource containing
      biodiversity information. Whilst it is certainly possible to exchange
      data as CDM domain objects serialized as XML or JSON (the CDM Server and
      the CDM Dataportals do this), the common data model is not intended to
      replace existing TDWG standards as a general purpose exchange standard.
      It is possible to convert data held in a CDM store into a relevant TDWG
      standard for exchange and in some cases this may be the desired route
      for data held in the CDM (e.g. for exchange with an application that is
      not part of the cyberplatform, but which is capable of understanding
      data in a TDWG standard).</para>

      <para>Thus the CDM is intended for use as</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A domain model for applications, particularly those that
          enable taxonomists to do revisionary taxonomy and taxonomic field
          work</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A standard for exchange between applications that are part of
          the EDIT Internet Platform for Cybertaxonomy</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In terms of scope, the CDM covers information core to the vision
      of the cyberplatform i.e. descriptive and revisionary taxonomy,
      including taxonomic fieldwork :-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Taxonomic names and nomenclature, typification</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Taxonomic concepts and relationships between accepted names
          and synonyms, including the placement of the same taxonomic concept
          in different taxonomic hierarchies.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Specimens and Observations of individual organisms, their
          collection, location, processing and taxonomic determination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Structured and unstructured information about names, taxa, and
          specimens.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In addition to this core area, the CDM covers some related domains
      that are important:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Literature</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>People, teams of people and institutions in various roles
          (i.e. as authors, collectors, artists, rights holders etc)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Media (images, video and audio files, plus more
          taxonomy-specific media such as phylogenies and compiled
          keys)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Molecular data, such as DNA sequences and loci</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As you might expect, there are also a number of data entities
      representing controlled vocabularies, identity of users (and their roles
      and permissions), and ancillary data common to all major classes such as
      multilingual text content, annotations and markers.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>A UML Package diagram showing the CDM packages and their
        members.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/ModelOverview20.gif" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata contentwidth="160mm"
                       fileref="resources/images/ModelOverview20.gif"
                       scalefit="1" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="base-classes.xml" />

    <xi:include href="annotation-and-markers.xml" />

    <!--<xi:include href="extensions.xml" />-->

    <xi:include href="identifiable-entities.xml" />

    <!--
      ben: I think that some explaination of how the CDM deals with core
      data classes, would be really useful here. In some cases, we're still
      trying to understand how it should work and in that case it might
      still be useful to have a straw-man that people can disagree with or
      improve.
      -->

    <!--<xi:include href="taxonomic-names.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="taxonomic-concepts.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="specimens-and-observations.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="descriptive-data.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="terms-and-vocabularies.xml" />-->

    <!-- ben: We'll need to touch on _where_ these external files live . . .-->

    <!--<xi:include href="media.xml" />-->

    <!-- ben: I'll include something about validation once I start 
              work on the validation framework next month
      -->

    <!--<xi:include href="validation.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Persistence Layer</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>Even the most basic of taxonomic applications have a requirement
      for users to be able to save the information that they create. In
      addition, a common component of taxonomic applications is the use of a
      database to provide users with the ability to filter or search their
      data in one way or another. Some applications will require more advanced
      functionality, such as auditing or versioning of data. All of this logic
      is contained in the persistence layer, providing clean separation
      between data access and more taxonomy-centric business logic in the
      service layer.</para>

      <para>Persistence is not a simple problem to solve, especially in
      application developed in Object-Oriented languages, with large amounts
      of data, or with many users accessing data at the same time. The CDM
      Library uses the <link
      xlink:href="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</link> object/relational
      persistence and query service as the basis of its persistence layer.
      Several member projects of the Hibernate stable, including <link
      xlink:href="http://annotations.hibernate.org">Hibernate
      Annotations</link>, <link
      xlink:href="http://search.hibernate.org">Hibernate Search</link> and
      <link linkend="http://jboss.org/envers/">Hibernate Envers</link> (part
      of Hibernate Core) provide the basis of the more advanced
      persistence-related functionality in the CDM Library. As a consequence
      some of the behaviour of the CDM Library is constrained by the
      underlying ORM technology. The advantage of using an ORM is that the
      same software can be used with multiple database systems with (almost)
      no changes to the application. Currently the CDM Library has been tested
      with (version numbers &amp; platforms in brackets)</para>

      <!--I don't know how many of these have been tested, on which platforms, but it would be good to include some measure of which platform / database combinations 
have been used and how, so that potential users can evaluate the technology. In an ideal world, we would pick some databases as "supported" and ensure that
the test suite runs on that platform / db combination (i.e. you don't release until the tests pass). For the others, we still might want to say: "We tested 
the CDM on this platform and it seemed to work".-->

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>IBM <link
          xlink:href="http://www.ibm.com/software/data/db2/">DB2</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="???">H2</link> (default local database used
          by the Taxonomic Editor, 1.0.73)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://hsqldb.org">HSQLDB</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com">MySQL</link> (4.1.20:
          linux; 5.1.32: windows)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="???">ODBC</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link
            xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/database/index.html">Oracle
            Database 11<emphasis>g</emphasis></link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="???">Microsoft SQL Server 2000</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="???"
            xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2005/">Microsoft
            SQL Server 2005</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="???" xlink:href="http://www.sybase.co.uk/">Sybase
            Advantage Database Server</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In theory, application developers should not need to use the
      persistence layer directly, but should instead use the <link
      linkend="api">API</link>, which provides a <emphasis>facade</emphasis>
      over the persistence layer and extra business logic that most
      applications using the CDM will require.</para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="basic-persistence.xml" />

    <xi:include href="versioning.xml" />

    <xi:include href="free-text-search.xml" />
  </part>

  <part xml:id="api">
    <title>API Methods</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>Apart from the Common Data Model classes themselves, the CDM
      Service layer contains the components most likely to be used directly by
      applications based upon the CDM Java Library. This layer contains a set
      of basic service objects that can be used as a facade over the
      persistence logic.</para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="service.xml" />

    <!--<xi:include href="application-controller.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="transactions.xml" />-->

    <xi:include href="guid-resolution.xml" />

    <xi:include href="security.xml" />
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>CDM Input / Output Layer</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part describes the input output routines:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="base-io-usage.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="cdm-xml-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="abcd-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="berlinmodel-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="excel-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="sdd-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="taxonx-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="tcsrdf-input-output.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="tcsxml-input-output.xml" />-->
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>CDM Server</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>This part describes the cdm-server application:</para>
    </partintro>

    <!--<xi:include href="cdm-server.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="instalation.xml" />-->

    <!--<xi:include href="configuration.xml" />-->
  </part>
</book>
